<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sbomify</title><link>https://sbomify.com/tags/compliance/</link><description>Your Security Artifact Hub. From zero to SBOM hero. Generate, manage, and share SBOMs and compliance documents. Built for CRA compliance and seamless integration with your existing tools.</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sbomify.com/tags/compliance/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Announcing sbomify v0.26: The One Where Bootstrap Moved Out</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/02/16/announcing-sbomify-v0-26-the-one-where-bootstrap-moved-out/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/02/16/announcing-sbomify-v0-26-the-one-where-bootstrap-moved-out/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="a-faster-more-accessible-ui">A Faster, More Accessible UI&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The first thing you will notice is that &lt;strong>sbomify feels faster&lt;/strong>. Pages load more quickly, transitions are smoother, and the interface is more consistent throughout the application. Dark mode now works reliably across every page, and accessibility has been improved with better contrast ratios, keyboard navigation, and screen reader support.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Under the hood, we rebuilt the entire frontend from scratch. But what matters to you is the result: a cleaner, more polished experience that gets out of your way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We have also redesigned the &lt;strong>onboarding wizard&lt;/strong>. New users can now get from sign-up to their first SBOM upload in fewer steps, with clearer guidance at each stage.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="real-time-dashboard-updates">Real-Time Dashboard Updates&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Until now, checking whether an assessment finished or a new SBOM was uploaded meant manually refreshing the page. That changes with v0.26.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Your dashboard now updates in &lt;strong>real-time&lt;/strong>. When a teammate uploads an SBOM, a compliance assessment completes, or a component status changes, you see it immediately. No more guessing, no more stale data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From your perspective, it just works.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="bsi-tr-03183-2-compliance">BSI TR-03183-2 Compliance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you operate in Germany or sell into the German market, sbomify now supports automated compliance checking against &lt;strong>BSI TR-03183-2&lt;/strong> — the German Federal Office for Information Security&amp;rsquo;s technical guideline for SBOM quality and completeness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like our other compliance plugins, you can enable it in &lt;strong>Settings -&amp;gt; Plugins&lt;/strong>. Once enabled, every SBOM upload is assessed automatically against the BSI requirements.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This plugin also introduces a &lt;strong>dependency system&lt;/strong> for compliance plugins. Plugins can now build on each other, so related standards share foundational checks rather than duplicating work. This means more consistent results across overlapping compliance frameworks.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="gdpr-self-service-account-deletion">GDPR Self-Service Account Deletion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Under GDPR, you have the right to delete your account and all associated data. Previously, this required contacting our support team and waiting for manual processing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With v0.26, you can &lt;strong>delete your own account&lt;/strong> directly from your profile settings. No tickets, no waiting. Your data is removed in accordance with our data retention policy.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="fine-grained-access-control">Fine-Grained Access Control&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>You can now control who sees what at a more granular level. Set &lt;strong>component visibility&lt;/strong> to restrict which components are visible to which roles, and control &lt;strong>document-level access&lt;/strong> to limit who can view specific SBOM documents.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is particularly useful for organizations sharing SBOMs externally through the &lt;strong>Trust Center&lt;/strong>. You can make some components public for customers and partners while keeping internal components private — all from the same workspace.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="other-improvements">Other Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Version field on Releases&lt;/strong> — You can now track release versions aligned with the Transparency Exchange API (TEA), making it easier to correlate SBOMs with specific product versions.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improved error tracking&lt;/strong> — We catch and resolve issues faster now, often before you notice them.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Custom login experience&lt;/strong> — The login page now uses a branded sbomify theme with better password validation feedback, so you know exactly what is needed when setting or changing your password.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Zero-downtime deployments&lt;/strong> — Deployments no longer cause brief interruptions. Updates happen seamlessly in the background, so the platform is always available.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="bug-fixes">Bug Fixes&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Fixed an issue where compliance assessments could fail on retry.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed IP address capture in NDA audit trails.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Improved error responses for duplicate SBOM uploads — the API response now includes an error code for easier debugging in CI/CD pipelines.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="infrastructure">Infrastructure&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>For self-hosted users, note that sbomify v0.26 now requires &lt;strong>Python 3.13&lt;/strong>. We have also updated several key dependencies, including gunicorn 25.x, ruff 0.15.x, and bandit 1.9.3. Check the full changelog for upgrade notes before updating your deployment.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you are on the &lt;strong>hosted platform&lt;/strong>, everything is already live — no action needed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For &lt;strong>self-hosted&lt;/strong> deployments, update to v0.26.0 by pulling the latest release.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/compare/v0.25.1...v0.26.0">full changelog on GitHub&lt;/a> for complete details. We would love to hear your feedback — reach out via &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/issues">GitHub Issues&lt;/a> or our community channels.&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item><item><title>The Role of SBOMs in Cybersecurity: From Visibility to Vulnerability Response</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/02/08/sbom-cybersecurity-role/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/02/08/sbom-cybersecurity-role/</guid><description>&lt;p>A &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/what-is-sbom/">Software Bill of Materials&lt;/a> (SBOM) is a foundational cybersecurity tool that provides a complete, machine-readable inventory of every component in a software product. In cybersecurity, SBOMs answer the question that every security team must be able to answer: &lt;em>what is in our software?&lt;/em> Without this visibility, vulnerability management, incident response, and compliance are all reactive at best and impossible at worst.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-sboms-matter-for-cybersecurity">Why SBOMs Matter for Cybersecurity&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Modern software is assembled from open source and third-party components. A typical application consists of &lt;a href="https://www.linux.com/training-tutorials/estimating-total-number-linux-contributors-approach-using-linus-law/">70-90% open source code&lt;/a> drawn from package registries. Each component is a potential entry point for attackers — whether through known vulnerabilities, compromised packages, or abandoned libraries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>SBOMs make the composition of software visible. This visibility is the prerequisite for every other cybersecurity activity involving third-party code: you cannot patch what you do not know you are running.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sboms-and-vulnerability-management">SBOMs and Vulnerability Management&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Vulnerability management is the cybersecurity function that benefits most directly from SBOMs. The workflow connects component inventories to threat intelligence, creating a continuous monitoring capability.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-problem-without-sboms">The Problem Without SBOMs&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When a new &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2025/12/18/cve-vulnerability-explained/">CVE&lt;/a> is disclosed, organizations without SBOMs must:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Manually determine which components are used across all applications&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Check each application&amp;rsquo;s dependency files (if accessible)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Search container images, build artifacts, and deployment manifests&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Aggregate findings across teams and environments&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>This manual process can take days or weeks. During that time, the vulnerability may be actively exploited.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-solution-with-sboms">The Solution With SBOMs&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>With SBOMs generated and ingested into a management platform like &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com">sbomify&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://dependencytrack.org/">OWASP Dependency-Track&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>New CVE is published to vulnerability databases&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Platform automatically matches the CVE to SBOM component inventories&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Affected products and versions are identified within seconds&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Alerts are sent to the responsible teams&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Remediation begins immediately&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>This automated approach reduces the response window from days to minutes. The difference is especially critical for vulnerabilities listed in the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2025/12/30/what-is-kev-cisa-known-exploited-vulnerabilities/">CISA KEV catalog&lt;/a> — those confirmed to be actively exploited in the wild.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="incident-response-the-log4shell-case-study">Incident Response: The Log4Shell Case Study&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Log4Shell vulnerability (&lt;a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/CVE-2021-44228">CVE-2021-44228&lt;/a>) in December 2021 is the defining example of why SBOMs matter for cybersecurity. Apache Log4j was a ubiquitous Java logging library used as both a direct and transitive &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/29/what-is-a-dependency-in-software/">dependency&lt;/a> in millions of applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Organizations with SBOMs&lt;/strong> queried their component inventories and identified affected systems within minutes. They knew exactly which applications used Log4j, at which versions, and in which environments.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Organizations without SBOMs&lt;/strong> spent weeks manually auditing codebases, scanning containers, and contacting vendors to determine exposure. Some discovered Log4j in applications they did not even know existed in their environment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Log4Shell became the single most cited argument for SBOM adoption. It demonstrated that in a crisis, the ability to answer &amp;ldquo;which of our systems are affected?&amp;rdquo; is not optional — it is a core cybersecurity capability.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sboms-and-the-compliance-landscape">SBOMs and the Compliance Landscape&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Multiple cybersecurity regulations and frameworks now require or strongly recommend SBOMs. This reflects the growing consensus that software transparency is essential for security.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="united-states">United States&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eo-14028/">Executive Order 14028&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> (&amp;ldquo;Improving the Nation&amp;rsquo;s Cybersecurity&amp;rdquo;, 2021) directed federal agencies to require SBOMs from software vendors. It established SBOMs as a baseline expectation for government software procurement.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/cisa-minimum-elements/">CISA Minimum Elements&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> defines the recommended fields for SBOMs, building on the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/ntia-minimum-elements/">NTIA minimum elements&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/nist-800-53/">NIST SP 800-53&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> includes supply chain risk management controls (SR family) that SBOMs help satisfy, particularly SR-4 (Provenance) and CM-8 (Component Inventory).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/nist-800-171/">NIST SP 800-171&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> (Rev 3) added a Supply Chain Risk Management family (03.17) relevant to DoD contractors handling Controlled Unclassified Information.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/fda-medical-device/">FDA Medical Device Guidance&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> requires SBOMs for medical device premarket submissions.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="european-union">European Union&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eu-cra/">EU Cyber Resilience Act&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> (CRA) requires manufacturers of products with digital elements to identify and document components, with SBOMs as the practical mechanism.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eu-nis2/">NIS2 Directive&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> requires supply chain security measures for essential and important entities.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="industry-standards">Industry Standards&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/pci-dss/">PCI DSS 4.0&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> requires maintaining an inventory of third-party software components for payment card environments.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>For a complete comparison of compliance frameworks, see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/">compliance overview&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sboms-across-the-cybersecurity-lifecycle">SBOMs Across the Cybersecurity Lifecycle&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>SBOMs support cybersecurity at every stage:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="prevention">Prevention&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dependency auditing.&lt;/strong> SBOMs reveal the full dependency tree including &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/29/what-is-a-dependency-in-software/">transitive dependencies&lt;/a>, enabling teams to identify and replace risky components before deployment.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>License compliance.&lt;/strong> SBOMs document the license of every component, preventing license conflicts that can create legal exposure. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2025/12/22/gpl-license-guide/">GPL&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/22/mit-license-guide/">MIT&lt;/a>, and &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/07/apache-license-2-guide/">Apache 2.0&lt;/a> guides for license-specific details.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Policy enforcement.&lt;/strong> SBOM-based tools can block deployments that include components with known critical vulnerabilities or prohibited licenses.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="detection">Detection&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Continuous vulnerability monitoring.&lt;/strong> SBOMs ingested into platforms like OWASP Dependency-Track are continuously matched against the &lt;a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/">NVD&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://osv.dev/">OSV&lt;/a>, and &lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/known-exploited-vulnerabilities-catalog">CISA KEV catalog&lt;/a>. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/02/01/sbom-scanning-vulnerability-detection/">SBOM scanning guide&lt;/a> for implementation details.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/02/05/what-is-cvss-vulnerability-scoring/">CVSS&lt;/a>-based triage.&lt;/strong> SBOMs paired with vulnerability data enable automated severity assessment, prioritizing critical and high-severity issues.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="response">Response&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Rapid impact assessment.&lt;/strong> Query SBOM repositories to immediately identify which products and environments contain an affected component.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Targeted remediation.&lt;/strong> Knowing exactly where a vulnerable component is deployed enables precise patching rather than broad emergency measures.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>VEX communication.&lt;/strong> Use Vulnerability Exploitability eXchange (VEX) documents to communicate whether a reported vulnerability actually affects your product.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="recovery">Recovery&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Audit trail.&lt;/strong> Retained SBOMs provide a historical record of what was deployed at any point in time, supporting post-incident analysis and regulatory reporting.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Rebuild verification.&lt;/strong> SBOMs document the components that should be present, enabling verification that rebuilt or patched software matches the intended composition.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you are beginning your SBOM journey:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Start generating SBOMs.&lt;/strong> Use our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/">language-specific SBOM guides&lt;/a> to generate SBOMs for your projects in &lt;a href="https://cyclonedx.org/">CycloneDX&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://spdx.dev/">SPDX&lt;/a> format. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/15/sbom-formats-cyclonedx-vs-spdx/">SBOM formats comparison&lt;/a> for format guidance.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Automate generation in CI/CD.&lt;/strong> Integrate SBOM generation into your build pipeline using the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action/">sbomify GitHub Action&lt;/a>, which handles generation, enrichment, and augmentation in one step. Standalone tools like &lt;a href="https://github.com/anchore/syft">Syft&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/aquasecurity/trivy">Trivy&lt;/a> are also available. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/26/sbom-generation-tools-comparison/">SBOM generation tools comparison&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Set up vulnerability monitoring.&lt;/strong> Use &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com">sbomify&lt;/a> for integrated monitoring (built-in OSV and Dependency-Track scanning), or deploy a standalone &lt;a href="https://dependencytrack.org/">OWASP Dependency-Track&lt;/a> instance for continuous monitoring.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Establish a management process.&lt;/strong> Define how SBOMs are stored, versioned, and distributed. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/18/sbom-management-best-practices/">SBOM management guide&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Map to compliance requirements.&lt;/strong> Identify which compliance frameworks apply to your organization and ensure your SBOM process meets their requirements. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/">compliance overview&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>For a comprehensive list of tools across the SBOM lifecycle, see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/resources/">resources page&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="frequently-asked-questions">Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="how-do-sboms-improve-cybersecurity">How do SBOMs improve cybersecurity?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SBOMs improve cybersecurity by providing component-level visibility into software. This visibility enables automated vulnerability detection (matching components against CVE databases), rapid incident response (immediately identifying affected systems when a new vulnerability is disclosed), continuous compliance monitoring (tracking regulatory requirements), and informed risk management (understanding the full dependency chain and its associated risks).&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="are-sboms-required-for-cybersecurity-compliance">Are SBOMs required for cybersecurity compliance?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SBOMs are required or strongly recommended by multiple frameworks: U.S. Executive Order 14028 requires them for federal software procurement, the EU Cyber Resilience Act requires them for products with digital elements, FDA guidance requires them for medical device submissions, and NIST SP 800-53/800-171 include supply chain controls that SBOMs help satisfy. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/">compliance overview&lt;/a> for a framework-by-framework breakdown.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="how-did-log4shell-demonstrate-the-need-for-sboms">How did Log4Shell demonstrate the need for SBOMs?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When the Log4Shell vulnerability (CVE-2021-44228) was disclosed in December 2021, organizations with SBOMs identified affected systems in minutes by querying their component inventories. Organizations without SBOMs spent weeks manually auditing codebases and scanning infrastructure. This stark contrast made Log4Shell the most commonly cited example of why SBOMs are essential for cybersecurity incident response.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-the-relationship-between-sboms-and-vulnerability-management">What is the relationship between SBOMs and vulnerability management?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SBOMs provide the component inventory that vulnerability management depends on. Without knowing what components are in your software, you cannot determine which vulnerabilities affect you. SBOMs ingested into monitoring platforms are continuously matched against vulnerability databases, enabling automated detection and alerting. This transforms vulnerability management from a periodic manual exercise into a continuous automated process.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="how-do-i-start-using-sboms-for-cybersecurity">How do I start using SBOMs for cybersecurity?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Start by generating SBOMs for your applications using tools like Syft, Trivy, or language-specific generators. Automate generation in your CI/CD pipeline. Ingest SBOMs into a monitoring platform like OWASP Dependency-Track for continuous vulnerability scanning. Define remediation SLAs based on CVSS severity and KEV status. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/">SBOM guides&lt;/a> for step-by-step instructions.&lt;/p></description><category>education</category></item><item><title>Announcing sbomify-action v0.13: The One Where We Go to FOSDEM</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/02/04/announcing-sbomify-action-v0-13-the-one-where-we-go-to-fosdem/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/02/04/announcing-sbomify-action-v0-13-the-one-where-we-go-to-fosdem/</guid><description>&lt;p>We timed the sbomify-action v0.13 release for &lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2026/schedule/event/UYTGWA-sbom-generation/">FOSDEM 2026&lt;/a>, where we presented on CRA-ready SBOM generation.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="fosdem-2026-cra-ready-sboms">FOSDEM 2026: CRA-Ready SBOMs&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This past weekend, we presented at FOSDEM in the Software Bill of Materials devroom. The talk covers a four-phase SBOM generation model addressing the EU&amp;rsquo;s Cyber Resilience Act requirements: authoring, augmenting, enriching, and signing SBOMs to exceed minimal compliance standards. It includes a demo of an open-source workflow using sbomify-action, helping teams avoid compliance gaps as the CRA timeline approaches.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you missed it, you can watch the full talk below.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="video-embed-wrapper my-8 w-full max-w-3xl mx-auto">
&lt;div class="relative w-full overflow-hidden rounded-xl sm:rounded-2xl shadow-lg" style="padding-bottom: 56.25%;">
&lt;video
class="absolute top-0 left-0 w-full h-full border-0 bg-black"
controls
preload="metadata"
title="CRA-Ready SBOMs: A Practical Blueprint for High-Quality Generation">
&lt;source src="https://video.fosdem.org/2026/ud2208/UYTGWA-sbom-generation.av1.webm" type="video/webm">
Your browser does not support the video tag.
&lt;/video>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;script type="application/ld+json">
{
"@context": "https://schema.org",
"@type": "VideoObject",
"name": "CRA-Ready SBOMs: A Practical Blueprint for High-Quality Generation",
"description": "A four-phase SBOM generation model addressing the EU\u0026#39;s Cyber Resilience Act requirements, covering authoring, augmenting, enriching, and signing SBOMs.",
"uploadDate": "2026-02-04T00:00:00Z",
"contentUrl": "https:\/\/video.fosdem.org\/2026\/ud2208\/UYTGWA-sbom-generation.av1.webm"
}
&lt;/script>
&lt;p>You can also find the talk on the &lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2026/schedule/event/UYTGWA-sbom-generation/">FOSDEM schedule&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="whats-new-in-v013">What&amp;rsquo;s New in v0.13&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="breaking-changes">Breaking Changes&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Python 3.11+ now required&lt;/strong> - We have increased the minimum Python version from 3.10 to 3.11 to take advantage of the built-in &lt;code>tomllib&lt;/code> module for TOML parsing. If you are running sbomify-action locally, ensure you have Python 3.11 or later installed.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="new-features">New Features&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="hash-enrichment-from-lockfiles">Hash Enrichment from Lockfiles&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>A common gap in SBOMs is missing cryptographic hashes for components. Many SBOM generation tools do not extract hashes, even when they are available in lockfiles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The new hash enrichment subsystem automatically extracts cryptographic hashes from your lockfiles and adds them to SBOM components. This improves SBOM quality and supports integrity verification workflows.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Supported lockfiles:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Cargo.lock (Rust)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>package-lock.json (npm)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pipfile.lock (Pipenv)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>pnpm-lock.yaml (pnpm)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>poetry.lock (Poetry)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>pubspec.lock (Dart/Flutter)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>uv.lock (uv)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>yarn.lock (Yarn)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="interactive-configuration-wizard">Interactive Configuration Wizard&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Getting started with sbomify-action is now easier than ever. The new &lt;code>sbomify init&lt;/code> command walks you through an interactive wizard to create your &lt;code>sbomify.json&lt;/code> configuration file. Answer a few questions about your project, and the wizard generates a working configuration.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>sbomify-action init
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;h3 id="conan-center-enrichment">Conan Center Enrichment&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>C/C++ projects using Conan now get automatic metadata enrichment from the Conan Center API. For each package, we fetch:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>License information&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Author details&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Homepage URL&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Repository URL&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Package description&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This follows our enrichment-first philosophy: even if your SBOM generation tool produces sparse output, sbomify-action fills in the gaps from authoritative sources.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="component-supplier-field-ntia-compliance">Component Supplier Field (NTIA Compliance)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>NTIA&amp;rsquo;s minimum elements for SBOMs include supplier information. Previously, some tools would populate this with package authors, which is not quite right. The supplier should be the distribution platform, not the individual who wrote the code.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Components now include a &lt;code>supplier&lt;/code> field populated with the distribution platform:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>PyPI for Python packages&lt;/li>
&lt;li>npm for JavaScript packages&lt;/li>
&lt;li>crates.io for Rust packages&lt;/li>
&lt;li>And so on for other ecosystems&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This improves compliance with NTIA SBOM requirements.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="purl-generation-from-vcs-url">PURL Generation from VCS URL&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For SPDX SBOMs, the main package component now generates a PURL from the VCS (Version Control System) URL when no explicit PURL is available. This ensures better NTIA compliance by providing a unique identifier for your software, even when traditional package manager PURLs are not applicable.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="organization-data-from-contact-profile-api">Organization Data from Contact Profile API&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The sbomify API integration now extracts organizational data from the contact_profile structure. This means your SBOMs can include accurate manufacturer and supplier organization details from your sbomify account settings.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="improvements">Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="lifecycle-property-standardization">Lifecycle Property Standardization&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We have updated lifecycle properties to use the official CycloneDX taxonomy. If you are using lifecycle data in your SBOMs, the property names have changed:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Old Property&lt;/th>
&lt;th>New Property&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;code>cle:releaseDate&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>cdx:lifecycle:milestone:generalAvailability&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;code>cle:eos&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>cdx:lifecycle:milestone:endOfSupport&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;code>cle:eol&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>cdx:lifecycle:milestone:endOfLife&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>This aligns with the CycloneDX specification and improves interoperability with other tools.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="better-error-handling">Better Error Handling&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We have made significant improvements to error handling throughout the tool:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>ToolNotAvailableError&lt;/strong> - Graceful handling when SBOM generation tools are missing, with clear instructions on what to install&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improved &amp;ldquo;component not found&amp;rdquo; messages&lt;/strong> - More context about what failed and why&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Better diagnostic info&lt;/strong> - SBOM generation errors now include more details for debugging&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Path expansion errors&lt;/strong> - Now include the file name and searched paths&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CLI flag detection&lt;/strong> - Helpful error when a file path looks like a CLI flag (a common typo)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Stdout capture&lt;/strong> - Tools that output errors to stdout instead of stderr are now handled correctly&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Install from PyPI:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>pip install sbomify-action
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Or use the GitHub Action:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-yaml" data-lang="yaml">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>- &lt;span style="color:#f92672">uses&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">sbomify/github-action@v0.13&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Check out the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action/compare/v0.12...v0.13">full changelog on GitHub&lt;/a> for complete details.&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item><item><title>Announcing sbomify v0.25: The One with Attestations</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/23/announcing-sbomify-v0-25-the-one-with-attestations/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/23/announcing-sbomify-v0-25-the-one-with-attestations/</guid><description>&lt;p>Software supply chain security is not just about knowing what is in your software. It is about proving that knowledge is authentic and has not been tampered with. With v0.25, sbomify takes a significant step forward by introducing &lt;strong>attestation verification&lt;/strong>, allowing you to cryptographically verify the provenance of your SBOMs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="github-attestation-plugin">GitHub Attestation Plugin&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The headline feature of v0.25 is our new &lt;strong>GitHub Attestation Plugin&lt;/strong>. This plugin verifies SBOM attestations using &lt;a href="https://www.sigstore.dev/">Sigstore&lt;/a> and cosign, the same infrastructure that powers supply chain security across the open source ecosystem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When you generate an SBOM using GitHub Actions, you can sign it using GitHub&amp;rsquo;s built-in attestation capability. The sbomify GitHub Attestation Plugin then verifies these signatures automatically when you upload your SBOM. If the attestation is valid, you get cryptographic proof that the SBOM was generated by your CI/CD pipeline and has not been modified since.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The plugin includes automatic retry logic to handle transient network issues when communicating with the Sigstore transparency log. This ensures reliable verification even under less-than-ideal network conditions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is our first attestation plugin, building on the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/blob/master/docs/ADR/ADR-003.md">plugin architecture&lt;/a> we introduced in v0.24. We plan to add support for additional attestation formats including in-toto in future releases.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="spdx-23-export">SPDX 2.3 Export&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>sbomify has supported uploading SBOMs in both CycloneDX and SPDX formats for a while. With v0.25, we are adding the ability to &lt;strong>download aggregated SBOMs in SPDX 2.3 format&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can now download aggregated SBOMs for releases, projects, and products in either CycloneDX or SPDX format directly from the UI. This gives you flexibility when working with tools and partners that prefer one format over the other. Internally, we continue to use CycloneDX as our canonical format, but the SPDX export ensures you can meet requirements regardless of which standard your ecosystem uses.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="product-lifecycle-management">Product Lifecycle Management&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Knowing when your software reaches end-of-support or end-of-life is critical for compliance and vulnerability management. v0.25 introduces &lt;strong>Product Lifecycle&lt;/strong> fields aligned with the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/cle/">CLE (Common Lifecycle Enumeration)&lt;/a> standard that let you track:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Release Date&lt;/strong> - When the product version was released&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>End-of-Support Date&lt;/strong> - When active support ends&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>End-of-Life Date&lt;/strong> - When all support, including security updates, ends&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>You can set these dates manually in the UI for both &lt;strong>products&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>components&lt;/strong>. This is useful for tracking your own release schedules and support commitments.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For common Linux distributions and frameworks, lifecycle data can also be added automatically. The &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/blog/2026/01/20/announcing-sbomify-action-v0-11-the-one-where-they-go-to-pypi/#know-when-your-software-goes-end-of-life">Lifecycle Database&lt;/a> in sbomify-action embeds CLE data directly into your SBOMs during generation. This covers distributions like Ubuntu, Debian, Alpine, and Fedora, as well as language runtimes and frameworks including Python, Go, Django, Rails, and React.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These dates flow through to your Trust Center and can be displayed on public product pages. For organizations subject to regulations like the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eu-cra/">EU Cyber Resilience Act&lt;/a>, tracking lifecycle information is a requirement.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="contact-role-flags">Contact Role Flags&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Building on the contact profile improvements from v0.24, this release adds &lt;strong>role flags&lt;/strong> to contacts. You can now designate contacts as:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Author&lt;/strong> - The person or team who created the component&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Security Contact&lt;/strong> - Who to reach for security issues&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Technical Contact&lt;/strong> - Who to reach for technical questions&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>We have also consolidated the previously separate author field into the main contact profile. Instead of managing authors separately, you now simply mark a contact as an author using the role flag. This simplifies contact management while aligning with how CycloneDX represents contact information.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="compliance-badges">Compliance Badges&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Compliance status is now more visible than ever. v0.25 introduces &lt;strong>compliance badges&lt;/strong> that display assessment results directly on product listings and public Trust Center pages. Badges only appear for assessments you pass, so you are showcasing compliance achievements rather than advertising gaps.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We have also added a &lt;strong>Copy Badge&lt;/strong> button that generates markdown snippets you can paste into your README files. This makes it easy to showcase your compliance status directly in your repository.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="other-improvements">Other Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CRA Plugin v1.1.0&lt;/strong> - The EU Cyber Resilience Act plugin now prioritizes native SBOM fields over &lt;code>cra:&lt;/code> annotations, making it easier to pass assessments without custom annotations&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Custom Domains&lt;/strong> - Added DCV (Domain Control Validation) delegation CNAME instructions for easier SSL certificate provisioning&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Architecture&lt;/strong> - Reorganized the codebase with cleaner api/domain/services layer separation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Billing&lt;/strong> - Enhanced billing processing and webhook handling for Stripe events (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Django Admin&lt;/strong> - Comprehensive theme update to match the webapp design system (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Footer&lt;/strong> - Simplified by removing version badges and moving build info to HTML comments (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="bug-fixes">Bug Fixes&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Fixed API error messages leaking team and resource information (security improvement)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed 403 errors when tagging SBOMs via API tokens in CI/CD pipelines&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed infinite &amp;ldquo;checking&amp;rdquo; state in the plugin UI when no plugins are enabled&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed RecursionError in public component page templates&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed plugin enable to not queue all historical SBOMs, which was blocking the web server (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed social card images with proper 1200x630 dimensions and meta tags (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed missing component context in component item view (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed SPDX SBOMs not being tagged to releases (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed social banner URLs for public Trust Center pages (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To enable the GitHub Attestation Plugin, navigate to &lt;strong>Settings → Plugins&lt;/strong> and enable the GitHub Attestation assessment. From there, every SBOM upload with a valid attestation will be automatically verified.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For SPDX downloads, visit any release, project, or product page and use the format selector to download the aggregated SBOM in your preferred format.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out the full changelog for &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/compare/v0.24...v0.25">v0.25&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/compare/v0.25...v0.25.1">v0.25.1&lt;/a> on GitHub.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As always, I would love to hear your feedback. If you have questions about attestation verification or ideas for additional plugins, drop us a note or open an issue on GitHub.&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item><item><title>The MIT License: A Complete Guide for Developers</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/22/mit-license-guide/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/22/mit-license-guide/</guid><description>&lt;p>The MIT License is a permissive open source license that allows virtually unrestricted use, modification, distribution, and sublicensing of software, including use in proprietary and commercial products. Its only substantive requirement is that the license text and copyright notice must be included with any substantial distribution of the software. The MIT License is the most widely used open source license in the world — GitHub&amp;rsquo;s data consistently shows it as the most popular license choice across its platform.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-mit-license">What Is the MIT License?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The MIT License (formally, the &amp;ldquo;MIT License&amp;rdquo; as listed in the &lt;a href="https://spdx.org/licenses/">SPDX License List&lt;/a> with identifier &lt;code>MIT&lt;/code>) is a permissive free software license originating at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. It is sometimes referred to as the &amp;ldquo;Expat License&amp;rdquo; to distinguish it from other licenses historically associated with MIT.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The full text of the MIT License is remarkably short — approximately 170 words:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Copyright (c) &amp;lt;year&amp;gt; &amp;lt;copyright holder&amp;gt;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation files (the &amp;ldquo;Software&amp;rdquo;), to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED &amp;ldquo;AS IS&amp;rdquo;, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This brevity is intentional. The MIT License prioritizes simplicity and clarity, making it easy for developers and organizations to understand exactly what is permitted and what is required.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-the-mit-license-permits">What the MIT License Permits&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The MIT License grants the following rights without restriction:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Use&lt;/strong> — Run the software for any purpose, including commercial use&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Copy&lt;/strong> — Make copies of the software&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Modify&lt;/strong> — Create derivative works based on the software&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Merge&lt;/strong> — Combine the software with other software&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Publish&lt;/strong> — Make the software publicly available&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Distribute&lt;/strong> — Share copies with others&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sublicense&lt;/strong> — Grant these same rights to third parties&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sell&lt;/strong> — Sell copies of the software, including modified versions&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The phrase &amp;ldquo;deal in the Software without restriction&amp;rdquo; is deliberately broad. There are no limitations on field of use, no requirements to share source code, and no requirements to license derivative works under the MIT License.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-the-mit-license-requires">What the MIT License Requires&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The MIT License has exactly one condition: &lt;strong>the copyright notice and permission notice must be included in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In practice, this means:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>If you distribute MIT-licensed code (in source or binary form), include the MIT license text and the original copyright notice&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you modify the code and redistribute it, the same requirement applies&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you include MIT-licensed code as part of a larger work, the license text must be present somewhere in the distribution (typically in a LICENSE file, NOTICES file, or third-party attribution document)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>There is no requirement to:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Make your source code available&lt;/li>
&lt;li>License your derivative works under MIT&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Notify the original author of your use&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Display attribution in a user interface&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="mit-license-vs-other-permissive-licenses">MIT License vs. Other Permissive Licenses&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The MIT License is one of several permissive licenses. Understanding the differences matters for license compliance, particularly in projects that combine code from multiple licenses.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="mit-vs-bsd-2-clause-and-3-clause">MIT vs. BSD (2-Clause and 3-Clause)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The BSD 2-Clause License (&amp;ldquo;Simplified BSD&amp;rdquo;) is functionally equivalent to the MIT License — both require attribution and disclaim warranties, with no other conditions. The wording differs, but the legal effect is the same.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The BSD 3-Clause License adds a &amp;ldquo;non-endorsement&amp;rdquo; clause: you may not use the name of the copyright holder or contributors to endorse or promote derived products without permission. The MIT License has no such clause.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Feature&lt;/th>
&lt;th>MIT&lt;/th>
&lt;th>BSD 2-Clause&lt;/th>
&lt;th>BSD 3-Clause&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Attribution required&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Non-endorsement clause&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Patent grant&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No (implicit)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No (implicit)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No (implicit)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>SPDX identifier&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>MIT&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>BSD-2-Clause&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>BSD-3-Clause&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;h3 id="mit-vs-apache-20">MIT vs. Apache 2.0&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/07/apache-license-2-guide/">Apache License 2.0&lt;/a> is also permissive but includes two significant additions that the MIT License lacks:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Explicit patent grant.&lt;/strong> Apache 2.0 Section 3 grants users a patent license covering the contributor&amp;rsquo;s contributions. The MIT License makes no mention of patents. While the broad language of the MIT License (&amp;ldquo;deal in the Software without restriction&amp;rdquo;) may imply a patent license in some jurisdictions, this is not settled law.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTICE file requirement.&lt;/strong> Apache 2.0 requires that any redistribution carry forward the contents of a NOTICE file if one exists. The MIT License has no equivalent mechanism.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>State changes requirement.&lt;/strong> Apache 2.0 requires that modified files carry a prominent notice stating the changes. MIT has no such requirement.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>For a detailed comparison including GPL, see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/07/apache-license-2-guide/">Apache License 2.0 guide&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="mit-vs-isc-license">MIT vs. ISC License&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The ISC License is a simplified rewrite of the MIT License. It removes the explicit enumeration of rights (&amp;ldquo;use, copy, modify&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;) in favor of a single clause: &amp;ldquo;Permission to use, copy, modify, and/or distribute this software for any purpose with or without fee is hereby granted.&amp;rdquo; The legal effect is generally considered identical to MIT. The ISC License is used by OpenBSD and many npm packages.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="mit-license-and-copyleft-gpl">MIT License and Copyleft (GPL)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The MIT License is compatible with copyleft licenses like the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2025/12/22/gpl-license-guide/">GPL&lt;/a> — but only in one direction. MIT-licensed code can be included in a GPL-licensed project. The combined work is then licensed under the GPL. However, GPL-licensed code cannot be included in an MIT-licensed project, because the GPL requires that the entire combined work be distributed under the GPL.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Combination&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Result&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Permitted?&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>MIT code included in GPLv2 project&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Combined work is GPLv2&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>MIT code included in GPLv3 project&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Combined work is GPLv3&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>GPL code included in MIT project&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Would require MIT project to become GPL&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No (unless relicensed)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>MIT code included in AGPL project&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Combined work is AGPL&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>This compatibility makes MIT one of the most versatile licenses for code reuse. MIT-licensed libraries can be used in virtually any project, regardless of the project&amp;rsquo;s own license.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="mit-license-in-commercial-software">MIT License in Commercial Software&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The MIT License is one of the most commercially friendly open source licenses. Organizations commonly use MIT-licensed code in proprietary products because:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>No source disclosure.&lt;/strong> You are not required to share your source code, even if you modify the MIT-licensed component.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>No license propagation.&lt;/strong> Your proprietary code does not need to be licensed under MIT.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Minimal compliance burden.&lt;/strong> Including the license text in your distribution (typically in a NOTICES or THIRD-PARTY file) satisfies the only condition.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>No patent risk (with caveats).&lt;/strong> While the MIT License does not include an explicit patent grant, its broad permission language is generally interpreted as an implied license. For maximum patent protection, consider &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/07/apache-license-2-guide/">Apache 2.0&lt;/a> instead.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The primary compliance risk with MIT is not the license itself but the volume. A typical web application may depend on hundreds of MIT-licensed packages. Each one requires its license text and copyright notice to be included in the distribution. Automated tooling — particularly SBOM-based compliance checking — is essential at this scale.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-sboms-track-mit-license-compliance">How SBOMs Track MIT License Compliance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/what-is-sbom/">Software Bill of Materials&lt;/a> documents every component in your software along with its license. For MIT-licensed components, SBOMs support compliance in several ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Identifying MIT dependencies.&lt;/strong> SBOMs include license information for each component, using the SPDX identifier &lt;code>MIT&lt;/code> for machine-readable identification. This makes it straightforward to enumerate all MIT-licensed components in a project.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Attribution aggregation.&lt;/strong> With hundreds of MIT-licensed dependencies, manually collecting license texts is impractical. SBOMs provide the component list from which attribution documents (NOTICES files, THIRD-PARTY files) can be generated automatically.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>License compatibility checking.&lt;/strong> SBOM-based compliance tools can detect potential issues — for example, flagging if MIT code is being redistributed without the required license text, or identifying MIT/GPL combinations that require the combined work to be GPL-licensed.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Audit evidence.&lt;/strong> SBOMs provide the documentation needed for license audits, M&amp;amp;A due diligence, and procurement assessments.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Both &lt;a href="https://cyclonedx.org/">CycloneDX&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://spdx.dev/">SPDX&lt;/a> support standardized license fields. The &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action/">sbomify GitHub Action&lt;/a> automatically enriches SBOMs with license data from multiple sources, making it practical to track MIT attribution requirements across hundreds of dependencies. For language-specific instructions, see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/">SBOM generation guides&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For a broader overview of open source licenses, see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2024/04/03/navigating-the-landscape-of-open-source-licenses/">guide to navigating the landscape of open source licenses&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="frequently-asked-questions">Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-the-mit-license-1">What is the MIT License?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The MIT License is a permissive open source license that allows unrestricted use, modification, distribution, and sublicensing of software, including in proprietary and commercial products. Its only requirement is that the license text and copyright notice be included with any distribution. It is the most widely used open source license, identified in the SPDX License List as &lt;code>MIT&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="can-i-use-mit-licensed-software-commercially">Can I use MIT-licensed software commercially?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Yes. The MIT License explicitly permits commercial use, including selling copies, incorporating MIT-licensed code into proprietary products, and distributing modified versions. The only requirement is that you include the MIT license text and copyright notice with your distribution.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-the-difference-between-mit-and-apache-20">What is the difference between MIT and Apache 2.0?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Both are permissive licenses that allow commercial use without requiring source code disclosure. The key differences are: Apache 2.0 includes an explicit patent grant and patent retaliation clause, while MIT does not address patents explicitly; Apache 2.0 requires carrying forward NOTICE file attributions, while MIT only requires including the license text; and Apache 2.0 requires noting changes to modified files, while MIT does not. For projects where patent protection is important, Apache 2.0 provides stronger guarantees.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="is-the-mit-license-compatible-with-the-gpl">Is the MIT License compatible with the GPL?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Yes, but only in one direction. MIT-licensed code can be included in GPL-licensed projects — the combined work is then distributed under the GPL. However, GPL-licensed code cannot be included in an MIT-licensed project without the entire project becoming GPL-licensed. This one-directional compatibility is a feature of the GPL&amp;rsquo;s copyleft requirement, not a restriction in the MIT License.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="do-i-need-to-include-the-mit-license-text-when-distributing-software">Do I need to include the MIT License text when distributing software?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Yes. The MIT License requires that &amp;ldquo;the above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.&amp;rdquo; In practice, this means including the license text in a LICENSE file, NOTICES file, or third-party attribution document shipped with your distribution. This applies to both source and binary distributions.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="how-do-i-comply-with-the-mit-license">How do I comply with the MIT License?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Include the full MIT license text (including the copyright notice) in your distribution. This is typically done by maintaining a LICENSE or THIRD-PARTY-NOTICES file that aggregates the license texts of all open source dependencies. For applications with many MIT-licensed dependencies, automated tools that generate attribution documents from SBOMs are the most reliable approach.&lt;/p></description><category>education</category></item><item><title>SBOM Management: How to Organize, Track, and Act on Your SBOMs</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/18/sbom-management-best-practices/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/18/sbom-management-best-practices/</guid><description>&lt;p>SBOM management is the practice of organizing, storing, versioning, distributing, and acting on &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/what-is-sbom/">Software Bills of Materials&lt;/a> across an organization&amp;rsquo;s software portfolio. Generating an SBOM is only the first step. Without a management process, SBOMs become stale documents that sit unused. Effective SBOM management turns component inventories into an operational tool for vulnerability response, compliance reporting, and supply chain risk reduction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://sbomify.com/assets/images/d2/sbom-management-lifecycle.svg" alt="SBOM management lifecycle from generation through storage and monitoring to action">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-sbom-management-matters">Why SBOM Management Matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Most organizations that begin their SBOM journey focus on generation — using tools like &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com">sbomify&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://github.com/anchore/syft">Syft&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://github.com/aquasecurity/trivy">Trivy&lt;/a>, or &lt;a href="https://github.com/CycloneDX/cdxgen">cdxgen&lt;/a> to produce SBOMs from their projects (see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/resources/">resources page&lt;/a> for a complete list). This is necessary but insufficient. An SBOM that is generated once and never updated or monitored provides little ongoing value.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The real benefits of SBOMs — rapid vulnerability response, continuous compliance, supply chain visibility — only materialize when SBOMs are actively managed. Consider the &lt;a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/CVE-2021-44228">Log4Shell&lt;/a> disclosure in December 2021: organizations with up-to-date, searchable SBOMs identified affected systems in minutes. Organizations without them spent weeks manually auditing codebases.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>SBOM management addresses three challenges:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Scale.&lt;/strong> A mid-sized organization may have hundreds of applications, each with its own SBOM containing hundreds of components. Managing this manually is not feasible.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Currency.&lt;/strong> Software changes with every commit. SBOMs must be regenerated and updated to reflect the current state of deployed software.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Actionability.&lt;/strong> An SBOM is only useful if it can be queried, monitored, and correlated with new threat intelligence. Storage without analysis is archival, not management.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="the-sbom-lifecycle">The SBOM Lifecycle&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The SBOM lifecycle mirrors the structure outlined on our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/resources/">resources page&lt;/a>: generation, distribution, and analysis. Management spans all three phases.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="phase-1-generation">Phase 1: Generation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SBOM generation should be automated in your CI/CD pipeline so that every build produces a current SBOM. Key considerations:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Format choice.&lt;/strong> Select &lt;a href="https://cyclonedx.org/">CycloneDX&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://spdx.dev/">SPDX&lt;/a> based on your compliance requirements and tooling. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/15/sbom-formats-cyclonedx-vs-spdx/">SBOM formats comparison&lt;/a> for guidance. Many organizations generate in both formats.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Generation point.&lt;/strong> Generate SBOMs at build time from resolved dependency trees (lock files, built artifacts), not from unresolved manifests. Build-time SBOMs capture the exact versions that will be deployed, including transitive dependencies.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Automation.&lt;/strong> Integrate SBOM generation into your CI/CD pipeline using tools like the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action/">sbomify GitHub Action&lt;/a>. Every release should produce an SBOM automatically.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Completeness.&lt;/strong> Ensure SBOMs capture all layers. For &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/03/container-security-best-practices/">containerized applications&lt;/a>, this means generating container-level SBOMs that include base image packages in addition to application dependencies.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>For language-specific generation instructions, see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/">SBOM guides&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="phase-2-storage-and-versioning">Phase 2: Storage and Versioning&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Generated SBOMs need a durable, queryable storage location. Approaches range from simple to sophisticated:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Artifact repository.&lt;/strong> Store SBOMs alongside the build artifacts they describe. If you use a container registry, attach SBOMs to container images using OCI artifacts. If you use a package registry, publish SBOMs as companion files.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Dedicated SBOM platform.&lt;/strong> Use a purpose-built platform like &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com">sbomify&lt;/a> that ingests, indexes, and monitors SBOMs across your portfolio. sbomify organizes SBOMs in a hierarchy of Products, Projects, and Components — matching how software is actually built — and provides centralized visibility, search, and policy enforcement. Its &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/trust-center/">Trust Center&lt;/a> feature also handles distribution to customers and auditors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Version control.&lt;/strong> Each SBOM should be versioned in lockstep with the software it describes. When version 2.1.3 of your application is released, the SBOM for 2.1.3 should be generated and stored. Previous versions should be retained for audit and incident response purposes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Retention policy.&lt;/strong> Define how long SBOMs are retained. At minimum, retain SBOMs for all currently deployed versions. For compliance, retain SBOMs for the duration required by your applicable frameworks — the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eu-cra/">EU CRA&lt;/a> requires vulnerability handling for the expected product lifetime or a minimum of five years.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="phase-3-monitoring-and-analysis">Phase 3: Monitoring and Analysis&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This is where SBOMs deliver their highest value. Continuous monitoring matches your SBOM components against vulnerability databases and threat intelligence feeds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Vulnerability monitoring.&lt;/strong> Ingest SBOMs into a management platform like &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com">sbomify&lt;/a> (which integrates Google OSV and &lt;a href="https://dependencytrack.org/">OWASP Dependency-Track&lt;/a>) or a standalone instance of Dependency-Track. These platforms continuously match components against the &lt;a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/">NVD&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://osv.dev/">OSV&lt;/a>, and the &lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/known-exploited-vulnerabilities-catalog">CISA KEV catalog&lt;/a>. When a new &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2025/12/18/cve-vulnerability-explained/">CVE&lt;/a> is published, the platform immediately identifies which of your products are affected.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>License compliance.&lt;/strong> Monitor for license conflicts and policy violations. Automated tools can flag &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2025/12/22/gpl-license-guide/">GPL&lt;/a> dependencies in proprietary products, &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/07/apache-license-2-guide/">Apache 2.0 / GPLv2 incompatibilities&lt;/a>, or components with unknown licenses.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Component lifecycle tracking.&lt;/strong> Monitor for end-of-life and end-of-support components. Dependencies that are no longer maintained represent a growing risk as new vulnerabilities go unpatched.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Policy enforcement.&lt;/strong> Define organizational policies (e.g., &amp;ldquo;no components with critical KEV-listed vulnerabilities in production,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;no AGPL-licensed components in SaaS products&amp;rdquo;) and monitor compliance across your portfolio.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sbom-distribution">SBOM Distribution&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>SBOMs are not just internal documents. Increasingly, they must be shared with customers, regulators, and supply chain partners.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="who-receives-sboms">Who Receives SBOMs&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Customers&lt;/strong> requesting SBOMs as part of procurement or vendor assessment&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Regulators&lt;/strong> requiring SBOMs under frameworks like &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eo-14028/">EO 14028&lt;/a> or the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eu-cra/">EU CRA&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Internal teams&lt;/strong> consuming software from other teams within the organization&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Auditors&lt;/strong> conducting security assessments or due diligence&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="distribution-methods">Distribution Methods&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Companion file.&lt;/strong> Publish the SBOM alongside the software release (e.g., in the GitHub release assets, alongside Docker images in a registry)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>API access.&lt;/strong> Provide programmatic access to SBOMs through a dedicated API endpoint&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dedicated platform.&lt;/strong> Use an SBOM management platform like &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/trust-center/">sbomify&amp;rsquo;s Trust Center&lt;/a> that provides a branded portal with controlled access to SBOMs and compliance documents for authorized consumers&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="what-to-include">What to Include&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Follow the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/ntia-minimum-elements/">NTIA minimum elements&lt;/a> as a baseline for SBOM content: supplier name, component name, component version, unique identifiers, dependency relationships, SBOM author, and timestamp. The &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/cisa-minimum-elements/">CISA minimum elements draft&lt;/a> adds recommended fields including license information and lifecycle/generation context.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organizing-sboms-at-scale">Organizing SBOMs at Scale&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As the number of SBOMs grows, organization becomes critical.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="by-product-and-version">By Product and Version&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The most natural organization maps SBOMs to the products and versions they describe. Each product-version combination should have exactly one authoritative SBOM. For products composed of multiple services or components, consider a hierarchical approach: a top-level SBOM for the product that references component-level SBOMs for each service.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="by-deployment-environment">By Deployment Environment&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Different environments (development, staging, production) may run different versions. Track which SBOM corresponds to what is currently deployed in each environment. This is especially important for incident response — when a new vulnerability is disclosed, you need to know what is in production right now, not what was released last quarter.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="by-supply-chain-position">By Supply Chain Position&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>If you both consume and produce software, maintain SBOMs in both directions: SBOMs you receive from your suppliers (upstream) and SBOMs you generate for your products (downstream). Correlating upstream SBOMs with downstream products lets you trace how a supplier vulnerability propagates through your software.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="best-practices">Best Practices&lt;/h2>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Automate generation in CI/CD.&lt;/strong> Never generate SBOMs manually. Integrate SBOM generation into your build pipeline so every release is automatically documented. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/">SBOM generation guides&lt;/a> for language-specific instructions.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Monitor continuously.&lt;/strong> Set up automated vulnerability monitoring against your SBOMs. New CVEs are published daily; manual cross-referencing does not scale. &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com">sbomify&lt;/a> provides integrated monitoring via Google OSV and OWASP Dependency-Track.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Version SBOMs with releases.&lt;/strong> Every software release should produce a corresponding SBOM. Store them together so you always know the component composition of any deployed version.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Define retention and distribution policies.&lt;/strong> Decide how long SBOMs are retained, who has access, and how they are shared with external consumers. Align retention with your compliance obligations.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Centralize visibility.&lt;/strong> As your SBOM inventory grows, centralize it in a platform that supports search, filtering, and cross-portfolio analysis. Being able to answer &amp;ldquo;which of our products use Log4j?&amp;rdquo; in seconds is the goal.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Keep SBOMs current.&lt;/strong> A stale SBOM is worse than no SBOM — it provides false confidence. Ensure that deployed software always has a corresponding current SBOM. Flag and investigate any deployed artifacts without an associated SBOM.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Act on findings.&lt;/strong> SBOM management is not complete without a remediation process. When monitoring surfaces a vulnerability, define SLAs for response based on severity, &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2025/12/30/what-is-kev-cisa-known-exploited-vulnerabilities/">KEV status&lt;/a>, and deployment context.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="frequently-asked-questions">Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-sbom-management">What is SBOM management?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SBOM management is the practice of organizing, storing, versioning, distributing, and continuously monitoring Software Bills of Materials across an organization&amp;rsquo;s software portfolio. It encompasses the entire SBOM lifecycle: automated generation in CI/CD, durable storage with version tracking, continuous vulnerability monitoring against databases like the NVD and CISA KEV, license compliance checking, and distribution to customers and regulators.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="why-is-sbom-management-important">Why is SBOM management important?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Generating an SBOM is only the first step. Without management, SBOMs quickly become stale and unused. SBOM management enables rapid vulnerability response (identifying affected products in seconds when a new CVE is disclosed), continuous compliance monitoring, and supply chain visibility at scale. Organizations with hundreds of applications and thousands of dependencies cannot manage software composition manually.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-tools-are-used-for-sbom-management">What tools are used for SBOM management?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Key tools include &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com">sbomify&lt;/a> for integrated SBOM management (generation, storage, monitoring, and distribution in one platform), OWASP Dependency-Track for standalone vulnerability monitoring, and Grype for CLI-based scanning. For generation-only tools, Syft, Trivy, and cdxgen produce SBOMs in CycloneDX or SPDX format. For a comprehensive listing, see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/resources/">SBOM resources page&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="how-often-should-sboms-be-updated">How often should SBOMs be updated?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SBOMs should be regenerated with every software release and ideally with every build in your CI/CD pipeline. The SBOM for a deployed application should always reflect its current composition. Additionally, SBOMs should be continuously monitored against vulnerability databases, as new CVEs are published daily that may affect previously scanned components.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-should-be-included-in-an-sbom">What should be included in an SBOM?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>At minimum, follow the NTIA minimum elements: supplier name, component name, component version, unique identifiers (purl or CPE), dependency relationships, SBOM author, and timestamp. The CISA minimum elements draft adds license information and generation context. For compliance with specific frameworks, check the requirements on our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/">compliance overview page&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description><category>education</category></item><item><title>Announcing sbomify v0.24: The One with All the Plugins</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/14/announcing-sbomify-v0-24-the-one-with-all-the-plugins/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/14/announcing-sbomify-v0-24-the-one-with-all-the-plugins/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today marks a pivotal release for sbomify. With v0.24, we are laying the foundation for what will become a fully extensible, plugin-based platform. This release introduces our new &lt;strong>Plugin-Based Assessment Framework&lt;/strong>, a unified architecture for running automated assessments on every SBOM upload. This represents a fundamental shift in how we think about sbomify&amp;rsquo;s architecture going forward.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="plugin-based-assessment-framework">Plugin-Based Assessment Framework&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The headline feature of v0.24 is our new assessment plugin system, documented in &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/blob/master/docs/ADR/ADR-003.md">ADR-003: Plugin-based Assessments for SBOM Uploads&lt;/a>. If you want to understand where sbomify is headed, this architectural decision record is essential reading.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="four-assessment-categories">Four Assessment Categories&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The plugin framework is designed to support four distinct categories of SBOM assessment:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Category&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Description&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Examples&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Security&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Vulnerability scanning via external tools and APIs&lt;/td>
&lt;td>OSV, Dependency-Track&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>License&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Policy evaluation against approved/denied license lists&lt;/td>
&lt;td>License policy checks&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Compliance&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Validation against regulatory and industry standards&lt;/td>
&lt;td>NTIA, CISA, CRA, FDA&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Attestation&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Integrity and provenance verification&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Sigstore, in-toto&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Each category has different characteristics. Security plugins integrate with external vulnerability databases that change continuously, so they support scheduled re-runs. Compliance and license plugins are deterministic for a given ruleset version. Attestation plugins verify cryptographic signatures and provenance data.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="compliance-plugins-shipping-now">Compliance Plugins Shipping Now&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This release ships with five compliance plugins ready to use. Each plugin aligns with our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/">compliance documentation&lt;/a>, so you can understand exactly what is being validated:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/ntia-minimum-elements/">NTIA Minimum Elements&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> - Validates your SBOMs against the foundational US baseline for SBOM data fields&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/cisa-minimum-elements/">CISA 2025 Minimum Elements&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> - Checks compliance with the updated US guidance including hash, license, and generation context&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eu-cra/">EU Cyber Resilience Act (CRA)&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> - Validates against Regulation 2024/2847 requirements (beta)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/fda-medical-device/">FDA Medical Device Cybersecurity&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> - Ensures medical device SBOM requirements are met, including lifecycle properties&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Checksum Verification&lt;/strong> - A test plugin that validates SBOM integrity through checksum verification (useful as a reference implementation)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Each plugin runs automatically when you upload an SBOM. Simply enable the plugins you need in &lt;strong>Settings → Plugins&lt;/strong>, and assessments happen transparently in the background.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="why-this-architecture-matters">Why This Architecture Matters&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The design decisions in ADR-003 are intentional and set the stage for everything that follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Assessments tied to uploads, not content hashes&lt;/strong> - Each upload is assessed independently, giving you a complete history of checks over time&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Immutable AssessmentRun records&lt;/strong> - Every assessment is recorded permanently, enabling full audit trails and historical tracking&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Python SDK with normalized results&lt;/strong> - All plugins return results in a consistent &lt;code>AssessmentResult&lt;/code> schema with &lt;code>Finding&lt;/code> entries, making it easy to compare and aggregate data across plugin types&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Config hashing for reproducibility&lt;/strong> - When assessment results change, you can trace exactly why by comparing configuration hashes&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Per-team plugin enablement&lt;/strong> - Teams can enable the plugins relevant to their needs, with feature gating based on billing plans&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-migration-path">The Migration Path&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This plugin system is the future of sbomify. In upcoming releases, we will be migrating our existing features into this architecture:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Phase 2: Security Plugins&lt;/strong>
Our current &lt;strong>OSV vulnerability scanning&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>Dependency Track integration&lt;/strong> will be refactored into security plugins. This migration will make these features more modular, give you historical tracking of all vulnerability scans, and allow the same plugin architecture to power scheduled re-scans as vulnerability databases are updated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Phase 3 and Beyond&lt;/strong>
We have a roadmap of additional plugins including license policy evaluation, attestation verification (Sigstore and in-toto), and VEX (Vulnerability Exploitability eXchange) statement processing. The goal is to make sbomify a platform where you can mix and match the capabilities you need.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="vuejs-to-alpinejs-migration-complete">Vue.js to Alpine.js Migration Complete&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We have completed the frontend migration we started in previous releases. This release replaces the remaining &lt;strong>35 Vue.js components&lt;/strong> with lightweight Alpine.js implementations backed by Django templates.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This migration closes out &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/blob/master/docs/ADR/ADR-001.md">ADR-001: Django Monolith&lt;/a>. As documented there, our detour into Vue turned out to be a mistake. While we wanted to maintain an API-first approach, leveraging Django Templates with server-side rendering minimizes complexity compared to a separate Vue frontend. Equally important, Vue made end-to-end testing more challenging, and we had several blocks silently failing as a result.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The result is a significantly smaller bundle size, faster page loads, a more maintainable codebase, and much better test coverage. If you have been following our journey from Vue.js to Alpine.js + HTMX, this release marks the finish line.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="contact-profiles-cyclonedx-alignment">Contact Profiles CycloneDX Alignment&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Contact profiles have been restructured to align with the CycloneDX specification. The new &lt;strong>3-level hierarchy&lt;/strong> (Profile → Entity → Contact) matches how CycloneDX represents organizational and contact information.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you have existing contact profiles, they will be automatically migrated to the new structure. No action required on your part.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="billing-system-improvements">Billing System Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We have made several improvements to how billing works:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dynamic pricing from Stripe&lt;/strong> - Pricing is now synced directly from Stripe, ensuring consistency across the platform&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Promotion codes at checkout&lt;/strong> - You can now apply promotion codes when subscribing or upgrading&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Billing period visibility&lt;/strong> - Your current billing period and next billing date are now displayed in team settings&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improved subscription management&lt;/strong> - New management commands for subscription reconciliation and better webhook handling&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="other-improvements">Other Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Trust Center&lt;/strong>: Consolidated templates, improved SEO, and better UX across the board&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CycloneDX 1.6+&lt;/strong>: Added manufacturer field support with backward compatibility for 1.5&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CI/CD Templates&lt;/strong>: New configuration templates for Azure DevOps and Jenkins&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>License Expressions&lt;/strong>: Optimized parsing with server-side rendering support&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mobile Experience&lt;/strong>: Improved search bar responsiveness on mobile devices&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Document Upload&lt;/strong>: Better drag-and-drop experience&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Workspace Labels&lt;/strong>: Now use title case (Product, Compliance Artifact, Project)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="security-and-infrastructure">Security and Infrastructure&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>On the security front, we addressed findings from Semgrep and Bandit scans, added &lt;code>noreferrer&lt;/code> to external links, and fixed a user invitation limit bypass vulnerability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Infrastructure updates include upgrading our base image to &lt;strong>Debian Trixie&lt;/strong>, updating &lt;code>python-keycloak&lt;/code> to 7.0.1, and bumping our GitHub Actions dependencies to their latest versions.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="bug-fixes">Bug Fixes&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Fixed duplicate artifacts appearing in release pages when components belong to multiple projects&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed barcode rendering on private product identifiers page&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed latest badge display and modal issues in release UI&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed private component access returning 404 instead of 403 Forbidden&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed &lt;code>$schema&lt;/code> alias handling in CycloneDX SBOM serialization&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed domain verification cron job registration&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you are self-hosting sbomify, update to v0.24 to take advantage of the new plugin system. For users on our hosted platform, these features are already live.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To enable assessment plugins, navigate to &lt;strong>Settings → Plugins&lt;/strong> and enable the assessments relevant to your requirements. From there, every SBOM upload will be automatically assessed, with full historical tracking of all results.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/compare/v0.23...master">full changelog on GitHub&lt;/a> for complete details.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As always, I would love to hear your feedback. Drop us a note or open an issue on GitHub if you have questions, suggestions, or ideas for new plugins. The plugin architecture is designed to be extensible, and we are eager to hear what assessments would be most valuable to you!&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item><item><title>FDA Medical Device SBOM Requirements: What the New Cybersecurity Guidance Means for Manufacturers</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/09/fda-medical-device-sbom-requirements/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/09/fda-medical-device-sbom-requirements/</guid><description>&lt;p>On June 27, 2025, the FDA issued updated guidance on &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Cybersecurity in Medical Devices: Quality System Considerations and Content of Premarket Submissions.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong> This document marks a significant step forward in how medical device manufacturers must approach software security and transparency. At the heart of these recommendations lies the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/what-is-sbom/">Software Bill of Materials (SBOM)&lt;/a> — now an essential element of premarket submissions for connected medical devices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re a manufacturer preparing a 510(k), PMA, or other premarket submission, here&amp;rsquo;s what you need to know about the FDA&amp;rsquo;s SBOM expectations and how to prepare.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-the-guidance-says-about-sboms">What the Guidance Says About SBOMs&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The FDA guidance recommends the inclusion of an SBOM under &lt;strong>Section V.A.4 (Software Bill of Materials)&lt;/strong> as part of cybersecurity documentation in premarket submissions. Additionally, &lt;strong>Appendix 4&lt;/strong> lists SBOM sections as recommended documentation when cybersecurity risk is relevant.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While the guidance language is technically &lt;strong>non-binding&lt;/strong> (&amp;ldquo;contains nonbinding recommendations&amp;rdquo;), the practical reality is different:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Under &lt;strong>Section 524B of the FD&amp;amp;C Act&lt;/strong>, the FDA has authority over &amp;ldquo;cyber devices&amp;rdquo; — devices with software that can be vulnerable and are connected&lt;/li>
&lt;li>FDA may &lt;strong>refuse to accept premarket submissions&lt;/strong> that do not provide adequate SBOM and related cybersecurity information&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Insufficient SBOM documentation can lead to &lt;strong>delays in review&lt;/strong> or requests for resubmission&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In practice, the SBOM has moved from &amp;ldquo;nice-to-have&amp;rdquo; to &lt;strong>essential cybersecurity documentation&lt;/strong> for medical device submissions. This mirrors the broader global trend toward &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/why-now/">mandatory SBOM requirements&lt;/a> across regulatory frameworks.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sbom-content-expectations">SBOM Content Expectations&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The FDA guidance does not define SBOM fields directly. Instead, it explicitly references the &lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://www.ntia.gov/sites/default/files/publications/sbom_minimum_elements_report_0.pdf">NTIA Minimum Elements for a Software Bill of Materials&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> as the baseline expectation for SBOM content in premarket submissions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This distinction matters: the FDA is effectively saying &amp;ldquo;provide an SBOM that meets the NTIA minimum elements&amp;rdquo; — not &amp;ldquo;provide an SBOM with these FDA-defined fields.&amp;rdquo; This approach mirrors how other regulators (including the EU&amp;rsquo;s Cyber Resilience Act) reference SBOMs indirectly via standards bodies, allowing requirements to evolve without requiring agencies to reissue guidance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="ntia-minimum-elements">NTIA Minimum Elements&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The NTIA baseline defines what every SBOM should contain. For each software component:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Supplier name&lt;/strong> — who supplied the component&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Component name&lt;/strong> — the name of the component&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Version&lt;/strong> — the version identifier&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Unique identifier&lt;/strong> — such as Package URL (purl) or CPE&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dependency relationship&lt;/strong> — how components relate to each other&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Author of SBOM data&lt;/strong> — who created the SBOM&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Timestamp&lt;/strong> — when the SBOM was created&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="machine-readable-formats">Machine-Readable Formats&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SBOMs should be provided in machine-readable formats that support the NTIA minimum elements:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>SPDX&lt;/strong> (Software Package Data Exchange)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CycloneDX&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Both formats are widely accepted and can represent the required NTIA data fields.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="complete-software-inventory">Complete Software Inventory&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>All software included in the device must be identified:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Commercial software&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Open-source components&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Third-party libraries&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Off-the-shelf (OTS) components&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="support-and-lifecycle-metadata">Support and Lifecycle Metadata&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Beyond the NTIA baseline, FDA expects additional context for medical device submissions:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Level of support&lt;/strong> from the component supplier (active, legacy, or unsupported)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>End-of-support and end-of-life dates&lt;/strong> for each component&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="vulnerability-context">Vulnerability Context&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SBOMs should be supplemented with:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A &lt;strong>known vulnerabilities assessment&lt;/strong> for identified components&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Controls or mitigation descriptions&lt;/strong> explaining whether vulnerabilities are mitigated by design&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This means SBOMs are expected to be part of a comprehensive &lt;strong>vulnerability and risk management package&lt;/strong>, not just a flat inventory list.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="lifecycle-and-traceability-requirements">Lifecycle and Traceability Requirements&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The FDA guidance ties SBOMs into broader cybersecurity documentation expectations throughout the device lifecycle. Understanding the full &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/generate-collaborate-analyze/">SBOM lifecycle&lt;/a> — from generation through distribution and analysis — is critical for FDA compliance:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="secure-product-development-and-traceability">Secure Product Development and Traceability&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>SBOMs must be &lt;strong>traceable to security architecture views&lt;/strong> and threat models that FDA reviewers evaluate&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The documentation should demonstrate how software components affect device security risks&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="ongoing-updates">Ongoing Updates&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>SBOMs should be &lt;strong>updated to reflect changes&lt;/strong> throughout software updates and the device lifecycle&lt;/li>
&lt;li>This is not a one-time snapshot — it&amp;rsquo;s a living document&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Proper &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/how-to-version-sboms">SBOM versioning practices&lt;/a> are essential for maintaining traceability&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="integration-with-other-documentation">Integration with Other Documentation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In premarket submissions, SBOMs typically appear alongside:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Security Risk Management Reports&lt;/strong> — showing how components affect device risks&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Vulnerability Assessments&lt;/strong> — outcomes derived from SBOM analysis&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Software Support Information&lt;/strong> — lifecycle and maintenance details&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Labeling and Transparency Materials&lt;/strong> — cybersecurity information for end users&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="why-cicd-integration-is-essential">Why CI/CD Integration Is Essential&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Given the FDA&amp;rsquo;s emphasis on traceability and ongoing updates, &lt;strong>manual SBOM generation is not sustainable&lt;/strong> for medical device compliance. Every software build should automatically generate an SBOM that:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Captures the exact components at the moment of build&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Is cryptographically linked to that specific release&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Can be traced back to source code and build artifacts&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Is automatically stored and versioned for audit trails&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Integrating SBOM generation into your CI/CD pipeline ensures that every release — whether it&amp;rsquo;s a major version update or a security patch — has accurate, reproducible documentation. This is particularly important for medical devices where you may need to answer FDA questions about software composition years after the initial submission.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="distribution-and-transparency">Distribution and Transparency&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The FDA expects manufacturers to share cybersecurity information with stakeholders, including healthcare providers and end users. This means having a reliable system for distributing SBOMs to:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>FDA reviewers during premarket submissions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Auditors during compliance assessments&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Healthcare organizations evaluating your devices&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Security researchers conducting vulnerability assessments&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Email and shared drives don&amp;rsquo;t scale for this — you need a dedicated &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/trust-center/">SBOM hub and Trust Center&lt;/a> that provides controlled access to current and historical SBOMs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="practical-implications-for-manufacturers">Practical Implications for Manufacturers&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re preparing a premarket submission (510(k), PMA, De Novo), here&amp;rsquo;s what the FDA expects in practice:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sbom-compliance-checklist">SBOM Compliance Checklist&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>NTIA Minimum Elements&lt;/strong> — Ensure your SBOM includes all required fields (supplier, component name, version, unique identifier, dependencies, author, timestamp)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Machine-readable format&lt;/strong> — Use SPDX or CycloneDX&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Inventory completeness&lt;/strong> — Cover all software elements in your device&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Support and lifecycle metadata&lt;/strong> — Document support status and EOL dates for each component&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Known vulnerability assessment&lt;/strong> — Tie vulnerabilities back to risk controls&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Traceability and architecture linkage&lt;/strong> — Connect SBOMs to documentation and risk models&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Ongoing maintenance strategy&lt;/strong> — Plan for SBOM updates through the device&amp;rsquo;s life&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="consequences-of-non-compliance">Consequences of Non-Compliance&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Noncompliance or insufficient SBOM information can result in:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Refuse-to-accept decisions&lt;/strong> at the submission stage&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Delays in review&lt;/strong> requiring resubmission with complete SBOM and analysis&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The message is clear: get your SBOM documentation right the first time.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-sbomify-helps-with-fda-compliance">How sbomify Helps with FDA Compliance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Medical devices often have long lifecycles — sometimes 10-15 years or more. Managing SBOMs across that timespan, through multiple software updates and component changes, requires purpose-built tooling that automates the entire &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/generate-collaborate-analyze/">SBOM lifecycle&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="">sbomify&lt;/a> provides the infrastructure medical device manufacturers need:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="automated-cicd-integration">Automated CI/CD Integration&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This is the foundation of FDA-compliant SBOM management. sbomify integrates directly into your build pipeline:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/generate-collaborate-analyze/">Generate SBOMs automatically&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> during every build — no manual steps&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Augment and enrich&lt;/strong> SBOMs with supplier information, licensing, and metadata required by NTIA minimum elements&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Cryptographic signing and attestation&lt;/strong> for verifiable integrity&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Upload to sbomify with our &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action">GitHub Action&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2024/11/12/gitlab-support/">GitLab modules&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Every release automatically documented and stored for regulatory review&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>By automating generation in CI/CD, you ensure that SBOMs are always accurate, reproducible, and traceable to specific builds — exactly what the FDA expects.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="trust-center-for-regulatory-distribution">Trust Center for Regulatory Distribution&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Email and file shares don&amp;rsquo;t meet FDA expectations for professional cybersecurity documentation. sbomify&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/trust-center/">Trust Center&lt;/a> gives you:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A &lt;strong>branded portal&lt;/strong> for sharing SBOMs with FDA reviewers, auditors, and healthcare organizations&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Controlled access&lt;/strong> — determine who can see which products and versions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Always current&lt;/strong> — stakeholders access live data, not stale email attachments&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Audit trail&lt;/strong> — track who accessed what and when&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Professional presentation that demonstrates your commitment to transparency&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="sbom-lifecycle-management">SBOM Lifecycle Management&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Archive and track SBOMs across product versions and releases&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Maintain full version history for regulatory audits spanning years&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Support long-lived medical devices with complete historical records&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="centralized-sbom-hub">Centralized SBOM Hub&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Manage SBOMs for multiple device products in one platform&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Standardize generation and storage across engineering teams&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Aggregate component-level SBOMs into product-level views with our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/sbom-hierarchy/">SBOM hierarchy&lt;/a> feature — essential for complex medical devices with multiple software subsystems&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="continuous-vulnerability-monitoring">Continuous Vulnerability Monitoring&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Integrate with &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/integrations/">Google OSV and Dependency Track&lt;/a> for ongoing vulnerability detection&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Monitor archived SBOMs for newly discovered CVEs&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Track vulnerability status even for devices shipped years ago — critical for the FDA&amp;rsquo;s post-market cybersecurity expectations&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The FDA&amp;rsquo;s June 2025 cybersecurity guidance makes it clear: SBOMs are no longer optional for medical device manufacturers. They&amp;rsquo;re a critical component of premarket submissions and ongoing compliance. The guidance sets clear expectations for SBOM content, format, and lifecycle management — and the FDA is prepared to refuse submissions that don&amp;rsquo;t meet these standards.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Getting ahead of these requirements isn&amp;rsquo;t just about regulatory compliance — it&amp;rsquo;s about building more secure devices and maintaining trust with healthcare providers and patients.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://app.sbomify.com">Get started with sbomify&lt;/a> and build FDA-ready SBOM documentation into your medical device development process.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="resources">Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="official-documentation">Official Documentation&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.fda.gov/media/119933/download">FDA Guidance: Cybersecurity in Medical Devices (PDF)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.ntia.gov/sites/default/files/publications/sbom_minimum_elements_report_0.pdf">NTIA Minimum Elements for a Software Bill of Materials (PDF)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-sboms">Learn More About SBOMs&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/what-is-sbom/">What is an SBOM?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/generate-collaborate-analyze/">The SBOM Lifecycle: Generation, Distribution, and Analysis&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/how-to-version-sboms">How to Version SBOMs&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/why-now/">The Growing Importance of SBOMs in Cybersecurity Compliance&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="related-compliance-frameworks">Related Compliance Frameworks&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2024/07/10/understanding-the-eu-cyber-resilience-act-the-role-of-sboms-in-enhancing-cybersecurity/">Understanding the EU Cyber Resilience Act&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2025/01/07/how-sboms-can-help-you-achieve-pci-dss-4-compliance/">How SBOMs Help with PCI DSS 4.0 Compliance&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/06/cra-explained-cyber-resilience-act-for-device-manufacturers/">CRA Explained: What the Cyber Resilience Act Means for Device Manufacturers&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="sbomify-features">sbomify Features&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/sbom-hierarchy/">SBOM Hierarchy&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/integrations/">Integrations&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/trust-center/">Trust Center&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description><category>compliance</category></item><item><title>Apache License 2.0: What It Is, How It Works, and What It Means for Your Software</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/07/apache-license-2-guide/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/07/apache-license-2-guide/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Apache License 2.0 is a permissive open source license published by the &lt;a href="https://www.apache.org/">Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a> (ASF) that allows users to freely use, modify, distribute, and sublicense software with minimal restrictions. Its defining features are an explicit patent grant that protects users from patent litigation by contributors, and straightforward attribution requirements through the NOTICE file mechanism. The Apache License 2.0 is one of the most popular open source licenses in the world, used by projects including Apache HTTP Server, Kubernetes, Android (AOSP), TensorFlow, and thousands of others.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-apache-license-20">What Is the Apache License 2.0?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Apache License 2.0 (formally, the &lt;a href="https://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0">Apache License, Version 2.0&lt;/a>) is a permissive free software license written by the Apache Software Foundation and released in January 2004. &amp;ldquo;Permissive&amp;rdquo; means that the license imposes minimal restrictions on how the software can be used, modified, and redistributed — including in proprietary, closed-source products.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Apache License 2.0 replaced the earlier Apache License 1.1 and 1.0, which had more restrictive advertising clauses similar to the original BSD license. Version 2.0 was designed to be clear, comprehensive, and compatible with a broad range of other open source licenses.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The license is identified in the &lt;a href="https://spdx.org/licenses/">SPDX License List&lt;/a> as &lt;code>Apache-2.0&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="key-provisions">Key Provisions&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="permissions-granted">Permissions Granted&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The Apache License 2.0 grants the following rights, in both copyright and patent terms:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Use&lt;/strong> — Run the software for any purpose, including commercial use&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Modify&lt;/strong> — Create derivative works based on the software&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Distribute&lt;/strong> — Distribute copies of the original or modified software&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sublicense&lt;/strong> — Grant these same rights to others&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Patent use&lt;/strong> — Use any patents held by contributors that cover their contributions&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="conditions">Conditions&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The license requires:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Attribution.&lt;/strong> You must include a copy of the Apache License 2.0 in any distribution and retain all copyright, patent, trademark, and attribution notices from the original source.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTICE file.&lt;/strong> If the original work includes a NOTICE file (a text file containing attribution notices required by the license), you must include a readable copy of the NOTICE file in your distribution. You may add your own attribution notices to the NOTICE file, but you may not remove existing ones.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>State changes.&lt;/strong> If you modify the software, you must include a prominent notice stating that you changed the files.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-not-required">What Is NOT Required&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Unlike copyleft licenses such as the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2025/12/22/gpl-license-guide/">GPL&lt;/a>, the Apache License 2.0 does &lt;strong>not&lt;/strong> require:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Distributing your source code (you can distribute binaries only)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Licensing your derivative works under the Apache License&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Making your modifications open source&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This is what makes it &amp;ldquo;permissive&amp;rdquo; — you can incorporate Apache-licensed code into proprietary software without triggering any obligation to open-source your own code.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-patent-grant">The Patent Grant&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Apache License 2.0&amp;rsquo;s explicit patent grant is one of its most important features and a key reason organizations choose it over other permissive licenses like MIT or BSD.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Section 3 of the license states that each contributor grants &amp;ldquo;a perpetual, worldwide, non-exclusive, no-charge, royalty-free, irrevocable &amp;hellip; patent license&amp;rdquo; covering the contributor&amp;rsquo;s contributions. This means:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>If a contributor holds patents that cover their code contribution, they are granting you a license to those patents for the purpose of using, making, and selling the software.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>This protection applies to all users and redistributors of the software.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The patent grant is automatically revoked for any user who initiates patent litigation against the project (the &amp;ldquo;patent retaliation&amp;rdquo; clause in Section 3).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Neither the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/22/mit-license-guide/">MIT license&lt;/a> nor the BSD licenses include an explicit patent grant, which creates theoretical patent risk — a contributor could contribute code and later assert patent claims against users. The Apache License 2.0 eliminates this risk.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-notice-file">The NOTICE File&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The NOTICE file is a mechanism unique to the Apache License 2.0 for managing attribution requirements. The Apache Software Foundation &lt;a href="https://www.apache.org/legal/src-headers.html">requires&lt;/a> all ASF projects to include a NOTICE file containing:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The project name and a brief description&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Copyright notices from all contributors&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Any third-party attribution notices required by dependencies&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>When you redistribute Apache-licensed software, you must include the contents of the NOTICE file in at least one of:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A NOTICE file included with your distribution&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Documentation provided alongside the distribution&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A display generated by your software (if it has a user-facing display)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The NOTICE file is a common source of compliance failures. Organizations that use Apache-licensed components must ensure they carry forward all required attributions, especially when bundling multiple Apache-licensed libraries.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="license-compatibility">License Compatibility&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>License compatibility determines whether code from different licenses can be combined in a single work. The Apache License 2.0 has broad compatibility with other open source licenses, but there are notable interactions.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>License&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Compatible with Apache 2.0?&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Notes&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>MIT&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>MIT code can be included in Apache-licensed projects and vice versa&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>BSD (2-clause, 3-clause)&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Similar permissive terms; no conflict&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>GPL v3&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes (one direction)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Apache 2.0 code can be included in GPLv3 projects; the combined work is GPLv3&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>GPL v2&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>The Apache 2.0 patent clause is considered an &amp;ldquo;additional restriction&amp;rdquo; under GPLv2&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>LGPL v3&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes (one direction)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Similar to GPLv3 compatibility&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>MPL 2.0&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>MPL 2.0 was explicitly designed for compatibility&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>AGPL v3&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes (one direction)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Apache 2.0 code can be included in AGPLv3 projects&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The GPLv2 incompatibility is historically significant. It means you cannot combine Apache 2.0 code with GPLv2-only code (like the Linux kernel) in a single work. This was one of the issues addressed when GPLv3 was designed to be compatible with Apache 2.0.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="apache-license-20-vs-mit-vs-gpl">Apache License 2.0 vs. MIT vs. GPL&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>These are the three most commonly encountered open source licenses. Understanding their differences is essential for license compliance.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Feature&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Apache 2.0&lt;/th>
&lt;th>MIT&lt;/th>
&lt;th>GPL v3&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>License type&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Permissive&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Permissive&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Copyleft&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Patent grant&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Explicit&lt;/td>
&lt;td>None&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Explicit&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Source code required&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes (for distributed works)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Derivative works license&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Any license&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Any license&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Must be GPL&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Attribution required&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes (NOTICE file)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes (license text)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes (license text + source)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Commercial use&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>SPDX identifier&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>Apache-2.0&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>MIT&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>GPL-3.0-only&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>For organizations that want permissive licensing with patent protection, Apache 2.0 is the standard choice. For projects that prioritize simplicity and brevity, MIT is often preferred. For projects that want to ensure all derivatives remain open source, GPL is the appropriate choice.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For a broader overview of open source licenses, see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2024/04/03/navigating-the-landscape-of-open-source-licenses/">guide to navigating the landscape of open source licenses&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-sboms-track-apache-license-compliance">How SBOMs Track Apache License Compliance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/what-is-sbom/">Software Bill of Materials&lt;/a> documents every component in your software along with its license. For Apache-licensed components, SBOMs support compliance in several ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Identifying Apache-licensed dependencies.&lt;/strong> SBOMs include license information for each component, making it straightforward to identify all Apache 2.0 dependencies in your project. The SPDX identifier &lt;code>Apache-2.0&lt;/code> provides machine-readable identification.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTICE file tracking.&lt;/strong> By identifying which components are Apache-licensed, SBOMs help teams ensure they are carrying forward all required NOTICE file attributions.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Compatibility checking.&lt;/strong> Automated license compliance tools can process SBOMs to detect potential compatibility conflicts — for example, flagging if Apache 2.0 and GPLv2-only components coexist in the same project.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Audit trail.&lt;/strong> SBOMs provide the evidence that organizations need for license audits and due diligence in M&amp;amp;A transactions, documenting exactly which licenses are present in a software product.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Both &lt;a href="https://cyclonedx.org/">CycloneDX&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://spdx.dev/">SPDX&lt;/a> support standardized license fields. The &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/cisa-minimum-elements/">CISA minimum elements draft&lt;/a> includes license as a recommended SBOM field, recognizing that license information is increasingly expected in SBOMs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action/">sbomify GitHub Action&lt;/a> automatically enriches SBOMs with license data from multiple sources, making it straightforward to identify all Apache-licensed components in your dependency tree. For language-specific instructions, see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/">SBOM generation guides&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="frequently-asked-questions">Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-the-apache-license-20-1">What is the Apache License 2.0?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The Apache License 2.0 is a permissive open source license published by the Apache Software Foundation. It allows free use, modification, distribution, and sublicensing of the software, including in proprietary products. Its key features are an explicit patent grant protecting users from contributor patent claims, and a NOTICE file mechanism for managing attribution requirements.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="can-i-use-apache-20-licensed-software-in-commercial-products">Can I use Apache 2.0 licensed software in commercial products?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Yes. The Apache License 2.0 explicitly permits commercial use, including incorporating Apache-licensed code into proprietary, closed-source products. The only requirements are that you include the Apache license text, retain attribution notices, include the NOTICE file if one exists, and note any modifications you made to the original files.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-the-difference-between-apache-20-and-mit">What is the difference between Apache 2.0 and MIT?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Both are permissive licenses that allow commercial use without requiring source code disclosure. The key differences are: Apache 2.0 includes an explicit patent grant and patent retaliation clause, while MIT does not address patents; Apache 2.0 requires carrying forward NOTICE file attributions, while MIT only requires including the license text; and Apache 2.0 requires stating changes to modified files, while MIT does not.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="is-apache-20-compatible-with-the-gpl">Is Apache 2.0 compatible with the GPL?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Apache 2.0 is compatible with GPL v3 but NOT with GPL v2. Apache 2.0 code can be included in a GPLv3 project (the combined work is licensed under GPLv3), but the Apache 2.0 patent termination clause is considered an &amp;ldquo;additional restriction&amp;rdquo; under GPLv2, making the two licenses incompatible. This distinction matters for projects like the Linux kernel, which is GPLv2-only.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-the-notice-file-in-the-apache-license">What is the NOTICE file in the Apache License?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The NOTICE file is a text file that Apache-licensed projects use to collect attribution notices. It contains the project name, copyright notices, and any third-party attributions required by dependencies. When you redistribute Apache-licensed software, you must include the contents of the NOTICE file with your distribution. Failure to carry forward NOTICE attributions is a common compliance oversight.&lt;/p></description><category>education</category></item><item><title>CRA Explained: What the Cyber Resilience Act Means for Device Manufacturers</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/06/cra-explained-cyber-resilience-act-for-device-manufacturers/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/06/cra-explained-cyber-resilience-act-for-device-manufacturers/</guid><description>&lt;p>The EU Cyber Resilience Act (CRA) is transforming how device manufacturers approach cybersecurity. To break down what this means in practice, Viktor sat down with Sarah Fluchs on the Nerding Out with Viktor podcast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sarah isn&amp;rsquo;t just any commentator on the CRA - she serves on the &lt;strong>EU Commission&amp;rsquo;s CRA expert group&lt;/strong>, giving her first-hand involvement in shaping this landmark regulation. With a PhD in security-by-design and years of experience in OT (Operational Technology) cybersecurity, she brings a rare blend of technical depth and policy insight.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="video-embed-wrapper my-8 w-full max-w-3xl mx-auto">
&lt;div class="relative w-full overflow-hidden rounded-xl sm:rounded-2xl shadow-lg" style="padding-bottom: 56.25%;">
&lt;iframe
class="absolute top-0 left-0 w-full h-full border-0"
src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/e9_bpsJKOL0"
title="CRA Explained: Cyber Resilience Act for Device Manufacturers"
allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share"
referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin"
allowfullscreen
loading="lazy">
&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;script type="application/ld+json">
{
"@context": "https://schema.org",
"@type": "VideoObject",
"name": "CRA Explained: Cyber Resilience Act for Device Manufacturers",
"description": "Podcast episode with EU CRA expert Sarah Fluchs explaining SBOM requirements, the 5-year support mandate, and vulnerability management for device manufacturers.",
"thumbnailUrl": "https://img.youtube.com/vi/e9_bpsJKOL0/maxresdefault.jpg",
"uploadDate": "2026-01-06T00:00:00Z",
"embedUrl": "https://www.youtube.com/embed/e9_bpsJKOL0",
"contentUrl": "https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e9_bpsJKOL0"
}
&lt;/script>
&lt;h2 id="sboms-are-non-negotiable-for-cra-compliance">SBOMs Are Non-Negotiable for CRA Compliance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Sarah is emphatic: &lt;strong>SBOMs are critical for CRA compliance&lt;/strong>. The regulation requires manufacturers to maintain full visibility into their software supply chain, and SBOMs are the mechanism to achieve this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But generating quality SBOMs is only half the battle. The real challenge lies in managing them over time - tracking versions, maintaining audit trails, and making software components traceable across complex supply chains. For manufacturers of long-lifecycle hardware, this represents a fundamental operational shift.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is exactly where proper tooling becomes essential. A platform like &lt;a href="">sbomify&lt;/a> addresses these challenges by providing:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Lifecycle management&lt;/strong> - Archive and track SBOMs across product versions and releases&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Centralized portal&lt;/strong> - Manage all your security artifacts in one place, with full version history&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Trust Center&lt;/strong> - Share SBOMs with stakeholders (customers, auditors, regulators) through a branded portal&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CI/CD integration&lt;/strong> - Generate SBOMs automatically in your pipeline and upload them to sbomify&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="the-5-year-support-requirement-changes-everything">The 5-Year Support Requirement Changes Everything&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The CRA mandates security updates for the expected product lifetime, with a &lt;strong>minimum of five years&lt;/strong>. For OT devices that often operate for 20+ years, this forces companies to fundamentally rethink their approach.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This isn&amp;rsquo;t just about patching - it&amp;rsquo;s about maintaining comprehensive records of what software was shipped, when, and to whom. You need to be able to answer: &amp;ldquo;What components were in version 2.3.1 that we shipped in 2024?&amp;rdquo; years down the line.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is where SBOM archiving becomes critical. With sbomify, every release is captured and stored, creating an auditable trail that satisfies CRA&amp;rsquo;s documentation requirements without manual tracking.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="vulnerability-management-at-scale">Vulnerability Management at Scale&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Manufacturers must establish robust vulnerability handling processes, including responsible disclosure mechanisms. Sarah notes that the hardest part isn&amp;rsquo;t formal reporting - it&amp;rsquo;s building an efficient system to triage the influx of vulnerability reports.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>sbomify integrates with vulnerability databases like &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/integrations/">Google OSV&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/integrations/">Dependency Track&lt;/a>, allowing you to continuously monitor your archived SBOMs for newly discovered vulnerabilities - even for products shipped years ago.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sarahs-key-message">Sarah&amp;rsquo;s Key Message&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;CRA compliance isn&amp;rsquo;t about ticking boxes. Done right, it&amp;rsquo;s a path to stronger engineering practices, deeper supply chain accountability, and better product security.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Her advice for manufacturers getting started:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Find your showstoppers early&lt;/strong> - Run your products through the CRA requirements now to identify major blockers&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Start your risk assessment&lt;/strong> - This is the linchpin that informs all other decisions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Establish vulnerability handling&lt;/strong> - Build the processes to manage the influx of security information&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="listen-to-the-full-episode">Listen to the Full Episode&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://vpetersson.com/podcast/S02E21.html">Full episode with transcript&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e9_bpsJKOL0">YouTube&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://open.spotify.com/show/2eoSJgEN0YOgshqYkqnX2B">Spotify&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/podcast/nerding-out-with-viktor/id1722663668">Apple Podcasts&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://music.amazon.com/podcasts/c2443912-6c23-4ce9-804c-4caa827f63d7/nerding-out-with-viktor">Amazon Music&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="get-cra-ready-with-sbomify">Get CRA-Ready with sbomify&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The CRA deadline is approaching fast. &lt;a href="">sbomify&lt;/a> gives you the infrastructure to generate, manage, and share SBOMs throughout your product lifecycle - whether you&amp;rsquo;re shipping embedded devices, IoT products, or enterprise software.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://app.sbomify.com">Get started free →&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="related-resources">Related Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/policies/cyber-resilience-act">EU Cyber Resilience Act - Official EU page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/why-now/">Why Now? CRA is Coming&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2024/07/10/understanding-the-eu-cyber-resilience-act-the-role-of-sboms-in-enhancing-cybersecurity/">Understanding the EU Cyber Resilience Act: The Role of SBOMs&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description><category>podcast</category></item><item><title>The GPL License: A Comprehensive Guide to the GNU General Public License</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2025/12/22/gpl-license-guide/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2025/12/22/gpl-license-guide/</guid><description>&lt;p>The GPL (GNU General Public License) is a free software license that guarantees end users the freedom to run, study, modify, and share software. Created by Richard Stallman and the Free Software Foundation (FSF), the GPL is the most widely used copyleft license in open source software. Its defining characteristic is the copyleft requirement: any derivative work must also be distributed under the GPL, ensuring that the freedoms it grants are preserved downstream.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-gpl">What Is the GPL?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The GNU General Public License, commonly called the GPL or GNU GPL, is a series of free software licenses published by the &lt;a href="https://www.fsf.org/">Free Software Foundation&lt;/a> (FSF). The GPL was first written by Richard Stallman in 1989 for the GNU Project and has since become the most prominent copyleft license in the world.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The core idea behind the GPL is simple: software licensed under the GPL can be freely used, modified, and distributed, but anyone who distributes modified versions must also make their source code available under the same GPL terms. This &amp;ldquo;share-alike&amp;rdquo; obligation is what distinguishes copyleft licenses from permissive licenses like &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/22/mit-license-guide/">MIT&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/07/apache-license-2-guide/">Apache 2.0&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The GPL family includes three major versions and two important variants:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>GPL v2&lt;/strong> (1991) — The version that popularized copyleft; still used by the Linux kernel&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>GPL v3&lt;/strong> (2007) — Updated to address patents, tivoization, and international compatibility&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>LGPL&lt;/strong> (Lesser GPL) — A weaker copyleft for libraries, allowing proprietary linking&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>AGPL&lt;/strong> (Affero GPL) — Extends copyleft to software accessed over a network&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="gpl-v2-vs-gpl-v3-key-differences">GPL v2 vs. GPL v3: Key Differences&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Understanding the differences between GPL version 2 and version 3 matters because they have different implications for commercial use and distribution.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Feature&lt;/th>
&lt;th>GPL v2 (1991)&lt;/th>
&lt;th>GPL v3 (2007)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Patent grant&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Implicit (not explicit)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Explicit patent license from contributors&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Tivoization protection&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes — prevents hardware that blocks modified software from running&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Anti-DRM provisions&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes — modified GPL software cannot be locked down by DRM&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>License compatibility&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Narrower&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Broader — compatible with Apache 2.0, for example&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Internationalization&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>US-centric language&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Jurisdiction-neutral terminology&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Installation information&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Not required&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Required for &amp;ldquo;User Products&amp;rdquo; (consumer devices)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Notable users&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Linux kernel, Git, WordPress (v2 or later)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>GCC, GNU Bash, Samba&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>GPL v2 includes a clause that allows licensees to use &amp;ldquo;version 2 or any later version,&amp;rdquo; but this is optional — the copyright holder can specify &amp;ldquo;GPL v2 only.&amp;rdquo; The Linux kernel, for instance, is licensed under &amp;ldquo;GPL v2 only&amp;rdquo; because Linus Torvalds chose not to adopt v3.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>GPL v3 was designed to close perceived loopholes in v2. The anti-tivoization provisions were a direct response to devices (like TiVo) that used GPL software but locked the hardware to prevent users from running modified versions. The explicit patent grant protects users and developers from patent litigation by contributors.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="understanding-copyleft">Understanding Copyleft&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Copyleft is the legal mechanism that makes the GPL distinctive. While copyright restricts copying and modification by default, copyleft uses copyright law to ensure that freedoms are preserved. Under a copyleft license:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>You can use, modify, and distribute the software freely&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you distribute the software (modified or unmodified), you must provide the source code&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Your distribution must be under the same license terms&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You cannot add restrictions beyond what the license specifies&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>This creates a &amp;ldquo;viral&amp;rdquo; effect: GPL code that enters a project tends to make the whole project (or at least the derivative portions) subject to the GPL. This is the characteristic that makes commercial adoption of GPL software more complex than permissive-licensed alternatives.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-counts-as-a-derivative-work">What Counts as a Derivative Work?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This is the most debated question in GPL compliance. The GPL requires that &amp;ldquo;the work as a whole&amp;rdquo; be licensed under the GPL if it is based on GPL-licensed code. But what exactly constitutes a derivative work?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Generally accepted interpretations:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Modifying GPL source code and distributing it&lt;/strong> — clearly a derivative work&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Statically linking against a GPL library&lt;/strong> — generally considered a derivative work&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dynamically linking against a GPL library&lt;/strong> — debated; the FSF considers it a derivative work, others disagree&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Using a GPL command-line tool in your build process&lt;/strong> — generally not a derivative work (the tool&amp;rsquo;s output is yours)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Using a GPL library as a separate process via IPC&lt;/strong> — generally not a derivative work&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The LGPL was created specifically to address the library linking question.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-lgpl-lesser-gpl-for-libraries">The LGPL: Lesser GPL for Libraries&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The GNU Lesser General Public License (LGPL) is a modified version of the GPL designed for software libraries. The LGPL allows proprietary software to link against LGPL-licensed libraries without the copyleft obligation applying to the proprietary code.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Under the LGPL:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>You can use the library in proprietary software without releasing your source code&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you modify the LGPL library itself, those modifications must be released under the LGPL&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You must allow users to replace the LGPL library with modified versions (e.g., via dynamic linking)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Common LGPL-licensed projects include the GNU C Library (glibc), Qt (available under both LGPL and commercial licenses), and many Java libraries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The LGPL is a pragmatic compromise: it keeps the library itself free while allowing commercial adoption that would be impractical under the full GPL.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-agpl-closing-the-network-loophole">The AGPL: Closing the Network Loophole&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The GNU Affero General Public License (AGPL) adds one significant provision to GPL v3: if you run modified AGPL software as a network service (such as a web application), you must make the modified source code available to users who interact with the software over the network.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Under the standard GPL, the copyleft obligation is triggered by &lt;em>distribution&lt;/em>. Running software on a server and letting users access it via a browser is not distribution — the users never receive a copy of the software. The AGPL closes this gap by treating network interaction as equivalent to distribution for the purpose of source code availability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>AGPL is commonly used by companies that offer open source software as a service but want to prevent competitors from running modified versions without contributing back. Notable AGPL projects include MongoDB (before its switch to SSPL), Grafana, and Nextcloud.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="gpl-and-commercial-use">GPL and Commercial Use&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A common misconception is that the GPL prohibits commercial use. It does not. The GPL explicitly allows commercial use, distribution, and even sale of GPL-licensed software. What it restricts is the ability to make the software proprietary.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="can-you-sell-gpl-software">Can You Sell GPL Software?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Yes. You can sell copies of GPL software, charge for support, or sell services around GPL software. The FSF itself has always supported commercial free software. The key constraint is that buyers must receive the same freedoms: the source code and the right to modify and redistribute.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="commercial-strategies-with-gpl-software">Commercial Strategies with GPL Software&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Organizations commonly take one of these approaches:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dual licensing&lt;/strong> — Offer the software under both the GPL (for open source users) and a commercial license (for proprietary users who want to avoid copyleft obligations). MySQL, Qt, and many others use this model.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Open core&lt;/strong> — Release the core product under the GPL and sell proprietary extensions or enterprise features under a commercial license.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Services and support&lt;/strong> — Distribute the software under the GPL and monetize through consulting, support contracts, and managed hosting. Red Hat built a multi-billion dollar business on this model.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>SaaS delivery&lt;/strong> — Run GPL software on your own servers without triggering the distribution clause (though this doesn&amp;rsquo;t apply to AGPL software).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="gpl-compliance-in-practice">GPL Compliance in Practice&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>GPL compliance requires careful attention to three areas: distribution, source code availability, and license notices.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="when-you-distribute-gpl-software">When You Distribute GPL Software&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>If you distribute GPL-licensed software (binary or source), you must:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Include a copy of the GPL license text&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Include copyright notices and any warranty disclaimers&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Provide the complete corresponding source code (or a written offer to provide it)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>License the whole work under the GPL (for derivative works)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="source-code-requirements">Source Code Requirements&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The source code you provide must be the &amp;ldquo;complete corresponding source&amp;rdquo; — everything needed to build the binary, including build scripts, interface definition files, and any shared libraries. For GPL v3, this extends to &amp;ldquo;Installation Information&amp;rdquo; for consumer products (the anti-tivoization clause).&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="common-compliance-failures">Common Compliance Failures&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Distributing binaries without source code or a valid written offer&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Failing to include the license text with distributed software&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Adding restrictions that the GPL does not permit (e.g., &amp;ldquo;no commercial use&amp;rdquo; clauses)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Confusing GPL v2 and GPL v3 obligations in mixed-license codebases&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="how-sboms-track-gpl-license-compliance">How SBOMs Track GPL License Compliance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/what-is-sbom/">Software Bill of Materials&lt;/a> plays a critical role in license compliance by documenting every component in your software along with its license. This is essential for GPL compliance because:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Identifying GPL components.&lt;/strong> SBOMs include license information for each component, making it straightforward to determine whether your project includes any GPL-licensed dependencies. The &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/cisa-minimum-elements/">CISA minimum elements draft&lt;/a> now includes license as a recommended SBOM field.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Tracking copyleft obligations.&lt;/strong> When an SBOM shows a GPL-licensed component, your legal and engineering teams can assess whether the copyleft obligation applies to your distribution model. This is especially important for complex dependency trees with dozens or hundreds of transitive dependencies.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Automating license audits.&lt;/strong> Tools that process SBOMs can automatically flag components with copyleft licenses, allowing organizations to enforce license policies in their CI/CD pipeline. This is far more reliable than manual code review for license compliance.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Supporting dual-license decisions.&lt;/strong> When a component is available under both GPL and a commercial license, the SBOM documents which license applies to your specific use.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Both &lt;a href="https://cyclonedx.org/">CycloneDX&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://spdx.dev/">SPDX&lt;/a> (which originated as a license documentation format) include standardized license fields. SPDX license expressions (e.g., &lt;code>GPL-2.0-only&lt;/code>, &lt;code>GPL-3.0-or-later&lt;/code>, &lt;code>LGPL-2.1-or-later&lt;/code>) provide machine-readable license identifiers that make automated compliance checking possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action/">sbomify GitHub Action&lt;/a> automatically enriches SBOMs with license data from multiple sources (including its LicenseDB covering 28 Linux distro versions), making GPL identification reliable even for system-level packages. For language-specific instructions, see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/">SBOM generation guides&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="gpl-license-comparison-table">GPL License Comparison Table&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>License&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Copyleft Strength&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Commercial Use&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Library Linking&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Network Use Trigger&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Patent Grant&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>GPL v2&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Strong&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Copyleft applies&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Implicit&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>GPL v3&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Strong&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Copyleft applies&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Explicit&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>LGPL v2.1&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Weak (library)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Allowed (proprietary)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Implicit&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>LGPL v3&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Weak (library)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Allowed (proprietary)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Explicit&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>AGPL v3&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Strong + network&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Copyleft applies&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Explicit&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>MIT&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>None (permissive)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No restrictions&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Apache 2.0&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>None (permissive)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No restrictions&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Explicit&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>For a broader overview of open source licenses, see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2024/04/03/navigating-the-landscape-of-open-source-licenses/">guide to navigating the landscape of open source licenses&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="frequently-asked-questions">Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-the-gpl-license">What is the GPL license?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The GPL (GNU General Public License) is a copyleft free software license created by the Free Software Foundation. It guarantees that users can run, study, modify, and distribute the software, with the condition that any distributed derivative works must also be licensed under the GPL and include source code. It is the most widely used copyleft license in open source software.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="can-i-use-gpl-software-in-commercial-products">Can I use GPL software in commercial products?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Yes. The GPL explicitly permits commercial use, distribution, and sale. The restriction is not on commerce but on making the software proprietary. If you distribute a product that includes GPL code, you must make the complete source code available under the GPL. Common commercial strategies include dual licensing, open core models, and selling services around GPL software.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-the-difference-between-gpl-and-lgpl">What is the difference between GPL and LGPL?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The GPL requires that any derivative work be distributed under the GPL (strong copyleft). The LGPL (Lesser GPL) allows proprietary software to link against LGPL-licensed libraries without the copyleft applying to the proprietary code. If you modify the LGPL library itself, those modifications must be shared, but your application code that uses the library can remain proprietary.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-the-difference-between-gpl-v2-and-gpl-v3">What is the difference between GPL v2 and GPL v3?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>GPL v3 (2007) added explicit patent grants, anti-tivoization provisions (preventing hardware lockdown of modified software), anti-DRM clauses, broader international compatibility, and better compatibility with other open source licenses like Apache 2.0. GPL v2 (1991) remains widely used, notably by the Linux kernel, which is licensed under &amp;ldquo;GPL v2 only.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="how-do-sboms-help-with-gpl-compliance">How do SBOMs help with GPL compliance?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SBOMs document every component in your software along with its license, making it possible to automatically identify GPL-licensed dependencies, track copyleft obligations, and enforce license policies in CI/CD pipelines. Both CycloneDX and SPDX include standardized license fields that support machine-readable GPL license identification using SPDX license expressions like &lt;code>GPL-2.0-only&lt;/code> or &lt;code>GPL-3.0-or-later&lt;/code>.&lt;/p></description><category>education</category></item><item><title>Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC): A Complete Guide</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2025/12/15/software-development-life-cycle-sdlc-sbom-integration/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2025/12/15/software-development-life-cycle-sdlc-sbom-integration/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC) is a structured process that defines the stages involved in developing software from initial concept through deployment and maintenance. SDLC provides a systematic framework that development teams use to plan, create, test, and deliver high-quality software. Understanding the SDLC is essential for any organization building software today, particularly as security and compliance requirements become integral to every phase of development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://sbomify.com/assets/images/d2/sdlc-sbom.svg" alt="SDLC phases with SBOM integration points">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-software-development-life-cycle">What Is the Software Development Life Cycle?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>SDLC, short for Software Development Life Cycle, is a methodology used by software engineering teams to design, develop, and test software in a predictable and efficient manner. Rather than writing code ad hoc, SDLC defined processes ensure that each stage of development has clear objectives, deliverables, and quality checks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The concept of a structured development life cycle emerged in the 1960s as software projects grew in complexity. What began as a simple sequential process has evolved into a family of software development life cycle models, each suited to different project types and organizational needs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At its core, every SDLC framework answers the same questions: What are we building? How will we build it? How do we know it works? And how do we keep it running?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-phases-of-the-sdlc">The Phases of the SDLC&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>While specific terminology varies between models, most SDLC frameworks include six to eight phases. Here are the core stages that appear in virtually every approach.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="1-planning-and-requirements-analysis">1. Planning and Requirements Analysis&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The first phase involves gathering business requirements, identifying stakeholders, and defining project scope. Teams assess feasibility, estimate resources, and create a project plan. Security considerations should enter the picture here through threat modeling and risk assessment.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="2-system-design">2. System Design&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Architects and senior developers translate requirements into a technical blueprint. This includes system architecture, technology stack selection, data models, and interface specifications. Design decisions made here have long-lasting implications for security and maintainability.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="3-implementation-coding">3. Implementation (Coding)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Developers write the actual source code based on the design specifications. This phase typically involves selecting libraries, frameworks, and third-party components. These &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/29/what-is-a-dependency-in-software/">dependency&lt;/a> choices directly impact the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2025/12/26/software-supply-chain-management/">software supply chain&lt;/a> and are the foundation of what an &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/what-is-sbom/">SBOM&lt;/a> will eventually document.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="4-testing">4. Testing&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Quality assurance teams verify that the software meets requirements and is free of defects. Testing includes unit tests, integration tests, system tests, and user acceptance testing. Security testing, including vulnerability scanning and penetration testing, is increasingly part of this phase.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="5-deployment">5. Deployment&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The tested software is released to production environments. Deployment strategies such as blue-green deployments, canary releases, and rolling updates help reduce risk. This phase is where CI/CD pipelines automate the build, test, and release process.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="6-maintenance-and-operations">6. Maintenance and Operations&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>After deployment, teams monitor the application, fix bugs, apply security patches, and release updates. This phase often lasts the longest and is where vulnerability management and ongoing compliance activities take place.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="software-development-life-cycle-models">Software Development Life Cycle Models&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Over the decades, several SDLC models have emerged to address different project needs. Each model organizes the core phases differently.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Model&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Approach&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Best Suited For&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Key Characteristic&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Waterfall&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Sequential, linear&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Well-defined projects with stable requirements&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Each phase completes before the next begins&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Agile&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Iterative, incremental&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Projects with evolving requirements&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Short sprints, continuous feedback&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Spiral&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Risk-driven, iterative&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Large, high-risk projects&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Risk analysis at every iteration&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>V-Model&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Verification and validation&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Safety-critical and regulated systems&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Each development phase has a corresponding test phase&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>DevOps&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Continuous integration and delivery&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Fast-moving organizations&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Merges development and operations&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Lean&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Waste elimination&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Startups and rapid prototyping&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Minimize overhead, maximize value&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The Waterfall model was the original SDLC approach, moving linearly from requirements through deployment. Agile methodologies, including Scrum and Kanban, replaced the rigid sequential approach with iterative cycles that deliver working software in short sprints. Most modern teams use some form of Agile combined with DevOps practices.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="where-security-fits-from-sdlc-to-secure-sdlc">Where Security Fits: From SDLC to Secure SDLC&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Traditional SDLC models treated security as a gate at the end of development — a final check before release. This approach consistently proved inadequate. Vulnerabilities discovered late in the cycle are far more expensive to fix than those caught early.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Secure Software Development Life Cycle (SSDLC or Secure SDLC) integrates security activities into every phase:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Planning:&lt;/strong> Threat modeling, security requirements definition&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Design:&lt;/strong> Security architecture review, attack surface analysis&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Implementation:&lt;/strong> Secure coding standards, dependency management, SBOM generation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Testing:&lt;/strong> Static Application Security Testing (SAST), Dynamic Application Security Testing (DAST), &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/11/software-composition-analysis-sca/">Software Composition Analysis (SCA)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Deployment:&lt;/strong> Configuration hardening, secrets management, SBOM distribution&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Maintenance:&lt;/strong> Vulnerability monitoring, patch management, SBOM updates&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This shift-left approach — moving security earlier in the development process — is central to &lt;a href="https://www.nist.gov/publications/devsecops-nist-special-publication-800-218-secure-software-development-framework-ssdf">DevSecOps&lt;/a>, where security becomes a shared responsibility across the entire team rather than a bottleneck at the end.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sdlc-and-sboms-integration-at-every-phase">SDLC and SBOMs: Integration at Every Phase&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/what-is-sbom/">Software Bill of Materials&lt;/a> (SBOM) documents every component, library, and dependency in a piece of software. Rather than treating SBOM generation as a one-time event, modern organizations integrate SBOMs throughout the SDLC.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="during-implementation">During Implementation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When developers add dependencies — open source libraries, frameworks, and packages — they shape the software&amp;rsquo;s composition. This is the moment to begin tracking what goes into the build. Tools like the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action/">sbomify GitHub Action&lt;/a> can generate SBOMs automatically as part of the build process. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/">SBOM generation guides&lt;/a> for language-specific instructions covering Python, JavaScript, Java, Go, Rust, and more.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="during-testing">During Testing&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SBOMs enable automated &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/02/01/sbom-scanning-vulnerability-detection/">vulnerability scanning&lt;/a>. Once you have a complete inventory of components, platforms like &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com">sbomify&lt;/a> can continuously monitor your SBOMs against vulnerability databases. Standalone tools like &lt;a href="https://github.com/anchore/grype">Grype&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://dependencytrack.org/">OWASP Dependency-Track&lt;/a> can also cross-reference your SBOM against the &lt;a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/">National Vulnerability Database&lt;/a> (NVD) and &lt;a href="https://osv.dev/">OSV&lt;/a>. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/resources/">resources page&lt;/a> for a complete list of SBOM generation and analysis tools.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="during-deployment">During Deployment&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The SBOM becomes a release artifact alongside the software itself. Compliance frameworks including the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eu-cra/">EU Cyber Resilience Act&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eo-14028/">Executive Order 14028&lt;/a> require SBOMs to be available to downstream consumers. Signing the SBOM provides tamper-evidence for the supply chain.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="during-maintenance">During Maintenance&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>As new vulnerabilities are discovered — often months or years after deployment — SBOMs allow organizations to quickly determine whether they are affected. When the &lt;a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/CVE-2021-44228">Log4Shell vulnerability&lt;/a> was disclosed in December 2021, organizations with SBOMs could identify affected systems in minutes rather than weeks.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sdlc-best-practices-for-modern-teams">SDLC Best Practices for Modern Teams&lt;/h2>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Choose the right model for your context.&lt;/strong> Agile works well for most web and cloud applications. V-Model or Spiral may be more appropriate for safety-critical systems in medical devices or automotive software.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Shift security left.&lt;/strong> Integrate threat modeling in planning, dependency review in implementation, and automated security testing in CI/CD. Catching vulnerabilities early saves time and reduces risk.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Automate everything repeatable.&lt;/strong> Use CI/CD pipelines to automate builds, tests, security scans, SBOM generation, and deployments. Manual processes introduce inconsistency and slow the cycle.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Track your dependencies.&lt;/strong> Every third-party library is a potential risk vector. Maintain SBOMs, monitor for vulnerabilities, and have a process for updating or replacing compromised components.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Build compliance into the workflow.&lt;/strong> Rather than scrambling for compliance at audit time, embed &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/">SBOM generation&lt;/a> and vulnerability scanning into your standard SDLC process. This is especially critical for organizations subject to the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/ntia-minimum-elements/">NTIA minimum elements&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/cisa-minimum-elements/">CISA guidance&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Measure and improve.&lt;/strong> Track metrics like lead time, deployment frequency, mean time to recovery, and vulnerability remediation time. Use retrospectives to continuously improve the process.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="nist-and-the-sdlc">NIST and the SDLC&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) has published several frameworks relevant to securing the SDLC:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://csrc.nist.gov/pubs/sp/800/218/final">NIST SP 800-218&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> (Secure Software Development Framework, SSDF) provides practices for integrating security into the development process, organized into four groups: Prepare the Organization, Protect the Software, Produce Well-Secured Software, and Respond to Vulnerabilities.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://csrc.nist.gov/pubs/sp/800/53/r5/upd1/final">NIST SP 800-53&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> includes the SA (System and Services Acquisition) and SR (Supply Chain Risk Management) control families that directly address SDLC security controls.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://www.nist.gov/cyberframework">NIST Cybersecurity Framework 2.0&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> provides a high-level structure for managing cybersecurity risk that maps to SDLC activities.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>These frameworks are increasingly referenced in procurement requirements and regulatory compliance, making them essential reading for teams working on government or critical infrastructure projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="frequently-asked-questions">Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-sdlc-in-software-development">What is SDLC in software development?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SDLC stands for Software Development Life Cycle. It is a structured process that guides software development from initial planning through deployment and ongoing maintenance. The SDLC provides a framework of phases — including requirements analysis, design, implementation, testing, deployment, and maintenance — that help teams deliver reliable software in a systematic way.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-are-the-most-common-sdlc-models">What are the most common SDLC models?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The most widely used software development life cycle models are Waterfall, Agile (including Scrum and Kanban), DevOps, V-Model, Spiral, and Lean. Agile and DevOps are the most popular for modern web and cloud applications due to their iterative approach and emphasis on continuous delivery.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="how-do-sboms-fit-into-the-sdlc">How do SBOMs fit into the SDLC?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SBOMs integrate into multiple SDLC phases. During implementation, SBOM generation tools capture component inventories. During testing, SBOMs enable automated vulnerability scanning. During deployment, SBOMs are distributed alongside release artifacts for compliance. During maintenance, SBOMs allow rapid identification of affected systems when new vulnerabilities are disclosed. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/">SBOM generation guides&lt;/a> for language-specific integration steps.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-the-difference-between-sdlc-and-devops">What is the difference between SDLC and DevOps?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SDLC is the overall process framework for software development, while DevOps is a specific approach that emphasizes collaboration between development and operations teams with a focus on automation, continuous integration, and continuous delivery. DevOps can be seen as a modern SDLC model rather than an alternative to the SDLC concept itself.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-a-secure-sdlc">What is a Secure SDLC?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>A Secure SDLC (sometimes called SSDLC) integrates security practices into every phase of the software development life cycle, rather than treating security as a final checkpoint. This includes threat modeling during planning, secure coding standards during implementation, SAST/DAST during testing, and vulnerability monitoring during maintenance. NIST SP 800-218 (SSDF) provides a standardized framework for implementing a Secure SDLC.&lt;/p></description><category>education</category></item><item><title>The Role of SBOMs in an OBOM: Ensuring Compliance and Security in Smart Thermometer Development</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2024/07/09/the-role-of-sboms-in-an-obom-ensuring-compliance-and-security-in-smart-thermometer-development/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 15:04:57 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2024/07/09/the-role-of-sboms-in-an-obom-ensuring-compliance-and-security-in-smart-thermometer-development/</guid><description>&lt;p>In today&amp;rsquo;s software landscape, compliance with security and transparency mandates is more critical than ever. Executive orders, such as the one issued by the U.S. government in May 2021, emphasize the importance of Software Bill of Materials (SBOMs) for ensuring software security and integrity. While SBOMs provide detailed inventories of software components, integrating them into an Operations Bill of Materials (OBOM) offers an enhanced framework that encompasses both software and runtime operational dependencies. This article explores the central role of SBOMs in OBOMs, using the development of a smart thermometer as an example, and discusses how this integration ensures compliance and bolsters security.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="understanding-sboms">Understanding SBOMs&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-an-sbom">What is an SBOM?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>A Software Bill of Materials (SBOM) is a formal record that lists all components, libraries, and modules included in a software product. It provides a transparent view of the software’s codebase, aiding in dependency tracking, license management, and vulnerability identification. According to recent executive orders, SBOMs are essential for maintaining software security and transparency.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="example-smart-thermometer-development">Example: Smart Thermometer Development&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="components-of-the-smart-thermometer">Components of the Smart Thermometer&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Python Backend&lt;/strong>: The backend server written in Python, which handles data processing and user interactions.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Docker Files&lt;/strong>: Containerization files used to ensure consistent deployment environments.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Device Software&lt;/strong>: Firmware written in Rust, running on the thermometer device, which includes dependencies specific to the embedded system.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="central-role-of-sboms-in-oboms">Central Role of SBOMs in OBOMs&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="aggregated-sbom-for-compliance">Aggregated SBOM for Compliance&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In the context of a smart thermometer, an aggregated SBOM provides a comprehensive inventory of all software components involved:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Backend SBOM&lt;/strong>: Listing Python libraries and dependencies.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Container SBOM&lt;/strong>: Including Docker configurations and base images.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Device SBOM&lt;/strong>: Documenting Rust dependencies and embedded libraries.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="integrating-sboms-into-oboms">Integrating SBOMs into OBOMs&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>An OBOM incorporates these SBOMs and extends them by adding runtime operational information:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Runtime Dependencies&lt;/strong>: Specific libraries and services required for the backend and device software to function during runtime.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Configuration Settings&lt;/strong>: Environment variables, configuration files, and system settings necessary for deployment and operation.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Infrastructure Components&lt;/strong>: Details about cloud servers, network configurations, and other infrastructure elements.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Operational Tools&lt;/strong>: Monitoring, logging, and backup tools essential for maintaining the operational integrity of the system.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="benefits-of-sbom-integration">Benefits of SBOM Integration&lt;/h3>
&lt;h4 id="enhanced-security-and-compliance">Enhanced Security and Compliance&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Example: Comprehensive Vulnerability Management&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Integrating SBOMs within an OBOM allows for detailed tracking of both software and operational components, ensuring compliance with security standards outlined in executive orders. For the smart thermometer, this means that any vulnerabilities identified in the Python libraries, Docker images, or Rust dependencies can be promptly addressed, ensuring the overall security of the product.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="operational-transparency">Operational Transparency&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Example: Detailed Auditing and Compliance&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An aggregated SBOM within an OBOM provides a transparent view of all software and runtime components used in the smart thermometer, facilitating easier audits and ensuring compliance with regulatory standards. This transparency is crucial for meeting the requirements set by executive orders, which mandate visibility into software supply chains.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="obom-as-a-value-added-extension">OBOM as a Value-Added Extension&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="runtime-information">Runtime Information&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>While the SBOM is central to compliance, incorporating it into an OBOM adds valuable runtime information:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Runtime Dependencies&lt;/strong>: Ensuring that all necessary libraries and services are available and correctly configured during the operation of the smart thermometer.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Configuration Management&lt;/strong>: Detailed documentation of environment variables, configuration files, and system settings for consistent deployments across different environments.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="enhancing-security-and-efficiency-with-obom">Enhancing Security and Efficiency with OBOM&lt;/h3>
&lt;h4 id="streamlined-deployment">Streamlined Deployment&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>By integrating SBOMs into an OBOM, the smart thermometer’s development team can ensure consistent deployment processes. This minimizes the risk of deployment failures and enhances operational efficiency.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="disaster-recovery">Disaster Recovery&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Incorporating SBOMs into an OBOM aids in disaster recovery by providing detailed information about the operational setup. This ensures that in case of a system failure, the exact configurations and dependencies can be quickly restored.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="improved-collaboration">Improved Collaboration&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>An OBOM that includes SBOMs fosters better collaboration between development and operations teams, ensuring that deployment and maintenance processes are well-aligned.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="end-to-end-example-smart-thermometer-obom">End-to-End Example: Smart Thermometer OBOM&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To illustrate a valid end-to-end example that complies with the CycloneDX standard, here is a simplified version of an OBOM for a smart thermometer:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="example-json-structure">Example JSON Structure&lt;/h3>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-json" data-lang="json">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>{
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;bomFormat&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;CycloneDX&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;specVersion&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;1.3&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">1&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;components&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;type&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;application&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;Smart Thermometer Backend&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;2.0.0&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;bom-ref&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;backend-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;components&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;type&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;library&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;Flask&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;1.1.2&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;bom-ref&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;flask-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;licenses&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;license&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;id&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;BSD-3-Clause&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;type&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;library&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;Requests&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;2.23.0&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;bom-ref&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;requests-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;licenses&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;license&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;id&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;Apache-2.0&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;type&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;container&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;Smart Thermometer Container&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;1.0.0&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;bom-ref&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;container-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;components&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;type&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;operating-system&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;Ubuntu&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;20.04&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;bom-ref&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;ubuntu-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;type&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;library&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;Docker&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;19.03&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;bom-ref&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;docker-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;type&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;firmware&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;Smart Thermometer Device Firmware&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;3.2.1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;bom-ref&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;firmware-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;components&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;type&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;library&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;Rust Standard Library&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;1.49.0&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;bom-ref&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;rust-stdlib-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;type&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;library&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;Embedded HAL&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;0.2.4&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;bom-ref&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;embedded-hal-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ],
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;dependencies&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;ref&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;backend-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;dependsOn&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;flask-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;requests-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;ref&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;container-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;dependsOn&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;ubuntu-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;docker-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;ref&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;firmware-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;dependsOn&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;rust-stdlib-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;embedded-hal-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ],
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;metadata&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;timestamp&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;2023-07-09T14:28:00Z&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;tools&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;vendor&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;CycloneDX&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;CycloneDX Maven Plugin&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;1.4.0&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ],
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;component&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;type&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;application&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;Smart Thermometer&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;3.0.0&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;bom-ref&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;smart-thermometer-1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>}
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;h3 id="explanation">Explanation&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Components&lt;/strong>: This section lists all components of the smart thermometer, including backend libraries, Docker container elements, and device firmware libraries.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dependencies&lt;/strong>: Specifies the relationships between components, indicating which components depend on others.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Metadata&lt;/strong>: Contains additional information about the BOM, such as the timestamp, tools used to generate the BOM, and details about the top-level component (the smart thermometer).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>While the inclusion of Software Bills of Materials (SBOMs) is mandated by executive orders for ensuring software security and transparency, integrating SBOMs into an Operations Bill of Materials (OBOM) provides additional operational benefits. For the development of a smart thermometer, this integration enhances security, compliance, and operational efficiency. By adopting SBOMs as a foundational element and viewing OBOM as a value-added extension, organizations can build a more secure, transparent, and resilient software ecosystem.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>References:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Executive Order on Improving the Nation&amp;rsquo;s Cybersecurity. (2021). The White House. Retrieved from &lt;a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/statements-releases/2021/05/12/executive-order-on-improving-the-nations-cybersecurity/">White House&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>CycloneDX. (n.d.). &lt;em>CycloneDX Specification&lt;/em>. Retrieved from &lt;a href="https://cyclonedx.org/specification/overview/">CycloneDX&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST). (2021). &lt;em>Security and Privacy Controls for Information Systems and Organizations&lt;/em>. Retrieved from &lt;a href="https://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/SpecialPublications/NIST.SP.800-53r5.pdf">NIST&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>By focusing on the critical role of SBOMs within OBOMs, organizations can ensure compliance with executive mandates while leveraging the additional benefits of a comprehensive operational framework.&lt;/p></description><category>education</category></item><item><title>Call for Views on the Code of Practice for Software Vendors: Ensuring Security and Resilience</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2024/05/26/call-for-views-on-the-code-of-practice-for-software-vendors-ensuring-security-and-resilience/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 06:33:13 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2024/05/26/call-for-views-on-the-code-of-practice-for-software-vendors-ensuring-security-and-resilience/</guid><description>&lt;p>The UK government has launched a call for views on a new voluntary Code of Practice for Software Vendors. This initiative aims to enhance the security and resilience of software sold to businesses and organizations. The Code, co-designed with industry and academic experts, outlines fundamental principles for secure design, development, deployment, and customer communication. It seeks feedback on its suitability and the supporting materials provided. This effort is part of broader measures to strengthen cybersecurity across the UK’s digital supply chains and improve organizational resilience.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For more details, visit the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/calls-for-evidence/call-for-views-on-the-code-of-practice-for-software-vendors/call-for-views-on-the-code-of-practice-for-software-vendors">official call for views&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description><category>news</category></item><item><title>Navigating the Landscape of Open Source Licenses</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2024/04/03/navigating-the-landscape-of-open-source-licenses/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 17:27:35 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2024/04/03/navigating-the-landscape-of-open-source-licenses/</guid><description>&lt;p>Open-source software forms the backbone of countless applications, from the smallest utilities to the infrastructure running the largest data centers. The licenses under which this software is released can significantly affect how it&amp;rsquo;s used, integrated, and distributed. This blog post aims to demystify open-source licenses, highlighting their key characteristics, especially in terms of legal compliance and commercial compatibility.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="1-mit-license">1. &lt;strong>MIT License&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> One of the most permissive and straightforward open-source licenses. It allows almost unrestricted freedom to use, modify, and distribute the licensed software, provided that the original license and copyright notice are included with any substantial portions of the software.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> Highly compatible. Its permissiveness makes it favorable for commercial use, without imposing significant legal constraints on distribution.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="2-apache-license-20">2. &lt;strong>Apache License 2.0&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> Similar to the MIT License in its permissiveness, the Apache License also provides an express grant of patent rights from contributors to users. It allows for commercial use, modification, and distribution of the licensed software.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> Generally considered commercially friendly. It requires explicit attribution and provides an explicit grant of patent rights, reducing legal risks for commercial applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="3-gnu-general-public-license-gpl-versions-2--3">3. &lt;strong>GNU General Public License (GPL) Versions 2 &amp;amp; 3&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> The GPL licenses are copyleft licenses, which means that any derivative work must be distributed under the same license terms. Version 3 (GPLv3) introduced terms intended to protect against patent aggression and to prevent tivoization (the practice of designing hardware to prevent modifications to the software it runs).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> GPLv3 is often considered commercially &amp;ldquo;toxic&amp;rdquo; because it requires that derivative works be open-sourced under the same license, potentially exposing proprietary code. GPLv2 is seen as slightly more lenient, though still challenging for commercial proprietary use.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="4-gnu-lesser-general-public-license-lgpl">4. &lt;strong>GNU Lesser General Public License (LGPL)&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> A compromise between the strong copyleft of the GPL and permissive licenses like MIT and Apache. It allows linking to open-source libraries (under LGPL) in proprietary software without the requirement to release the proprietary software&amp;rsquo;s source code.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> More commercially friendly than GPL, especially for use in proprietary software that uses open-source libraries without modifying them.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="5-bsd-licenses-2-clause-and-3-clause">5. &lt;strong>BSD Licenses (2-clause and 3-clause)&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> The BSD licenses are permissive, similar to the MIT License. The 2-clause license is very straightforward, allowing for almost unrestricted use, while the 3-clause license adds a non-endorsement clause, preventing the use of the licensor&amp;rsquo;s name to promote derived products without permission.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> Both are considered commercially friendly due to their permissiveness and minimal requirements.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="6-mozilla-public-license-20-mpl-20">6. &lt;strong>Mozilla Public License 2.0 (MPL 2.0)&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> A middle-ground license that allows the code to be combined with proprietary software. It requires that modifications to the licensed code be open-sourced, but allows for the combination of the MPL-licensed code with proprietary code into a larger work without open-sourcing the proprietary components.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> MPL 2.0 is seen as commercially friendly, especially for projects that want to ensure improvements to open-source code are shared while allowing for commercial application development.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="7-eclipse-public-license-epl">7. &lt;strong>Eclipse Public License (EPL)&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> Similar to the MPL, the EPL is a moderate copyleft license that requires that modifications to EPL-licensed code be made available under the EPL, but allows for proprietary applications to link to EPL-licensed libraries without open-sourcing the proprietary code.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> The EPL is generally considered to be commercially friendly, especially for developers looking to use open-source libraries within proprietary applications without distributing the entire source code.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="8-creative-commons-licenses">8. &lt;strong>Creative Commons Licenses&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> Creative Commons licenses are not typically used for software but for creative works such as videos, photographs, and documentation. CC licenses come in various forms, from the most permissive (CC0, which is essentially public domain) to more restrictive forms (such as CC BY-NC-ND, which allows sharing but not commercial use or derivative works without permission).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> The commercial friendliness of CC licenses varies. CC0 is highly compatible with commercial use, imposing no restrictions. Other, more restrictive licenses (like CC BY-NC-ND) limit commercial use and derivative works, making them less suitable for commercial projects that require modification or commercial distribution of the content.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="9-gnu-affero-general-public-license-agplv3">9. &lt;strong>GNU Affero General Public License (AGPLv3)&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> Similar to GPLv3, but with an additional requirement that if you run a modified program on a server and let other users communicate with it there, you must also release the modified source code to those users. This license aims to close the &amp;ldquo;application service provider&amp;rdquo; loophole in the GPLv3.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> Like GPLv3, AGPLv3 is considered challenging for commercial use, especially for software offered as a service, due to its requirement to share source code modifications.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="10-european-union-public-license-eupl">10. &lt;strong>European Union Public License (EUPL)&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> The EUPL is a strong copyleft license approved by the European Commission. It is compatible with several other licenses, including the GPL, allowing for the integration of EUPL-licensed code with code under those licenses.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> The EUPL&amp;rsquo;s copyleft nature makes it less commercially friendly for proprietary software, similar to the GPL. However, its compatibility with other licenses offers some flexibility for open-source projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="11-zliblibpng-license">11. &lt;strong>Zlib/libpng License&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> This is a very permissive license for software libraries that allows for modification, distribution, and use in proprietary applications, provided that credit is given to the author.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> Highly compatible with commercial projects due to its minimal restrictions, making it favorable for use in both open-source and proprietary software.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="12-artistic-license-20">12. &lt;strong>Artistic License 2.0&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> Originally designed for the Perl programming language, this license encourages artistic freedom by allowing modified versions of the software to be distributed under a different license or as closed source, provided that certain conditions are met.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> This license is generally considered commercially friendly, offering flexibility for developers to use and contribute to open-source projects while retaining the option to distribute proprietary versions.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="13-redis-license">13. &lt;strong>Redis License&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> Redis uses a combination of open-source and proprietary licensing for different components of its software. The core of Redis is licensed under the BSD license, making it highly permissive and commercially friendly. However, certain Redis modules are licensed under the Redis Source Available License (RSAL), which restricts the use of the software in a database, caching, or a database-like functionality in a commercial product without purchasing a commercial license.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> The core BSD-licensed part of Redis is commercially friendly. The RSAL for certain modules introduces restrictions intended to protect the commercial interests of Redis Labs, the company behind Redis, making those modules less suitable for commercial products seeking to use advanced features of Redis without engaging in a commercial relationship with Redis Labs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="14-mysql-license">14. &lt;strong>MySQL License&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description:&lt;/strong> MySQL, one of the world&amp;rsquo;s most popular open-source relational database management systems, is dual-licensed. For open-source projects, it can be used under the GNU General Public License (GPL), which allows for free use, modification, and distribution under the same GPL license. For organizations wishing to incorporate MySQL into proprietary products, commercial licenses are available from Oracle Corporation, which acquired MySQL as part of its purchase of Sun Microsystems.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commercial Compatibility:&lt;/strong> The GPL license for MySQL is suitable for open-source projects but can be restrictive for proprietary commercial use due to its copyleft requirements. The commercial licensing option provides the necessary legal framework for proprietary use but at the cost of licensing fees, making it a significant consideration for companies planning to use MySQL in their products or services.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The landscape of open-source and creative licenses is broad and varied, catering to different needs, goals, and legal requirements. Creative Commons licenses expand the scope of open-source principles to creative works, offering a range of options from completely unrestricted use to more controlled scenarios. Understanding the specific terms and implications of each license type is crucial for ensuring legal compliance and aligning with project or organizational goals, whether the focus is on software, documentation, or other creative content. Careful consideration and, when necessary, legal consultation can help navigate this complex landscape effectively.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>This is not legal advice. Please consult a legal professional before making commercial decisions around licensing.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description><category>education</category></item></channel></rss>