<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sbomify</title><link>https://sbomify.com/tags/secure-by-design/</link><description>Your Security Artifact Hub. From zero to SBOM hero. Generate, manage, and share SBOMs and compliance documents. Built for CRA compliance and seamless integration with your existing tools.</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 15:56:35 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sbomify.com/tags/secure-by-design/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Embracing Cybersecurity with CISA&amp;#39;s &amp;#39;Secure by Design&amp;#39; Initiative</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2024/07/24/embracing-cybersecurity-with-cisas-secure-by-design-initiative/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 15:56:35 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2024/07/24/embracing-cybersecurity-with-cisas-secure-by-design-initiative/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the ever-evolving landscape of cyber threats, the importance of integrating robust security measures into the earliest stages of software development cannot be overstated. Recognizing this need, the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency (CISA), alongside various international partners, has released an updated guide titled &amp;ldquo;Shifting the Balance of Cybersecurity Risk: Principles and Approaches for Secure by Design Software&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/resources-tools/resources/secure-by-design">CISA&lt;/a>). This comprehensive document emphasizes the urgency for software manufacturers to prioritize security from the outset, fundamentally shifting the cybersecurity burden away from consumers and towards developers.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="key-principles-of-secure-by-design">Key Principles of Secure by Design&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The guide outlines three core principles that software manufacturers are encouraged to adopt:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Take Ownership of Customer Security Outcomes&lt;/strong>: Manufacturers are urged to take full responsibility for the security of their products, ensuring that security features are enabled by default and that customers are protected without needing to take additional steps (&lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/news-events/news/cisa-us-and-international-partners-announce-updated-secure-design-principles-joint-guide">CISA&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Embrace Radical Transparency and Accountability&lt;/strong>: This principle advocates for openness about vulnerabilities and security practices. By ensuring complete and accurate vulnerability advisories, manufacturers can build trust and enhance their products&amp;rsquo; security (&lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/news-events/news/us-and-international-partners-publish-secure-design-and-default-principles-and-approaches">CISA&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Lead from the Top&lt;/strong>: Executive leadership must prioritize security as a critical element of product development. This cultural shift within organizations is crucial for embedding security into every stage of the software lifecycle (&lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/news-events/news/next-chapter-secure-design">CISA&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h4 id="international-collaboration">International Collaboration&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The updated guidance has garnered support from cybersecurity authorities worldwide, including agencies from Australia, Canada, Germany, the UK, and several other nations. This international coalition underscores the global consensus on the necessity of secure by design principles (&lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/news-events/news/us-and-international-partners-publish-secure-design-and-default-principles-and-approaches">CISA&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CISA Director Jen Easterly highlighted the collaborative effort, stating, &amp;ldquo;Ensuring that software manufacturers integrate security into the earliest phases of design for their products is critical to building a secure and resilient technology ecosystem&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/news-events/news/cisa-us-and-international-partners-announce-updated-secure-design-principles-joint-guide">CISA&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="practical-steps-for-implementation">Practical Steps for Implementation&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>To assist manufacturers in adopting these principles, the guide provides practical steps and examples of artifacts that can demonstrate a commitment to secure by design. These artifacts, ranging from secure coding practices to comprehensive vulnerability management processes, serve as evidence of a manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s dedication to security (&lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/news-events/news/next-chapter-secure-design">CISA&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Moreover, the guide encourages manufacturers to engage in continuous learning and adaptation. This includes participating in secure by design summits, collaborating with educational institutions, and adhering to secure coding practices advocated by the broader cybersecurity community (&lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/news-events/news/next-chapter-secure-design">CISA&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="the-road-ahead">The Road Ahead&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>CISA&amp;rsquo;s updated guidance is more than a set of recommendations; it is a call to action for the entire software industry. By adopting secure by design principles, manufacturers can significantly reduce the prevalence of vulnerabilities and enhance the overall security of technology products used globally.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As the digital landscape continues to expand, the need for secure software becomes ever more critical. CISA&amp;rsquo;s initiative represents a significant step towards a more secure digital future, where security is an integral part of the development process, rather than an afterthought (&lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/resources-tools/resources/secure-by-design">CISA&lt;/a>) (&lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/sites/default/files/2023-06/principles_approaches_for_security-by-design-default_508c.pdf#:~:text=URL%3A%20https%3A%2F%2Fwww.cisa.gov%2Fsites%2Fdefault%2Ffiles%2F2023">CISA&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For more detailed information and to access the full guide, visit the &lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/resources-tools/resources/secure-by-design">CISA Secure by Design page&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description><category>compliance</category></item></channel></rss>