<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sbomify</title><link>https://sbomify.com/tags/team/</link><description>Your Security Artifact Hub. From zero to SBOM hero. Generate, manage, and share SBOMs and compliance documents. Built for CRA compliance and seamless integration with your existing tools.</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 09:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sbomify.com/tags/team/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Chris Swan Joins sbomify Advisory Board</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2025/02/21/chris-swan-joins-sbomify/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2025/02/21/chris-swan-joins-sbomify/</guid><description>&lt;p>sbomify is excited to announce that Chris Swan has joined its advisory board. Chris brings extensive experience in DevOps, open source, and cybersecurity, making him an invaluable asset as sbomify continues simplifying and securing software supply chains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://sbomify.com/assets/images/chris_swan.webp" alt="Chris Swan">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Chris currently serves as an Engineer at &lt;a href="https://atsign.com/">Atsign&lt;/a>, working on the atPlatform, a privacy-focused open-source networking platform. He previously held leadership roles at DXC Technology, UBS, Cohesive Networks, and Credit Suisse, focusing on cloud, security, and infrastructure innovation. Chris is also known for his insightful writing as an &lt;a href="https://www.infoq.com/profile/Chris-Swan/#allActivity">editor at InfoQ&lt;/a> and as co-host of the &lt;a href="https://techdebtburndown.com/">&lt;em>Tech Debt Burndown&lt;/em>&lt;/a> podcast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Chris&amp;rsquo;s involvement with sbomify began during his work at Atsign, where he successfully integrated sbomify into their CI/CD pipeline to automate SBOM generation. This collaboration, detailed in the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/case-studies/atsign">Atsign case study&lt;/a>, demonstrates Chris&amp;rsquo;s practical approach to integrating security seamlessly into developer workflows.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Chris&amp;rsquo;s perspective aligns perfectly with sbomify’s mission of developer-friendly, frictionless SBOM management.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve been interested in SBOMs since Josh Corman first introduced me to them back in 2015. With the US Executive Order 14028 in place, and EU Cyber Resilience Act (CRA) on the way it&amp;rsquo;s becoming a super hot topic, and there&amp;rsquo;s lots of work to be done to make implementation easy and effective. Viktor has an incredible vision for sbomify, and I&amp;rsquo;m delighted to be able to help make it happen.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em> -Chris Swan&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To experience effortless SBOM management, &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com">try sbomify today&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item></channel></rss>