<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sbomify</title><link>https://sbomify.com/tags/fda/</link><description>Your Security Artifact Hub. From zero to SBOM hero. Generate, manage, and share SBOMs and compliance documents. Built for CRA compliance and seamless integration with your existing tools.</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sbomify.com/tags/fda/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>FDA Medical Device SBOM Requirements: What the New Cybersecurity Guidance Means for Manufacturers</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/09/fda-medical-device-sbom-requirements/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/09/fda-medical-device-sbom-requirements/</guid><description>&lt;p>On June 27, 2025, the FDA issued updated guidance on &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Cybersecurity in Medical Devices: Quality System Considerations and Content of Premarket Submissions.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong> This document marks a significant step forward in how medical device manufacturers must approach software security and transparency. At the heart of these recommendations lies the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/what-is-sbom/">Software Bill of Materials (SBOM)&lt;/a> — now an essential element of premarket submissions for connected medical devices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re a manufacturer preparing a 510(k), PMA, or other premarket submission, here&amp;rsquo;s what you need to know about the FDA&amp;rsquo;s SBOM expectations and how to prepare.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-the-guidance-says-about-sboms">What the Guidance Says About SBOMs&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The FDA guidance recommends the inclusion of an SBOM under &lt;strong>Section V.A.4 (Software Bill of Materials)&lt;/strong> as part of cybersecurity documentation in premarket submissions. Additionally, &lt;strong>Appendix 4&lt;/strong> lists SBOM sections as recommended documentation when cybersecurity risk is relevant.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While the guidance language is technically &lt;strong>non-binding&lt;/strong> (&amp;ldquo;contains nonbinding recommendations&amp;rdquo;), the practical reality is different:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Under &lt;strong>Section 524B of the FD&amp;amp;C Act&lt;/strong>, the FDA has authority over &amp;ldquo;cyber devices&amp;rdquo; — devices with software that can be vulnerable and are connected&lt;/li>
&lt;li>FDA may &lt;strong>refuse to accept premarket submissions&lt;/strong> that do not provide adequate SBOM and related cybersecurity information&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Insufficient SBOM documentation can lead to &lt;strong>delays in review&lt;/strong> or requests for resubmission&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In practice, the SBOM has moved from &amp;ldquo;nice-to-have&amp;rdquo; to &lt;strong>essential cybersecurity documentation&lt;/strong> for medical device submissions. This mirrors the broader global trend toward &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/why-now/">mandatory SBOM requirements&lt;/a> across regulatory frameworks.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sbom-content-expectations">SBOM Content Expectations&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The FDA guidance does not define SBOM fields directly. Instead, it explicitly references the &lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://www.ntia.gov/sites/default/files/publications/sbom_minimum_elements_report_0.pdf">NTIA Minimum Elements for a Software Bill of Materials&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> as the baseline expectation for SBOM content in premarket submissions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This distinction matters: the FDA is effectively saying &amp;ldquo;provide an SBOM that meets the NTIA minimum elements&amp;rdquo; — not &amp;ldquo;provide an SBOM with these FDA-defined fields.&amp;rdquo; This approach mirrors how other regulators (including the EU&amp;rsquo;s Cyber Resilience Act) reference SBOMs indirectly via standards bodies, allowing requirements to evolve without requiring agencies to reissue guidance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="ntia-minimum-elements">NTIA Minimum Elements&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The NTIA baseline defines what every SBOM should contain. For each software component:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Supplier name&lt;/strong> — who supplied the component&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Component name&lt;/strong> — the name of the component&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Version&lt;/strong> — the version identifier&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Unique identifier&lt;/strong> — such as Package URL (purl) or CPE&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dependency relationship&lt;/strong> — how components relate to each other&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Author of SBOM data&lt;/strong> — who created the SBOM&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Timestamp&lt;/strong> — when the SBOM was created&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="machine-readable-formats">Machine-Readable Formats&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SBOMs should be provided in machine-readable formats that support the NTIA minimum elements:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>SPDX&lt;/strong> (Software Package Data Exchange)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CycloneDX&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Both formats are widely accepted and can represent the required NTIA data fields.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="complete-software-inventory">Complete Software Inventory&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>All software included in the device must be identified:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Commercial software&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Open-source components&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Third-party libraries&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Off-the-shelf (OTS) components&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="support-and-lifecycle-metadata">Support and Lifecycle Metadata&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Beyond the NTIA baseline, FDA expects additional context for medical device submissions:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Level of support&lt;/strong> from the component supplier (active, legacy, or unsupported)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>End-of-support and end-of-life dates&lt;/strong> for each component&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="vulnerability-context">Vulnerability Context&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SBOMs should be supplemented with:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A &lt;strong>known vulnerabilities assessment&lt;/strong> for identified components&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Controls or mitigation descriptions&lt;/strong> explaining whether vulnerabilities are mitigated by design&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This means SBOMs are expected to be part of a comprehensive &lt;strong>vulnerability and risk management package&lt;/strong>, not just a flat inventory list.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="lifecycle-and-traceability-requirements">Lifecycle and Traceability Requirements&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The FDA guidance ties SBOMs into broader cybersecurity documentation expectations throughout the device lifecycle. Understanding the full &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/generate-collaborate-analyze/">SBOM lifecycle&lt;/a> — from generation through distribution and analysis — is critical for FDA compliance:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="secure-product-development-and-traceability">Secure Product Development and Traceability&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>SBOMs must be &lt;strong>traceable to security architecture views&lt;/strong> and threat models that FDA reviewers evaluate&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The documentation should demonstrate how software components affect device security risks&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="ongoing-updates">Ongoing Updates&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>SBOMs should be &lt;strong>updated to reflect changes&lt;/strong> throughout software updates and the device lifecycle&lt;/li>
&lt;li>This is not a one-time snapshot — it&amp;rsquo;s a living document&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Proper &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/how-to-version-sboms">SBOM versioning practices&lt;/a> are essential for maintaining traceability&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="integration-with-other-documentation">Integration with Other Documentation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In premarket submissions, SBOMs typically appear alongside:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Security Risk Management Reports&lt;/strong> — showing how components affect device risks&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Vulnerability Assessments&lt;/strong> — outcomes derived from SBOM analysis&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Software Support Information&lt;/strong> — lifecycle and maintenance details&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Labeling and Transparency Materials&lt;/strong> — cybersecurity information for end users&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="why-cicd-integration-is-essential">Why CI/CD Integration Is Essential&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Given the FDA&amp;rsquo;s emphasis on traceability and ongoing updates, &lt;strong>manual SBOM generation is not sustainable&lt;/strong> for medical device compliance. Every software build should automatically generate an SBOM that:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Captures the exact components at the moment of build&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Is cryptographically linked to that specific release&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Can be traced back to source code and build artifacts&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Is automatically stored and versioned for audit trails&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Integrating SBOM generation into your CI/CD pipeline ensures that every release — whether it&amp;rsquo;s a major version update or a security patch — has accurate, reproducible documentation. This is particularly important for medical devices where you may need to answer FDA questions about software composition years after the initial submission.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="distribution-and-transparency">Distribution and Transparency&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The FDA expects manufacturers to share cybersecurity information with stakeholders, including healthcare providers and end users. This means having a reliable system for distributing SBOMs to:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>FDA reviewers during premarket submissions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Auditors during compliance assessments&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Healthcare organizations evaluating your devices&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Security researchers conducting vulnerability assessments&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Email and shared drives don&amp;rsquo;t scale for this — you need a dedicated &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/trust-center/">SBOM hub and Trust Center&lt;/a> that provides controlled access to current and historical SBOMs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="practical-implications-for-manufacturers">Practical Implications for Manufacturers&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re preparing a premarket submission (510(k), PMA, De Novo), here&amp;rsquo;s what the FDA expects in practice:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sbom-compliance-checklist">SBOM Compliance Checklist&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>NTIA Minimum Elements&lt;/strong> — Ensure your SBOM includes all required fields (supplier, component name, version, unique identifier, dependencies, author, timestamp)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Machine-readable format&lt;/strong> — Use SPDX or CycloneDX&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Inventory completeness&lt;/strong> — Cover all software elements in your device&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Support and lifecycle metadata&lt;/strong> — Document support status and EOL dates for each component&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Known vulnerability assessment&lt;/strong> — Tie vulnerabilities back to risk controls&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Traceability and architecture linkage&lt;/strong> — Connect SBOMs to documentation and risk models&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Ongoing maintenance strategy&lt;/strong> — Plan for SBOM updates through the device&amp;rsquo;s life&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="consequences-of-non-compliance">Consequences of Non-Compliance&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Noncompliance or insufficient SBOM information can result in:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Refuse-to-accept decisions&lt;/strong> at the submission stage&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Delays in review&lt;/strong> requiring resubmission with complete SBOM and analysis&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The message is clear: get your SBOM documentation right the first time.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-sbomify-helps-with-fda-compliance">How sbomify Helps with FDA Compliance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Medical devices often have long lifecycles — sometimes 10-15 years or more. Managing SBOMs across that timespan, through multiple software updates and component changes, requires purpose-built tooling that automates the entire &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/generate-collaborate-analyze/">SBOM lifecycle&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="">sbomify&lt;/a> provides the infrastructure medical device manufacturers need:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="automated-cicd-integration">Automated CI/CD Integration&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This is the foundation of FDA-compliant SBOM management. sbomify integrates directly into your build pipeline:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/generate-collaborate-analyze/">Generate SBOMs automatically&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> during every build — no manual steps&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Augment and enrich&lt;/strong> SBOMs with supplier information, licensing, and metadata required by NTIA minimum elements&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Cryptographic signing and attestation&lt;/strong> for verifiable integrity&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Upload to sbomify with our &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action">GitHub Action&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2024/11/12/gitlab-support/">GitLab modules&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Every release automatically documented and stored for regulatory review&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>By automating generation in CI/CD, you ensure that SBOMs are always accurate, reproducible, and traceable to specific builds — exactly what the FDA expects.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="trust-center-for-regulatory-distribution">Trust Center for Regulatory Distribution&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Email and file shares don&amp;rsquo;t meet FDA expectations for professional cybersecurity documentation. sbomify&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/trust-center/">Trust Center&lt;/a> gives you:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A &lt;strong>branded portal&lt;/strong> for sharing SBOMs with FDA reviewers, auditors, and healthcare organizations&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Controlled access&lt;/strong> — determine who can see which products and versions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Always current&lt;/strong> — stakeholders access live data, not stale email attachments&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Audit trail&lt;/strong> — track who accessed what and when&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Professional presentation that demonstrates your commitment to transparency&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="sbom-lifecycle-management">SBOM Lifecycle Management&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Archive and track SBOMs across product versions and releases&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Maintain full version history for regulatory audits spanning years&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Support long-lived medical devices with complete historical records&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="centralized-sbom-hub">Centralized SBOM Hub&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Manage SBOMs for multiple device products in one platform&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Standardize generation and storage across engineering teams&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Aggregate component-level SBOMs into product-level views with our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/sbom-hierarchy/">SBOM hierarchy&lt;/a> feature — essential for complex medical devices with multiple software subsystems&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="continuous-vulnerability-monitoring">Continuous Vulnerability Monitoring&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Integrate with &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/integrations/">Google OSV and Dependency Track&lt;/a> for ongoing vulnerability detection&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Monitor archived SBOMs for newly discovered CVEs&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Track vulnerability status even for devices shipped years ago — critical for the FDA&amp;rsquo;s post-market cybersecurity expectations&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The FDA&amp;rsquo;s June 2025 cybersecurity guidance makes it clear: SBOMs are no longer optional for medical device manufacturers. They&amp;rsquo;re a critical component of premarket submissions and ongoing compliance. The guidance sets clear expectations for SBOM content, format, and lifecycle management — and the FDA is prepared to refuse submissions that don&amp;rsquo;t meet these standards.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Getting ahead of these requirements isn&amp;rsquo;t just about regulatory compliance — it&amp;rsquo;s about building more secure devices and maintaining trust with healthcare providers and patients.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://app.sbomify.com">Get started with sbomify&lt;/a> and build FDA-ready SBOM documentation into your medical device development process.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="resources">Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="official-documentation">Official Documentation&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.fda.gov/media/119933/download">FDA Guidance: Cybersecurity in Medical Devices (PDF)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.ntia.gov/sites/default/files/publications/sbom_minimum_elements_report_0.pdf">NTIA Minimum Elements for a Software Bill of Materials (PDF)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-sboms">Learn More About SBOMs&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/what-is-sbom/">What is an SBOM?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/generate-collaborate-analyze/">The SBOM Lifecycle: Generation, Distribution, and Analysis&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/guides/how-to-version-sboms">How to Version SBOMs&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/why-now/">The Growing Importance of SBOMs in Cybersecurity Compliance&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="related-compliance-frameworks">Related Compliance Frameworks&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2024/07/10/understanding-the-eu-cyber-resilience-act-the-role-of-sboms-in-enhancing-cybersecurity/">Understanding the EU Cyber Resilience Act&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2025/01/07/how-sboms-can-help-you-achieve-pci-dss-4-compliance/">How SBOMs Help with PCI DSS 4.0 Compliance&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2026/01/06/cra-explained-cyber-resilience-act-for-device-manufacturers/">CRA Explained: What the Cyber Resilience Act Means for Device Manufacturers&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="sbomify-features">sbomify Features&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/sbom-hierarchy/">SBOM Hierarchy&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/integrations/">Integrations&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/trust-center/">Trust Center&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description><category>compliance</category></item></channel></rss>