<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sbomify</title><link>https://sbomify.com/tags/cpp/</link><description>Your Security Artifact Hub. From zero to SBOM hero. Generate, manage, and share SBOMs and compliance documents. Built for CRA compliance and seamless integration with your existing tools.</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sbomify.com/tags/cpp/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Using Conan for C SBOMs</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2025/09/04/conan/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2025/09/04/conan/</guid><description>&lt;p>Last November I wrote about
&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2024/11/18/c-conundrum/">The C conundrum&lt;/a> as there&amp;rsquo;s so
much C code that needs SBOMs, but there was no straightforward way to
generate them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://conan.io/">Conan&lt;/a> got a mention, but at the time wasn&amp;rsquo;t working as
hoped.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thankfully things have improved since then, which means that Conan provides
a viable route to generating SBOMs for C (and C++) projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The most crucial change is that SBOM generation tools like Aqua&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href="https://trivy.dev/">Trivy&lt;/a> can now generate reasonable output from Conan lock
files. That in turn means that sbomify can use a &lt;code>conan.lock&lt;/code> file in the same
way it would use a lock file for any other package manager.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Conan &lt;a href="https://docs.conan.io/2/">documentation&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://academy.jfrog.com/conan-2-essentials">tutorial&lt;/a> have improved
dramatically, which makes it much easier to get started.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s relatively straightforward to &amp;lsquo;bolt on&amp;rsquo; a &lt;code>conanfile.py&lt;/code> to a project and
use it to describe dependencies. A &lt;code>conan.lock&lt;/code> can then be generated and
used as the basis of an SBOM. The only problem is that any changes to the
project dependencies need to be (manually) updated in the Conan file.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A more integrated approach means going all in on Conan, and using it to
generate configuration and build descriptions like &lt;code>CMakeLists.txt&lt;/code>.
Conan is very capable and flexible, and an easy win for a green field project.
But the 6.5 billion lines of open source C out there are testament to a huge
brown field problem. There&amp;rsquo;s been huge investment in the existing config and
build systems for those projects, encapsulated in CMake, GNU Autotools, and
many other systems. Refactoring those projects into Conan will require deep
understanding of the existing tool chain, and how Conan generates builds.
We might wish for an AI magic wand to make the transition easy, but it seems
to be a task that&amp;rsquo;s beyond the present generation of coding assistants.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As regulatory pressure from the EU Cyber Resilience Act
(&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyber_Resilience_Act">CRA&lt;/a>) and other mandates
mounts there&amp;rsquo;s going to be increasing interest in getting SBOMs for C stuff.
Conan can be used as a &amp;lsquo;bolt on&amp;rsquo; workaround, and with increased adoption
and familiarity may become the de facto way of doing things. At least for
everything that lies outside of other package ecosystems like Yocto and
Zephyr.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is a guest post from &lt;a href="https://cpswan.net">Chris Swan&lt;/a>, an advisor at
sbomify and an Engineer at &lt;a href="https://atsign.com">Atsign&lt;/a> who are an early
adopter of sbomify.&lt;/p></description><category>guide</category></item><item><title>The C conundrum - generating SBOMs when there&amp;#39;s no lockfile</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2024/11/18/c-conundrum/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2024/11/18/c-conundrum/</guid><description>&lt;p>Generating an SBOM for something created in a modern language like Dart, Go,
Python or Rust is pretty easy. Dependencies are declared using the language&amp;rsquo;s
package manager, the package manager creates a .lock file, and then an SBOM
can be generated from the .lock file. Under the hood sbomify uses
&lt;a href="https://trivy.dev/">Trivy&lt;/a> to do that, and other tools like
&lt;a href="https://github.com/anchore/syft">Syft&lt;/a> do the same.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s no package manager for C though, at least not a universally used one.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s a huge problem, because apps developed using modern languages where
it&amp;rsquo;s easy to create SBOMs are the very tip of an iceberg where stuff developed
in C is both the rest of the visible iceberg and everything beneath the
surface - the apps we know are written in C, and the numerous libraries etc.
that they&amp;rsquo;re built on top of.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How are people going to comply with Executive Order 14028 (in the US) and
the forthcoming Cyber Resilience Act (CRA) in the EU if they&amp;rsquo;re dealing with
that iceberg of C?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Where there are package managers we can reasonably expect their maintainers
to start churning out SBOMs. &lt;a href="https://www.yoctoproject.org/">The Yocto Project&lt;/a>,
which builds embedded Linux distributions, has taken an early lead with their
machinery for
&lt;a href="https://docs.yoctoproject.org/dev/dev-manual/sbom.html">Creating a Software Bill of Materials&lt;/a>.
It&amp;rsquo;s also reasonable to expect that major distributions like Debian and Red Hat
will follow suit. They do after all have all the metadata that&amp;rsquo;s needed, and
they&amp;rsquo;ve already spent years on careful curation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But what about all the apps that aren&amp;rsquo;t in major distro package managers?
There are a few pieces to the puzzle out there, but not yet a complete
solution.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/DEMCON/cmake-sbom">cmake-sbom&lt;/a> can add the SBOM creation
process to CMake (a popular tool for building C projects), but a lot of the
data entry (and subsequent maintenance) is manual. This perhaps provides the
boilerplate for NTIA compliance, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t really help with upstream
dependencies.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.zephyrproject.org/">Zephyr&lt;/a> has the ability to generate SPDX
for the embedded systems it creates, based on earlier work in
&lt;a href="https://github.com/swinslow/cmake-spdx">cmake-spdx&lt;/a>. But that hasn&amp;rsquo;t
yet been cycled back into a generic tool that could be used by other
CMake based projects.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://conan.io/">Conan&lt;/a> is a package manager for C/C++, with many popular
dependencies already present there. That opens the door to generating SBOMs
from &lt;code>conan.lock&lt;/code> files, but right now the resulting files (at least those
generated by Syft) are of very poor quality, with incomplete CFEs.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/intel/cve-bin-tool">cve-bin-tool&lt;/a> can generate an SBOM
from the libraries it finds in a binary, but:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Only a limited subset of libraries are discoverable to the tool.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When generating SBOMs from test binaries they were of poor quality.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>cve-bin-tool flags binaries and the libraries they contain as being
vulnerable even when they&amp;rsquo;ve been patched to fix the relevant CVE, implying
a naive matching mechanism.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/trailofbits/it-depends">it-depends&lt;/a> finds nothing
(and it seems it&amp;rsquo;s a
&lt;a href="https://github.com/trailofbits/it-depends/issues/66">known issue&lt;/a>
despite the README saying it supports CMake projects).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Thankfully efforts are underway to resolve these problems. C (and C++) is
lined up for
&lt;a href="https://github.com/CISA-SBOM-Community/SBOM-Generation?tab=readme-ov-file#phase-3">Phase 3&lt;/a>
of the SBOM Generation Reference Implementations within the CISA SBOM
Community; and the working group had a call in the past week to look at
what&amp;rsquo;s already working and where effort can most effectively be applied
to provide tools for a broader range of projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is a guest post from &lt;a href="https://cpswan.net">Chris Swan&lt;/a>, an Engineer at
&lt;a href="https://atsign.com">Atsign&lt;/a> who are an early adopter of sbomify.&lt;/p></description><category>guide</category></item></channel></rss>