<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sbomify</title><link>https://sbomify.com/tags/ntia/</link><description>Your Security Artifact Hub. From zero to SBOM hero. Generate, manage, and share SBOMs and compliance documents. Built for CRA compliance and seamless integration with your existing tools.</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 08:03:32 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sbomify.com/tags/ntia/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Framing Software Component Transparency: Establishing a Common Software Bill of Materials (SBOM)</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2024/06/11/framing-software-component-transparency-establishing-a-common-software-bill-of-materials-sbom/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 08:03:32 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2024/06/11/framing-software-component-transparency-establishing-a-common-software-bill-of-materials-sbom/</guid><description>&lt;p>As the digital world grows ever more complex, the tools we use to ensure software security and transparency must evolve. The 2nd edition of &lt;a href="https://www.ntia.gov/files/ntia/publications/ntia_sbom_framing_2nd_edition_20211021.pdf">Framing Software Component Transparency: Establishing a Common Software Bill of Materials (SBOM)&lt;/a> has been pivotal in laying down the standards necessary for identifying and managing software components. This edition emphasized transparency, interoperability, and security, enabling organizations to manage vulnerabilities more effectively and enhance trust across software supply chains.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="key-highlights-from-the-2nd-edition">Key Highlights from the 2nd Edition&lt;/h4>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Enhanced Transparency&lt;/strong>: Improved clarity and accessibility of software component information, critical for managing vulnerabilities and ensuring system integrity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Interoperability Standards&lt;/strong>: Establishing a common framework that facilitates better communication and compatibility across different systems and organizations.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Security and Risk Management&lt;/strong>: Providing detailed insights into software components, empowering organizations to manage risks proactively.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Community and Collaboration&lt;/strong>: Encouraging a collaborative environment among developers, suppliers, and users to maintain software reliability.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h4 id="looking-ahead-to-the-3rd-edition">Looking Ahead to the 3rd Edition&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The forthcoming 3rd edition of &lt;em>Framing Software Component Transparency: Establishing a Common Software Bill of Materials (SBOM)&lt;/em> is set to build on the robust foundation laid by its predecessor. Here’s what we can anticipate:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Advanced Security Measures&lt;/strong>: Introducing more robust protocols to counter sophisticated cyber threats.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Greater Automation&lt;/strong>: Incorporating advanced automation tools to streamline SBOM creation and management, reducing manual efforts and errors.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Expanded Scope&lt;/strong>: Covering a broader range of software types and use cases to reflect the dynamic nature of modern technology.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Global Standards Alignment&lt;/strong>: Ensuring SBOM practices align with international standards to promote global interoperability and security.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="notable-additions-in-the-3rd-edition-draft">Notable Additions in the 3rd Edition Draft&lt;/h4>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Updated Language and Clarifications&lt;/strong>: To enhance understanding and implementation of SBOM attributes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>New Baseline Attributes&lt;/strong>: Inclusion of license and copyright holder information.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Data Maturity Levels&lt;/strong>: Introducing minimum expected, recommended practice, and aspirational goal maturity levels for SBOM attributes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Handling Undeclared Data&lt;/strong>: Providing guidelines for managing unknown or redacted components and dependencies.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>As we eagerly await the release of the 3rd edition, it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to reflect on the progress made and prepare for the future advancements in software security and transparency that the new edition promises. The continuous evolution of the SBOM framework is a testament to the collaborative efforts of the software community, aiming to create a more secure and transparent digital ecosystem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Stay tuned for more updates and insights as the 3rd edition of the SBOM Framing becomes available, setting the stage for the next chapter in software security and management.&lt;/p></description><category>education</category></item></channel></rss>