<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sbomify</title><link>https://sbomify.com/tags/spdx/</link><description>Your Security Artifact Hub. From zero to SBOM hero. Generate, manage, and share SBOMs and compliance documents. Built for CRA compliance and seamless integration with your existing tools.</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sbomify.com/tags/spdx/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Announcing sbomify v0.25: The One with Attestations</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/23/announcing-sbomify-v0-25-the-one-with-attestations/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/23/announcing-sbomify-v0-25-the-one-with-attestations/</guid><description>&lt;p>Software supply chain security is not just about knowing what is in your software. It is about proving that knowledge is authentic and has not been tampered with. With v0.25, sbomify takes a significant step forward by introducing &lt;strong>attestation verification&lt;/strong>, allowing you to cryptographically verify the provenance of your SBOMs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="github-attestation-plugin">GitHub Attestation Plugin&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The headline feature of v0.25 is our new &lt;strong>GitHub Attestation Plugin&lt;/strong>. This plugin verifies SBOM attestations using &lt;a href="https://www.sigstore.dev/">Sigstore&lt;/a> and cosign, the same infrastructure that powers supply chain security across the open source ecosystem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When you generate an SBOM using GitHub Actions, you can sign it using GitHub&amp;rsquo;s built-in attestation capability. The sbomify GitHub Attestation Plugin then verifies these signatures automatically when you upload your SBOM. If the attestation is valid, you get cryptographic proof that the SBOM was generated by your CI/CD pipeline and has not been modified since.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The plugin includes automatic retry logic to handle transient network issues when communicating with the Sigstore transparency log. This ensures reliable verification even under less-than-ideal network conditions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is our first attestation plugin, building on the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/blob/master/docs/ADR/ADR-003.md">plugin architecture&lt;/a> we introduced in v0.24. We plan to add support for additional attestation formats including in-toto in future releases.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="spdx-23-export">SPDX 2.3 Export&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>sbomify has supported uploading SBOMs in both CycloneDX and SPDX formats for a while. With v0.25, we are adding the ability to &lt;strong>download aggregated SBOMs in SPDX 2.3 format&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can now download aggregated SBOMs for releases, projects, and products in either CycloneDX or SPDX format directly from the UI. This gives you flexibility when working with tools and partners that prefer one format over the other. Internally, we continue to use CycloneDX as our canonical format, but the SPDX export ensures you can meet requirements regardless of which standard your ecosystem uses.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="product-lifecycle-management">Product Lifecycle Management&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Knowing when your software reaches end-of-support or end-of-life is critical for compliance and vulnerability management. v0.25 introduces &lt;strong>Product Lifecycle&lt;/strong> fields aligned with the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/cle/">CLE (Common Lifecycle Enumeration)&lt;/a> standard that let you track:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Release Date&lt;/strong> - When the product version was released&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>End-of-Support Date&lt;/strong> - When active support ends&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>End-of-Life Date&lt;/strong> - When all support, including security updates, ends&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>You can set these dates manually in the UI for both &lt;strong>products&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>components&lt;/strong>. This is useful for tracking your own release schedules and support commitments.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For common Linux distributions and frameworks, lifecycle data can also be added automatically. The &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/blog/2026/01/20/announcing-sbomify-action-v0-11-the-one-where-they-go-to-pypi/#know-when-your-software-goes-end-of-life">Lifecycle Database&lt;/a> in sbomify-action embeds CLE data directly into your SBOMs during generation. This covers distributions like Ubuntu, Debian, Alpine, and Fedora, as well as language runtimes and frameworks including Python, Go, Django, Rails, and React.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These dates flow through to your Trust Center and can be displayed on public product pages. For organizations subject to regulations like the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eu-cra/">EU Cyber Resilience Act&lt;/a>, tracking lifecycle information is a requirement.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="contact-role-flags">Contact Role Flags&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Building on the contact profile improvements from v0.24, this release adds &lt;strong>role flags&lt;/strong> to contacts. You can now designate contacts as:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Author&lt;/strong> - The person or team who created the component&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Security Contact&lt;/strong> - Who to reach for security issues&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Technical Contact&lt;/strong> - Who to reach for technical questions&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>We have also consolidated the previously separate author field into the main contact profile. Instead of managing authors separately, you now simply mark a contact as an author using the role flag. This simplifies contact management while aligning with how CycloneDX represents contact information.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="compliance-badges">Compliance Badges&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Compliance status is now more visible than ever. v0.25 introduces &lt;strong>compliance badges&lt;/strong> that display assessment results directly on product listings and public Trust Center pages. Badges only appear for assessments you pass, so you are showcasing compliance achievements rather than advertising gaps.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We have also added a &lt;strong>Copy Badge&lt;/strong> button that generates markdown snippets you can paste into your README files. This makes it easy to showcase your compliance status directly in your repository.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="other-improvements">Other Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CRA Plugin v1.1.0&lt;/strong> - The EU Cyber Resilience Act plugin now prioritizes native SBOM fields over &lt;code>cra:&lt;/code> annotations, making it easier to pass assessments without custom annotations&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Custom Domains&lt;/strong> - Added DCV (Domain Control Validation) delegation CNAME instructions for easier SSL certificate provisioning&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Architecture&lt;/strong> - Reorganized the codebase with cleaner api/domain/services layer separation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Billing&lt;/strong> - Enhanced billing processing and webhook handling for Stripe events (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Django Admin&lt;/strong> - Comprehensive theme update to match the webapp design system (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Footer&lt;/strong> - Simplified by removing version badges and moving build info to HTML comments (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="bug-fixes">Bug Fixes&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Fixed API error messages leaking team and resource information (security improvement)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed 403 errors when tagging SBOMs via API tokens in CI/CD pipelines&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed infinite &amp;ldquo;checking&amp;rdquo; state in the plugin UI when no plugins are enabled&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed RecursionError in public component page templates&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed plugin enable to not queue all historical SBOMs, which was blocking the web server (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed social card images with proper 1200x630 dimensions and meta tags (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed missing component context in component item view (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed SPDX SBOMs not being tagged to releases (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed social banner URLs for public Trust Center pages (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To enable the GitHub Attestation Plugin, navigate to &lt;strong>Settings → Plugins&lt;/strong> and enable the GitHub Attestation assessment. From there, every SBOM upload with a valid attestation will be automatically verified.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For SPDX downloads, visit any release, project, or product page and use the format selector to download the aggregated SBOM in your preferred format.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out the full changelog for &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/compare/v0.24...v0.25">v0.25&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/compare/v0.25...v0.25.1">v0.25.1&lt;/a> on GitHub.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As always, I would love to hear your feedback. If you have questions about attestation verification or ideas for additional plugins, drop us a note or open an issue on GitHub.&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item><item><title>SBOM Formats Compared: CycloneDX vs SPDX</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/15/sbom-formats-cyclonedx-vs-spdx/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/15/sbom-formats-cyclonedx-vs-spdx/</guid><description>&lt;p>An SBOM format defines the structure, fields, and serialization of a &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/what-is-sbom/">Software Bill of Materials&lt;/a>. Two formats have emerged as industry standards: &lt;a href="https://cyclonedx.org/">CycloneDX&lt;/a>, developed by OWASP, and &lt;a href="https://spdx.dev/">SPDX&lt;/a> (Software Package Data Exchange), developed by the Linux Foundation. Both are actively maintained, widely supported by tooling, and accepted by major compliance frameworks. Understanding their differences helps organizations choose the right format for their use case — or, as is increasingly common, support both.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="a-brief-history">A Brief History&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="spdx">SPDX&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SPDX originated in 2010 as a Linux Foundation project focused on standardizing how open source license information is communicated. Its roots in license compliance shaped the format&amp;rsquo;s design: SPDX has always included rich fields for license expressions, copyright text, and file-level attribution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>SPDX 2.0 was released in 2015. The later SPDX 2.2.1 became an &lt;a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/81870.html">ISO/IEC standard (5962:2021)&lt;/a> in 2021. SPDX 2.3, the current widely-deployed version, added support for additional relationship types and improved package identification.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://spdx.github.io/spdx-spec/v3.0.1/">SPDX 3.0&lt;/a>, released in 2024, is a significant redesign. It introduces a profile-based architecture where the core specification defines common elements and optional profiles (Security, Licensing, Build, AI, Dataset) extend the model for specific use cases. This makes SPDX 3.0 more flexible but also more complex than previous versions.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="cyclonedx">CycloneDX&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>CycloneDX was created in 2017 by &lt;a href="https://owasp.org/">OWASP&lt;/a> with a different starting point: application security. The format was designed specifically to support software supply chain security use cases including vulnerability tracking, dependency analysis, and component integrity verification.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CycloneDX has evolved rapidly through regular releases. &lt;a href="https://cyclonedx.org/docs/1.6/">CycloneDX 1.6&lt;/a> (2024) added attestation and cryptography bill of materials support. &lt;a href="https://cyclonedx.org/docs/1.7/">CycloneDX 1.7&lt;/a> (2025) added patent and intellectual property metadata, citations for data provenance, enhanced cryptographic transparency capabilities, and expanded formulations scope.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CycloneDX is an &lt;a href="https://ecma-international.org/publications-and-standards/standards/ecma-424/">Ecma International standard (ECMA-424)&lt;/a> as of 2024.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="governance-and-community">Governance and Community&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Aspect&lt;/th>
&lt;th>CycloneDX&lt;/th>
&lt;th>SPDX&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Governing body&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://owasp.org/">OWASP Foundation&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://www.linuxfoundation.org/">Linux Foundation&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Standards body&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://ecma-international.org/">Ecma International&lt;/a> (ECMA-424)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://www.iso.org/">ISO/IEC&lt;/a> (5962:2021)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Primary focus&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Application security and supply chain risk&lt;/td>
&lt;td>License compliance and software transparency&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Release cadence&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Frequent (roughly annual major versions)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Less frequent (major versions every 2-3 years)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Current version&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.7 (2025)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3.0.1 (2024), with 2.3 still widely deployed&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Serialization&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>JSON, XML, Protocol Buffers&lt;/td>
&lt;td>JSON, XML, RDF, Tag-Value (SPDX 2.3); JSON-LD (SPDX 3.0)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Both formats are open standards with active communities, public specification repositories, and contributor-friendly governance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="key-structural-differences">Key Structural Differences&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="document-model">Document Model&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>CycloneDX&lt;/strong> uses a flat, component-centric model. An SBOM is a document containing metadata and a list of components. Dependencies are expressed separately through a &lt;code>dependencies&lt;/code> array that maps component references to their dependents. This separation keeps the component list clean and the dependency graph explicit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>SPDX 2.3&lt;/strong> uses a package-and-relationship model. Packages are listed individually, and &lt;code>relationships&lt;/code> entries describe how they relate (e.g., &lt;code>DEPENDS_ON&lt;/code>, &lt;code>CONTAINS&lt;/code>, &lt;code>BUILD_TOOL_OF&lt;/code>). SPDX supports a wider set of relationship types than CycloneDX.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>SPDX 3.0&lt;/strong> moves to an element-based model with a linked-data approach. Elements (packages, files, snippets, etc.) are connected through relationships and can reference external documents. This is more powerful for complex use cases but adds modeling complexity.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="component-identification">Component Identification&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Both formats support Package URL (&lt;a href="https://github.com/package-url/purl-spec">purl&lt;/a>) and &lt;a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/products/cpe">CPE&lt;/a> for component identification. Purl is the preferred identifier in both ecosystems as it is more precise for software packages.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Identifier&lt;/th>
&lt;th>CycloneDX&lt;/th>
&lt;th>SPDX 2.3&lt;/th>
&lt;th>SPDX 3.0&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>purl&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>components[].purl&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>packages[].externalRefs[]&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>External identifier&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>CPE&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>components[].cpe&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>packages[].externalRefs[]&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>External identifier&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Hash&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>components[].hashes[]&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>packages[].checksums[]&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Verification properties&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Supplier&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>components[].supplier.name&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>packages[].supplier&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Organization agent linked to element&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>For a complete field-by-field mapping, see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/schema-crosswalk/">SBOM Schema Crosswalk&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="license-data">License Data&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SPDX has historically been stronger for license documentation, reflecting its origins. SPDX defines the &lt;a href="https://spdx.org/licenses/">SPDX License List&lt;/a> — the standard set of license identifiers (e.g., &lt;code>MIT&lt;/code>, &lt;code>Apache-2.0&lt;/code>, &lt;code>GPL-3.0-only&lt;/code>) used across the industry, including by CycloneDX.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CycloneDX supports license data through &lt;code>components[].licenses[]&lt;/code>, which can reference SPDX license identifiers or include full license text. Both formats support SPDX license expressions (compound expressions like &lt;code>MIT OR Apache-2.0&lt;/code>).&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="vulnerability-data">Vulnerability Data&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>CycloneDX&lt;/strong> includes a dedicated &lt;code>vulnerabilities&lt;/code> array at the document level, allowing SBOMs to carry vulnerability information alongside component data. This is useful for creating Vulnerability Exploitability eXchange (VEX) documents and for attaching vulnerability assessments directly to SBOMs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>SPDX 2.3&lt;/strong> does not have a native vulnerability data structure. Vulnerability information must be conveyed through external references or separate documents.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>SPDX 3.0&lt;/strong> introduces a Security profile that adds vulnerability and VEX support, closing this gap.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="lifecycle-and-build-data">Lifecycle and Build Data&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>CycloneDX 1.7&lt;/strong> includes &lt;code>metadata.lifecycles[].phase&lt;/code> to indicate when the SBOM was generated (design, pre-build, build, post-build, operations, discovery, decommission). This aligns with the &lt;a href="https://www.cisa.gov/resources-tools/resources/types-software-bill-materials-sbom">CISA SBOM types taxonomy&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>SPDX 3.0&lt;/strong> supports build information through its Build profile, which can document build system, build commands, and build environment details.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sbom-format-examples">SBOM Format Examples&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A minimal SBOM documenting a single component in each format:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="cyclonedx-json">CycloneDX (JSON)&lt;/h3>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-json" data-lang="json">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>{
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;bomFormat&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;CycloneDX&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;specVersion&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;1.6&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">1&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;metadata&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;timestamp&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;2026-01-15T12:00:00Z&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;component&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;type&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;application&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;my-application&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;1.0.0&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;components&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;type&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;library&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;lodash&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;4.17.21&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;purl&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;pkg:npm/lodash@4.17.21&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;licenses&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [{ &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;license&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: { &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;id&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;MIT&amp;#34;&lt;/span> } }]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>}
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;h3 id="spdx-23-json">SPDX 2.3 (JSON)&lt;/h3>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-json" data-lang="json">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>{
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;spdxVersion&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;SPDX-2.3&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;dataLicense&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;CC0-1.0&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;SPDXID&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;SPDXRef-DOCUMENT&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;my-application&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;documentNamespace&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;https://example.com/my-application-1.0.0&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;creationInfo&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;created&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;2026-01-15T12:00:00Z&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;creators&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [&lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;Tool: example-tool-1.0&amp;#34;&lt;/span>]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;packages&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;SPDXID&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;SPDXRef-Package-lodash&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;lodash&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;versionInfo&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;4.17.21&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;downloadLocation&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;https://registry.npmjs.org/lodash/-/lodash-4.17.21.tgz&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;licenseConcluded&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;MIT&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;externalRefs&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;referenceCategory&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;PACKAGE-MANAGER&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;referenceType&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;purl&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;referenceLocator&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;pkg:npm/lodash@4.17.21&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>}
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Both formats express the same information — a component named &lt;code>lodash&lt;/code> at version &lt;code>4.17.21&lt;/code>, licensed under MIT. CycloneDX uses a more compact syntax; SPDX 2.3 requires additional fields like &lt;code>downloadLocation&lt;/code>, &lt;code>SPDXID&lt;/code>, and &lt;code>documentNamespace&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="compliance-framework-preferences">Compliance Framework Preferences&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Different regulatory frameworks have varying levels of format preference.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Framework&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Format Preference&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eo-14028/">Executive Order 14028&lt;/a> (US)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Format-agnostic; both accepted&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/cisa-minimum-elements/">CISA Minimum Elements&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Format-agnostic; references both&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eu-cra/">EU Cyber Resilience Act&lt;/a> (via BSI TR-03183-2)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>CycloneDX 1.6+ or SPDX 3.0.1+, JSON or XML format required&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/ntia-minimum-elements/">NTIA Minimum Elements&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Format-agnostic; both satisfy minimum element requirements&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/fda-medical-device/">FDA Medical Device&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>SPDX and CycloneDX both referenced in FDA guidance&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/nist-800-53/">NIST SP 800-53&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Format-agnostic; focuses on controls, not format&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/nist-800-171/">NIST SP 800-171&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Format-agnostic; focuses on CUI protection requirements&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The EU CRA&amp;rsquo;s implementing guidance (BSI TR-03183-2) is the most prescriptive, requiring specific minimum versions of each format. Most other frameworks are deliberately format-neutral.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tooling-ecosystem">Tooling Ecosystem&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Both formats have broad tooling support. Most modern SBOM tools support both formats, either natively or through conversion.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="generation-tools">Generation Tools&lt;/h3>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Tool&lt;/th>
&lt;th>CycloneDX&lt;/th>
&lt;th>SPDX&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Notes&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action/">sbomify GitHub Action&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Generation + enrichment + augmentation, CI/CD integration&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://github.com/anchore/syft">Syft&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Multi-ecosystem, container support&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://github.com/aquasecurity/trivy">Trivy&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Vulnerability scanning + SBOM generation&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://github.com/CycloneDX/cdxgen">cdxgen&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>CycloneDX-native, broad language support&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://github.com/microsoft/sbom-tool">Microsoft SBOM Tool&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>No&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>SPDX-native, CI/CD integration&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;h3 id="analysis-and-management-tools">Analysis and Management Tools&lt;/h3>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Tool&lt;/th>
&lt;th>CycloneDX&lt;/th>
&lt;th>SPDX&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Notes&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com">sbomify&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Integrated management, monitoring, and distribution&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://github.com/anchore/grype">Grype&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>CLI vulnerability scanner&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://dependencytrack.org/">OWASP Dependency-Track&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Standalone monitoring platform&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://google.github.io/osv-scanner/">OSV-Scanner&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Google&amp;rsquo;s vulnerability scanner&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>For a comprehensive tool listing organized by lifecycle phase, see our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/resources/">SBOM resources page&lt;/a>. For tool comparison and benchmarks, see the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbom-benchmarks">sbom-benchmarks repository&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="when-to-use-which-format">When to Use Which Format&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There is no single &amp;ldquo;winner&amp;rdquo; between CycloneDX and SPDX. The right choice depends on your primary use case:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Choose CycloneDX when:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Your primary concern is application security and vulnerability management&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You need to include vulnerability or VEX data directly in the SBOM&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You are targeting EU CRA compliance and prefer the more compact format&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Your toolchain already uses CycloneDX-native tools like cdxgen&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You want a simpler document model with fewer required fields&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Choose SPDX when:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>License compliance is your primary driver&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You need detailed file-level analysis (SPDX supports file and snippet elements)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You are working in ecosystems that have standardized on SPDX (e.g., some automotive and embedded Linux communities)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You need ISO/IEC standard status (ISO/IEC 5962:2021)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You are working with SPDX 3.0 profiles for specialized use cases (AI, Build, Dataset)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Support both when:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>You distribute software to diverse customers with different format preferences&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Your compliance obligations span multiple frameworks with different preferences&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You use tools like Syft or Trivy that generate both formats from a single scan&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Many organizations generate SBOMs in both formats or convert between them using tools like the &lt;a href="https://github.com/CycloneDX/cyclonedx-cli">CycloneDX CLI&lt;/a>. The formats are converging in capability, and the practical differences are narrowing with each release.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="frequently-asked-questions">Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="what-are-the-main-sbom-formats">What are the main SBOM formats?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The two industry-standard SBOM formats are CycloneDX (developed by OWASP, standardized as ECMA-424) and SPDX (developed by the Linux Foundation, standardized as ISO/IEC 5962:2021). Both support JSON and XML serialization, are accepted by major compliance frameworks, and have broad tooling support. CycloneDX originated in application security; SPDX originated in license compliance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-the-difference-between-cyclonedx-and-spdx">What is the difference between CycloneDX and SPDX?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>CycloneDX is a security-focused format with a compact, component-centric model and native support for vulnerability and VEX data. SPDX is a compliance-focused format with rich license documentation capabilities and support for file-level and snippet-level analysis. CycloneDX has a simpler document structure; SPDX (especially 3.0) offers a more flexible element-based model with profiles for specialized use cases. Both support purl, CPE, and hash-based component identification.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="which-sbom-format-should-i-use">Which SBOM format should I use?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>If your primary concern is application security and vulnerability management, CycloneDX is often the more straightforward choice. If license compliance is your primary driver, SPDX&amp;rsquo;s deeper license support may be more appropriate. For EU CRA compliance via BSI TR-03183-2, you need CycloneDX 1.6+ or SPDX 3.0.1+ in JSON or XML format. Many organizations support both formats, as most modern tools can generate either.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="can-i-convert-between-cyclonedx-and-spdx">Can I convert between CycloneDX and SPDX?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Yes. Tools like the CycloneDX CLI support conversion between formats. However, conversion may result in some data loss where one format supports fields that the other does not. For critical compliance use cases, it is better to generate natively in the required format rather than converting.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-an-sbom-example">What is an SBOM example?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>An SBOM is a machine-readable document listing every component in a software product, including names, versions, package identifiers (purl), licenses, and supplier information. See the CycloneDX and SPDX JSON examples in this article for minimal working examples. For real-world SBOMs with hundreds of components, see the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbom-benchmarks">sbom-benchmarks repository&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description><category>education</category></item><item><title>Unpacking Raspberry Pi&amp;#39;s Built‑In SBOM Magic</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2025/04/17/unpacking-raspberry-pi-s-built-in-sbom-magic/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2025/04/17/unpacking-raspberry-pi-s-built-in-sbom-magic/</guid><description>&lt;p>When the Raspberry Pi Foundation quietly unveiled &lt;a href="https://github.com/raspberrypi/rpi-image-gen">rpi‑image‑gen&lt;/a>, most of the headlines focused on how it streamlines custom image creation. Tucked inside that announcement is something even more exciting for anyone who cares about software supply‑chain transparency: every image it builds comes with a Software Bill of Materials (SBOM) out of the box.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you live and breathe SBOMs, or you just want to understand why this matters, read on. We will walk through how the tool works, where the SBOM lives, and what is inside it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="a-quick-primer-on-rpiimagegen">A Quick Primer on rpi‑image‑gen&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Think of rpi‑image‑gen as the flexible cousin of the long‑standing &lt;a href="https://github.com/RPi-Distro/pi-gen">pi‑gen&lt;/a> project that the Raspberry Pi team uses for the official Raspberry Pi OS builds. While pi‑gen is opinionated and optimized for the distro maintainers&amp;rsquo; workflow, rpi‑image‑gen is designed for developers and device makers who need bespoke images.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Building a minimal Debian 12 image for 64‑bit devices takes just a few commands:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>git clone https://github.com/raspberrypi/rpi-image-gen.git
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>cd rpi-image-gen
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>sudo ./install_deps.sh
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>./build.sh
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Important: run it on a Raspberry Pi OS (f.k.a. Raspbian) machine for the smoothest experience. Running under plain Debian or Ubuntu tends to trip over architecture mismatches.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once the build finishes, you will find everything in &lt;code>work/deb12-arm64-min/artefacts/&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-text" data-lang="text">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>boot.vfat
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>boot.vfat.sparse
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>config.yaml
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>deb12-arm64-min.img
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>deb12-arm64-min.img.sparse
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>deb12-arm64-min.sbom &amp;lt;-- the star of the show
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>fstab
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>...
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>&lt;code>deb12-arm64-min.img&lt;/code> is the file you flash to your SD card. Right beside it sits &lt;code>deb12-arm64-min.sbom&lt;/code>, a 6.8 MB JSON document that catalogues every component in the image.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-the-sbom-gets-made">How the SBOM Gets Made&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Under the hood, rpi‑image‑gen calls a helper script at &lt;code>sbom/gen.sh&lt;/code>. That script invokes &lt;strong>Syft&lt;/strong>, Anchore&amp;rsquo;s open‑source SBOM generator, to crawl the root filesystem and spit out an SPDX 2.3‑compliant file. The default settings live in &lt;code>sbom/defaults&lt;/code>, so you can swap formats or tweak depth without touching the core builder.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Running &lt;code>jq&lt;/code> on the finished SBOM shows 214 packages detected:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>cat deb12-arm64-min.sbom | jq &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;.packages | length&amp;#39;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e"># 214&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;h2 id="measuring-quality-with-sbomqs">Measuring Quality with &lt;code>sbomqs&lt;/code>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A big SBOM is not automatically a good SBOM. To gauge quality, we ran &lt;strong>sbomqs&lt;/strong> from Interlynk:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>SBOM Quality Score: 7.8 / 10.0
Components: 214
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>Here are a few highlights from the report:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Category&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Metric&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Score&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Notes&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>NTIA minimum elements&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Unique IDs&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10.0&lt;/td>
&lt;td>All components identified&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>NTIA minimum elements&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Supplier info&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5.8&lt;/td>
&lt;td>124 of 214 list a supplier&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Quality&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Valid licenses&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.0&lt;/td>
&lt;td>187 of 214 carry a recognized license&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Semantic&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Checksums&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.0&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Checksums missing, an easy win for improvement&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Structural&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Spec compliance&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10.0&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Valid SPDX 2.3 JSON&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Even with a few gaps, an out‑of‑the‑box score of 7.8 is impressive. Most importantly, the file is fully parsable and ready for vulnerability scans and license audits.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-builtin-sboms-matter">Why Built‑In SBOMs Matter&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Zero setup overhead&lt;/strong> – You do not need to glue extra scanners into your pipeline; the SBOM arrives with every build.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Reproducibility&lt;/strong> – Anyone flashing your image can inspect exactly what shipped, making security reviews and bug hunts faster.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Regulatory head‑start&lt;/strong> – As governments push for transparency (think EU Cyber Resilience Act or US Executive Order 14028), having machine‑readable SBOMs from day one keeps you ahead of the curve.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="tips-for-taking-it-further">Tips for Taking It Further&lt;/h2>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Enable checksum generation&lt;/strong>: Edit &lt;code>sbom/defaults&lt;/code> and add &lt;code>--file-digests&lt;/code> to Syft&amp;rsquo;s args to fill that gap in the quality score.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Switch formats&lt;/strong>: Need CycloneDX instead of SPDX? Change &lt;code>output_format&lt;/code> from &lt;code>spdx-json&lt;/code> to &lt;code>cyclonedx-json&lt;/code> in &lt;code>sbom/defaults&lt;/code>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Automate uploads&lt;/strong>: Pipe the &lt;code>.sbom&lt;/code> file into your CI artefact store or an SBOM analysis platform such as sbomify.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Raspberry Pi has quietly raised the bar for embedded‑image builders by shipping SBOMs as a first‑class citizen. If you already depend on Raspberry Pi boards, rpi‑image‑gen is worth the upgrade for this feature alone. And if you are exploring ways to make your firmware supply chain more transparent, it is one of the simplest on‑ramps you will find. For those using other embedded build systems, check out how &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/2025/02/21/mastering-sbom-generation-with-yocto/">Yocto handles SBOM generation&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Give it a spin, peek inside the SBOM, and let us know what you discover.&lt;/p></description><category>news</category></item><item><title>What&amp;#39;s New in SPDX 3: Enhanced Referencing Capabilities</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2024/07/22/whats-new-in-spdx-3-enhanced-referencing-capabilities/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 13:15:15 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2024/07/22/whats-new-in-spdx-3-enhanced-referencing-capabilities/</guid><description>&lt;p>At sbomify, we pride ourselves on providing the latest insights and updates in the realm of Software Bill of Materials (SBOM). One of the most anticipated developments is the draft release of SPDX 3, which brings a host of new features and improvements. Notably, SPDX 3 now includes enhanced referencing capabilities, a critical feature that has long been available in CycloneDX. Let’s delve into what this means for SBOM practitioners and how it positions SPDX 3 as a robust standard for software component documentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="enhanced-referencing-capabilities">Enhanced Referencing Capabilities&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>One of the standout features in SPDX 3 is its improved referencing capabilities. This feature, already supported in CycloneDX, allows for more efficient and accurate representation of complex software dependencies and relationships. The inclusion of this capability in SPDX 3 signifies a major leap forward for the standard, aligning it more closely with industry needs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Key Aspects of Enhanced Referencing:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Nested References:&lt;/strong> SPDX 3 supports nested references, enabling users to document multi-level dependencies with precision. This is particularly useful for large software projects where components are often built on top of multiple layers of dependencies.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Cross-Document References:&lt;/strong> Users can now reference elements across different SPDX documents, facilitating better modularization and management of SBOMs. This is essential for organizations that need to maintain separate SBOMs for different projects or components but want to maintain a cohesive overview.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improved Relationship Types:&lt;/strong> The new version introduces more granular relationship types, such as “includes,” “requires,” and “optional,” providing a clearer picture of how components interact within the software ecosystem.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="the-importance-of-referencing">The Importance of Referencing&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Accurate referencing is crucial for several reasons:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dependency Management:&lt;/strong> With software becoming increasingly complex, managing dependencies accurately is critical. Enhanced referencing allows for a more detailed and accurate representation of dependencies, reducing the risk of missing or incorrectly documenting a component.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mitigating Flattening of SBOMs:&lt;/strong> Referencing mitigates the need to &amp;ldquo;flatten&amp;rdquo; multiple SBOMs into a single large SBOM. Flattening can lead to a loss of crucial structural information and make it harder to track where a specific library or component is used. By allowing references to multiple SBOMs, SPDX 3 helps maintain the integrity and structure of each SBOM, making it easier to understand the usage and dependencies of specific libraries and components.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Security and Compliance:&lt;/strong> Knowing the exact relationships between components helps in assessing the impact of vulnerabilities and ensuring compliance with licensing terms. Enhanced referencing makes it easier to trace and manage these aspects.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Automation and Efficiency:&lt;/strong> Improved referencing capabilities streamline the automation of SBOM generation and validation processes. This leads to more efficient workflows and reduces the likelihood of human error.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h4 id="comparing-spdx-3-and-cyclonedx">Comparing SPDX 3 and CycloneDX&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>For those familiar with CycloneDX, the inclusion of enhanced referencing in SPDX 3 brings the two standards closer in terms of functionality. CycloneDX has been a popular choice for its detailed referencing capabilities, and with SPDX 3 catching up, users can now choose the standard that best fits their needs without compromising on this critical feature.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>CycloneDX vs. SPDX 3: Key Points&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Existing Strengths of CycloneDX:&lt;/strong> CycloneDX has been favored for its strong support for detailed and nested references, making it a go-to for many organizations.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>SPDX 3 Advancements:&lt;/strong> With the introduction of similar capabilities in SPDX 3, users now have the flexibility to choose SPDX while still benefiting from comprehensive referencing features.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="still-in-draft-what-it-means">Still in Draft: What It Means&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>It’s important to note that SPDX 3 is still in draft form. This means the specification is open for feedback and further refinement before its final release. The draft status provides an opportunity for the community to contribute insights and suggest improvements, ensuring that the final version meets the diverse needs of the industry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Implications of the Draft Status:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Community Involvement:&lt;/strong> Stakeholders can participate in the review process, providing feedback to shape the final version of SPDX 3.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Ongoing Refinement:&lt;/strong> The draft status indicates that while the core features are in place, there may be adjustments and enhancements based on community input.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The draft release of SPDX 3, with its enhanced referencing capabilities, marks a significant advancement for SBOM standards. At SBOMify.com, we are excited about these developments and the potential they hold for improving software transparency and security. By aligning more closely with the features offered by CycloneDX, SPDX 3 provides a robust and flexible option for documenting software components and their relationships.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We encourage you to explore the draft version of SPDX 3, provide feedback, and prepare for the transition to this enhanced standard. Stay tuned to sbomify for the latest updates and in-depth analyses as SPDX 3 moves towards its final release.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For more detailed information and to participate in the feedback process, visit the &lt;a href="https://spdx.org/spdx-specification-draft">SPDX 3 draft specification&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description><category>education</category></item><item><title>Exploring the New SPDX 3.0: A Game Changer for SBOMs</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2024/04/28/exploring-the-new-spdx-3-0-a-game-changer-for-sboms/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 14:07:39 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2024/04/28/exploring-the-new-spdx-3-0-a-game-changer-for-sboms/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>TL;DR:&lt;/strong> SPDX 3.0 is the latest update to the Software Package Data Exchange standard, significantly enhancing the way Software Bill of Materials (SBOMs) are created, maintained, and utilized across the software industry. This new version offers improved compatibility, detail, and process automation, making it an indispensable tool for managing software supply chain security, ensuring compliance, and improving quality assurance in an increasingly complex digital world.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-an-sbom">What is an SBOM?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A Software Bill of Materials (SBOM) is essentially a comprehensive inventory of all components, libraries, and modules contained in a piece of software. Think of it as a detailed list of ingredients that tells you exactly what’s in the software you use or develop. SBOMs are crucial for tracking the origins of software components, managing licenses, and most importantly, identifying potential security vulnerabilities.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="introducing-spdx-30">Introducing SPDX 3.0&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Software Package Data Exchange (SPDX) format is one of the most widely recognized standards for communicating SBOM information. Developed by the SPDX Workgroup under the Linux Foundation, it provides a common format for software tools to share data about software packages. With the introduction of SPDX 3.0, several advancements have been made to further enhance the utility and adoption of SBOMs across industries.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="enhanced-compatibility-and-flexibility">Enhanced Compatibility and Flexibility&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>One of the standout features of SPDX 3.0 is its increased compatibility and flexibility. This new version supports a broader range of software packages and environments, making it applicable to more complex software systems than ever before. Whether you are dealing with traditional applications, microservices, or even IoT devices, SPDX 3.0 offers a robust framework for documenting software components.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="improved-accuracy-and-detail">Improved Accuracy and Detail&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>SPDX 3.0 has significantly improved the level of detail and accuracy in documenting software components. This new version allows for more precise descriptions of each component, including its origin, version, and any known vulnerabilities. This enhancement not only aids developers and security professionals in identifying risks but also helps in compliance with various regulatory requirements.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="streamlined-processes">Streamlined Processes&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The introduction of automated tooling compatibility in SPDX 3.0 streamlines the process of generating and maintaining SBOMs. Tools that support SPDX 3.0 can automatically generate accurate and up-to-date SBOMs as part of the software development process. This automation reduces human error and ensures that SBOMs are always reflective of the current state of the software, thereby enhancing overall software supply chain security.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-spdx-30-matters">Why SPDX 3.0 Matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In today’s software development environment, where third-party and open-source components are ubiquitous, having a clear understanding of what’s inside your software is more critical than ever. Here’s why SPDX 3.0 is a game changer:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Security&lt;/strong>: With detailed component tracking, organizations can quickly respond to new vulnerabilities as they are discovered. SPDX 3.0 enables faster and more accurate vulnerability management.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Compliance&lt;/strong>: Many industries are subject to regulations that require detailed software component documentation. SPDX 3.0 facilitates compliance with these regulations, reducing the risk of non-compliance penalties.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Quality Assurance&lt;/strong>: By providing a clear picture of all software ingredients, SPDX 3.0 helps quality assurance teams identify potential compatibility issues, outdated libraries, or unsupported licenses.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As the adoption of SPDX 3.0 grows, we can expect a more standardized approach to SBOM management across the tech industry. This will likely lead to improved software security practices, more efficient compliance processes, and a greater overall trust in technology ecosystems.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For developers, security professionals, and compliance officers, embracing SPDX 3.0 offers an opportunity to stay ahead in managing software risks effectively. It’s not just about complying with the current standards but setting a foundation for a more secure future in software development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>SPDX 3.0 is not just a new format; it&amp;rsquo;s a strategic tool in the ongoing battle to secure software supply chains against the threats of today and tomorrow. As we move forward, leveraging this standard will be key to maintaining the integrity and security of our digital infrastructure.&lt;/p></description><category>education</category></item></channel></rss>