<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sbomify</title><link>https://sbomify.com/tags/release/</link><description>Your Security Artifact Hub. From zero to SBOM hero. Generate, manage, and share SBOMs and compliance documents. Built for CRA compliance and seamless integration with your existing tools.</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sbomify.com/tags/release/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Announcing sbomify v0.26: The One Where Bootstrap Moved Out</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/02/16/announcing-sbomify-v0-26-the-one-where-bootstrap-moved-out/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/02/16/announcing-sbomify-v0-26-the-one-where-bootstrap-moved-out/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="a-faster-more-accessible-ui">A Faster, More Accessible UI&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The first thing you will notice is that &lt;strong>sbomify feels faster&lt;/strong>. Pages load more quickly, transitions are smoother, and the interface is more consistent throughout the application. Dark mode now works reliably across every page, and accessibility has been improved with better contrast ratios, keyboard navigation, and screen reader support.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Under the hood, we rebuilt the entire frontend from scratch. But what matters to you is the result: a cleaner, more polished experience that gets out of your way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We have also redesigned the &lt;strong>onboarding wizard&lt;/strong>. New users can now get from sign-up to their first SBOM upload in fewer steps, with clearer guidance at each stage.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="real-time-dashboard-updates">Real-Time Dashboard Updates&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Until now, checking whether an assessment finished or a new SBOM was uploaded meant manually refreshing the page. That changes with v0.26.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Your dashboard now updates in &lt;strong>real-time&lt;/strong>. When a teammate uploads an SBOM, a compliance assessment completes, or a component status changes, you see it immediately. No more guessing, no more stale data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From your perspective, it just works.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="bsi-tr-03183-2-compliance">BSI TR-03183-2 Compliance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you operate in Germany or sell into the German market, sbomify now supports automated compliance checking against &lt;strong>BSI TR-03183-2&lt;/strong> — the German Federal Office for Information Security&amp;rsquo;s technical guideline for SBOM quality and completeness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like our other compliance plugins, you can enable it in &lt;strong>Settings -&amp;gt; Plugins&lt;/strong>. Once enabled, every SBOM upload is assessed automatically against the BSI requirements.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This plugin also introduces a &lt;strong>dependency system&lt;/strong> for compliance plugins. Plugins can now build on each other, so related standards share foundational checks rather than duplicating work. This means more consistent results across overlapping compliance frameworks.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="gdpr-self-service-account-deletion">GDPR Self-Service Account Deletion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Under GDPR, you have the right to delete your account and all associated data. Previously, this required contacting our support team and waiting for manual processing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With v0.26, you can &lt;strong>delete your own account&lt;/strong> directly from your profile settings. No tickets, no waiting. Your data is removed in accordance with our data retention policy.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="fine-grained-access-control">Fine-Grained Access Control&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>You can now control who sees what at a more granular level. Set &lt;strong>component visibility&lt;/strong> to restrict which components are visible to which roles, and control &lt;strong>document-level access&lt;/strong> to limit who can view specific SBOM documents.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is particularly useful for organizations sharing SBOMs externally through the &lt;strong>Trust Center&lt;/strong>. You can make some components public for customers and partners while keeping internal components private — all from the same workspace.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="other-improvements">Other Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Version field on Releases&lt;/strong> — You can now track release versions aligned with the Transparency Exchange API (TEA), making it easier to correlate SBOMs with specific product versions.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improved error tracking&lt;/strong> — We catch and resolve issues faster now, often before you notice them.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Custom login experience&lt;/strong> — The login page now uses a branded sbomify theme with better password validation feedback, so you know exactly what is needed when setting or changing your password.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Zero-downtime deployments&lt;/strong> — Deployments no longer cause brief interruptions. Updates happen seamlessly in the background, so the platform is always available.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="bug-fixes">Bug Fixes&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Fixed an issue where compliance assessments could fail on retry.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed IP address capture in NDA audit trails.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Improved error responses for duplicate SBOM uploads — the API response now includes an error code for easier debugging in CI/CD pipelines.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="infrastructure">Infrastructure&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>For self-hosted users, note that sbomify v0.26 now requires &lt;strong>Python 3.13&lt;/strong>. We have also updated several key dependencies, including gunicorn 25.x, ruff 0.15.x, and bandit 1.9.3. Check the full changelog for upgrade notes before updating your deployment.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you are on the &lt;strong>hosted platform&lt;/strong>, everything is already live — no action needed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For &lt;strong>self-hosted&lt;/strong> deployments, update to v0.26.0 by pulling the latest release.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/compare/v0.25.1...v0.26.0">full changelog on GitHub&lt;/a> for complete details. We would love to hear your feedback — reach out via &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/issues">GitHub Issues&lt;/a> or our community channels.&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item><item><title>Announcing sbomify-action v0.13: The One Where We Go to FOSDEM</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/02/04/announcing-sbomify-action-v0-13-the-one-where-we-go-to-fosdem/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/02/04/announcing-sbomify-action-v0-13-the-one-where-we-go-to-fosdem/</guid><description>&lt;p>We timed the sbomify-action v0.13 release for &lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2026/schedule/event/UYTGWA-sbom-generation/">FOSDEM 2026&lt;/a>, where we presented on CRA-ready SBOM generation.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="fosdem-2026-cra-ready-sboms">FOSDEM 2026: CRA-Ready SBOMs&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This past weekend, we presented at FOSDEM in the Software Bill of Materials devroom. The talk covers a four-phase SBOM generation model addressing the EU&amp;rsquo;s Cyber Resilience Act requirements: authoring, augmenting, enriching, and signing SBOMs to exceed minimal compliance standards. It includes a demo of an open-source workflow using sbomify-action, helping teams avoid compliance gaps as the CRA timeline approaches.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you missed it, you can watch the full talk below.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="video-embed-wrapper my-8 w-full max-w-3xl mx-auto">
&lt;div class="relative w-full overflow-hidden rounded-xl sm:rounded-2xl shadow-lg" style="padding-bottom: 56.25%;">
&lt;video
class="absolute top-0 left-0 w-full h-full border-0 bg-black"
controls
preload="metadata"
title="CRA-Ready SBOMs: A Practical Blueprint for High-Quality Generation">
&lt;source src="https://video.fosdem.org/2026/ud2208/UYTGWA-sbom-generation.av1.webm" type="video/webm">
Your browser does not support the video tag.
&lt;/video>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;script type="application/ld+json">
{
"@context": "https://schema.org",
"@type": "VideoObject",
"name": "CRA-Ready SBOMs: A Practical Blueprint for High-Quality Generation",
"description": "A four-phase SBOM generation model addressing the EU\u0026#39;s Cyber Resilience Act requirements, covering authoring, augmenting, enriching, and signing SBOMs.",
"uploadDate": "2026-02-04T00:00:00Z",
"contentUrl": "https:\/\/video.fosdem.org\/2026\/ud2208\/UYTGWA-sbom-generation.av1.webm"
}
&lt;/script>
&lt;p>You can also find the talk on the &lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2026/schedule/event/UYTGWA-sbom-generation/">FOSDEM schedule&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="whats-new-in-v013">What&amp;rsquo;s New in v0.13&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="breaking-changes">Breaking Changes&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Python 3.11+ now required&lt;/strong> - We have increased the minimum Python version from 3.10 to 3.11 to take advantage of the built-in &lt;code>tomllib&lt;/code> module for TOML parsing. If you are running sbomify-action locally, ensure you have Python 3.11 or later installed.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="new-features">New Features&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="hash-enrichment-from-lockfiles">Hash Enrichment from Lockfiles&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>A common gap in SBOMs is missing cryptographic hashes for components. Many SBOM generation tools do not extract hashes, even when they are available in lockfiles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The new hash enrichment subsystem automatically extracts cryptographic hashes from your lockfiles and adds them to SBOM components. This improves SBOM quality and supports integrity verification workflows.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Supported lockfiles:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Cargo.lock (Rust)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>package-lock.json (npm)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pipfile.lock (Pipenv)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>pnpm-lock.yaml (pnpm)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>poetry.lock (Poetry)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>pubspec.lock (Dart/Flutter)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>uv.lock (uv)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>yarn.lock (Yarn)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="interactive-configuration-wizard">Interactive Configuration Wizard&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Getting started with sbomify-action is now easier than ever. The new &lt;code>sbomify init&lt;/code> command walks you through an interactive wizard to create your &lt;code>sbomify.json&lt;/code> configuration file. Answer a few questions about your project, and the wizard generates a working configuration.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>sbomify-action init
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;h3 id="conan-center-enrichment">Conan Center Enrichment&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>C/C++ projects using Conan now get automatic metadata enrichment from the Conan Center API. For each package, we fetch:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>License information&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Author details&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Homepage URL&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Repository URL&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Package description&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This follows our enrichment-first philosophy: even if your SBOM generation tool produces sparse output, sbomify-action fills in the gaps from authoritative sources.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="component-supplier-field-ntia-compliance">Component Supplier Field (NTIA Compliance)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>NTIA&amp;rsquo;s minimum elements for SBOMs include supplier information. Previously, some tools would populate this with package authors, which is not quite right. The supplier should be the distribution platform, not the individual who wrote the code.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Components now include a &lt;code>supplier&lt;/code> field populated with the distribution platform:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>PyPI for Python packages&lt;/li>
&lt;li>npm for JavaScript packages&lt;/li>
&lt;li>crates.io for Rust packages&lt;/li>
&lt;li>And so on for other ecosystems&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This improves compliance with NTIA SBOM requirements.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="purl-generation-from-vcs-url">PURL Generation from VCS URL&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For SPDX SBOMs, the main package component now generates a PURL from the VCS (Version Control System) URL when no explicit PURL is available. This ensures better NTIA compliance by providing a unique identifier for your software, even when traditional package manager PURLs are not applicable.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="organization-data-from-contact-profile-api">Organization Data from Contact Profile API&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The sbomify API integration now extracts organizational data from the contact_profile structure. This means your SBOMs can include accurate manufacturer and supplier organization details from your sbomify account settings.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="improvements">Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="lifecycle-property-standardization">Lifecycle Property Standardization&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We have updated lifecycle properties to use the official CycloneDX taxonomy. If you are using lifecycle data in your SBOMs, the property names have changed:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Old Property&lt;/th>
&lt;th>New Property&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;code>cle:releaseDate&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>cdx:lifecycle:milestone:generalAvailability&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;code>cle:eos&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>cdx:lifecycle:milestone:endOfSupport&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;code>cle:eol&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>cdx:lifecycle:milestone:endOfLife&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>This aligns with the CycloneDX specification and improves interoperability with other tools.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="better-error-handling">Better Error Handling&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We have made significant improvements to error handling throughout the tool:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>ToolNotAvailableError&lt;/strong> - Graceful handling when SBOM generation tools are missing, with clear instructions on what to install&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improved &amp;ldquo;component not found&amp;rdquo; messages&lt;/strong> - More context about what failed and why&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Better diagnostic info&lt;/strong> - SBOM generation errors now include more details for debugging&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Path expansion errors&lt;/strong> - Now include the file name and searched paths&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CLI flag detection&lt;/strong> - Helpful error when a file path looks like a CLI flag (a common typo)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Stdout capture&lt;/strong> - Tools that output errors to stdout instead of stderr are now handled correctly&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Install from PyPI:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>pip install sbomify-action
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Or use the GitHub Action:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-yaml" data-lang="yaml">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>- &lt;span style="color:#f92672">uses&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">sbomify/github-action@v0.13&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Check out the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action/compare/v0.12...v0.13">full changelog on GitHub&lt;/a> for complete details.&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item><item><title>Announcing sbomify v0.25: The One with Attestations</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/23/announcing-sbomify-v0-25-the-one-with-attestations/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/23/announcing-sbomify-v0-25-the-one-with-attestations/</guid><description>&lt;p>Software supply chain security is not just about knowing what is in your software. It is about proving that knowledge is authentic and has not been tampered with. With v0.25, sbomify takes a significant step forward by introducing &lt;strong>attestation verification&lt;/strong>, allowing you to cryptographically verify the provenance of your SBOMs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="github-attestation-plugin">GitHub Attestation Plugin&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The headline feature of v0.25 is our new &lt;strong>GitHub Attestation Plugin&lt;/strong>. This plugin verifies SBOM attestations using &lt;a href="https://www.sigstore.dev/">Sigstore&lt;/a> and cosign, the same infrastructure that powers supply chain security across the open source ecosystem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When you generate an SBOM using GitHub Actions, you can sign it using GitHub&amp;rsquo;s built-in attestation capability. The sbomify GitHub Attestation Plugin then verifies these signatures automatically when you upload your SBOM. If the attestation is valid, you get cryptographic proof that the SBOM was generated by your CI/CD pipeline and has not been modified since.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The plugin includes automatic retry logic to handle transient network issues when communicating with the Sigstore transparency log. This ensures reliable verification even under less-than-ideal network conditions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is our first attestation plugin, building on the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/blob/master/docs/ADR/ADR-003.md">plugin architecture&lt;/a> we introduced in v0.24. We plan to add support for additional attestation formats including in-toto in future releases.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="spdx-23-export">SPDX 2.3 Export&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>sbomify has supported uploading SBOMs in both CycloneDX and SPDX formats for a while. With v0.25, we are adding the ability to &lt;strong>download aggregated SBOMs in SPDX 2.3 format&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can now download aggregated SBOMs for releases, projects, and products in either CycloneDX or SPDX format directly from the UI. This gives you flexibility when working with tools and partners that prefer one format over the other. Internally, we continue to use CycloneDX as our canonical format, but the SPDX export ensures you can meet requirements regardless of which standard your ecosystem uses.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="product-lifecycle-management">Product Lifecycle Management&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Knowing when your software reaches end-of-support or end-of-life is critical for compliance and vulnerability management. v0.25 introduces &lt;strong>Product Lifecycle&lt;/strong> fields aligned with the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/cle/">CLE (Common Lifecycle Enumeration)&lt;/a> standard that let you track:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Release Date&lt;/strong> - When the product version was released&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>End-of-Support Date&lt;/strong> - When active support ends&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>End-of-Life Date&lt;/strong> - When all support, including security updates, ends&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>You can set these dates manually in the UI for both &lt;strong>products&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>components&lt;/strong>. This is useful for tracking your own release schedules and support commitments.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For common Linux distributions and frameworks, lifecycle data can also be added automatically. The &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/blog/2026/01/20/announcing-sbomify-action-v0-11-the-one-where-they-go-to-pypi/#know-when-your-software-goes-end-of-life">Lifecycle Database&lt;/a> in sbomify-action embeds CLE data directly into your SBOMs during generation. This covers distributions like Ubuntu, Debian, Alpine, and Fedora, as well as language runtimes and frameworks including Python, Go, Django, Rails, and React.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These dates flow through to your Trust Center and can be displayed on public product pages. For organizations subject to regulations like the &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eu-cra/">EU Cyber Resilience Act&lt;/a>, tracking lifecycle information is a requirement.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="contact-role-flags">Contact Role Flags&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Building on the contact profile improvements from v0.24, this release adds &lt;strong>role flags&lt;/strong> to contacts. You can now designate contacts as:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Author&lt;/strong> - The person or team who created the component&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Security Contact&lt;/strong> - Who to reach for security issues&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Technical Contact&lt;/strong> - Who to reach for technical questions&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>We have also consolidated the previously separate author field into the main contact profile. Instead of managing authors separately, you now simply mark a contact as an author using the role flag. This simplifies contact management while aligning with how CycloneDX represents contact information.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="compliance-badges">Compliance Badges&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Compliance status is now more visible than ever. v0.25 introduces &lt;strong>compliance badges&lt;/strong> that display assessment results directly on product listings and public Trust Center pages. Badges only appear for assessments you pass, so you are showcasing compliance achievements rather than advertising gaps.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We have also added a &lt;strong>Copy Badge&lt;/strong> button that generates markdown snippets you can paste into your README files. This makes it easy to showcase your compliance status directly in your repository.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="other-improvements">Other Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CRA Plugin v1.1.0&lt;/strong> - The EU Cyber Resilience Act plugin now prioritizes native SBOM fields over &lt;code>cra:&lt;/code> annotations, making it easier to pass assessments without custom annotations&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Custom Domains&lt;/strong> - Added DCV (Domain Control Validation) delegation CNAME instructions for easier SSL certificate provisioning&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Architecture&lt;/strong> - Reorganized the codebase with cleaner api/domain/services layer separation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Billing&lt;/strong> - Enhanced billing processing and webhook handling for Stripe events (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Django Admin&lt;/strong> - Comprehensive theme update to match the webapp design system (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Footer&lt;/strong> - Simplified by removing version badges and moving build info to HTML comments (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="bug-fixes">Bug Fixes&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Fixed API error messages leaking team and resource information (security improvement)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed 403 errors when tagging SBOMs via API tokens in CI/CD pipelines&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed infinite &amp;ldquo;checking&amp;rdquo; state in the plugin UI when no plugins are enabled&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed RecursionError in public component page templates&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed plugin enable to not queue all historical SBOMs, which was blocking the web server (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed social card images with proper 1200x630 dimensions and meta tags (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed missing component context in component item view (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed SPDX SBOMs not being tagged to releases (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed social banner URLs for public Trust Center pages (v0.25.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To enable the GitHub Attestation Plugin, navigate to &lt;strong>Settings → Plugins&lt;/strong> and enable the GitHub Attestation assessment. From there, every SBOM upload with a valid attestation will be automatically verified.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For SPDX downloads, visit any release, project, or product page and use the format selector to download the aggregated SBOM in your preferred format.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out the full changelog for &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/compare/v0.24...v0.25">v0.25&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/compare/v0.25...v0.25.1">v0.25.1&lt;/a> on GitHub.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As always, I would love to hear your feedback. If you have questions about attestation verification or ideas for additional plugins, drop us a note or open an issue on GitHub.&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item><item><title>Announcing sbomify-action v0.11: The One Where They Go to PyPI</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/20/announcing-sbomify-action-v0-11-the-one-where-they-go-to-pypi/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/20/announcing-sbomify-action-v0-11-the-one-where-they-go-to-pypi/</guid><description>&lt;p>With v0.11, sbomify-action is no longer tied to your CI/CD pipeline. Install it anywhere with &lt;code>pip install sbomify-action&lt;/code> and generate enriched SBOMs on your laptop, in your build scripts, or wherever you need them. This release also tackles two of the biggest pain points in SBOM generation: missing license data and tracking end-of-life software.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="highlights">Highlights&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Use it anywhere&lt;/strong> - Install from PyPI and run locally, in CI, or in any workflow&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Fill in missing licenses&lt;/strong> - LicenseDB automatically adds license data for 28 Linux distro versions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Know when software goes EOL&lt;/strong> - Lifecycle Database tracks support dates for distros and frameworks&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Choose your format&lt;/strong> - SPDX and CycloneDX with feature parity&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Prove what happened&lt;/strong> - Audit trail logs every SBOM transformation for compliance&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Rust projects welcome&lt;/strong> - Native generation and enrichment for the Rust ecosystem&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="never-miss-a-license-again">Never Miss a License Again&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>One of the most frustrating aspects of generating SBOMs for container images is discovering that half your packages are missing license information. This happens because many Linux distribution packages do not include machine-readable license metadata in their package manifests.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>LicenseDB&lt;/strong> solves this. We have built a pre-computed database of valid package licenses covering 28 Linux distro versions:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Debian (11, 12, 13)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ubuntu (20.04, 22.04, 24.04)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Alpine (3.13-3.21)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fedora (39, 40, 41, 42)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Amazon Linux (2, 2023)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>CentOS Stream (8, 9)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>AlmaLinux (8, 9)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rocky Linux (8, 9)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Wolfi/Chainguard (rolling)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>When you generate an SBOM, LicenseDB automatically fills in license data for packages that would otherwise be missing it. The lookup is architecture-agnostic, so you get consistent results whether you are building for amd64 or arm64.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>LicenseDB is our primary license source, but not our only one. We integrate with multiple providers for license data, including PyPI, crates.io, and other package registries. LicenseDB is checked first because it is fast (downloaded once from GitHub releases then cached locally) and reliable. When LicenseDB does not have coverage for a package, we fall back to other sources. See our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/features/integrations/">integrations page&lt;/a> for the full list of data sources.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We take a conservative approach: LicenseDB only includes licenses we can verify from authoritative sources. This means we do not have full coverage of every package, but we would rather provide a smaller, accurate database than try to guess licenses with heuristics. When it comes to license compliance, accuracy matters more than completeness.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="know-when-your-software-goes-end-of-life">Know When Your Software Goes End-of-Life&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Compliance frameworks like FedRAMP and SOC2 increasingly require organizations to demonstrate they are not running end-of-life software. But tracking EOL dates across dozens of components, base images, and frameworks is tedious and error-prone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The new &lt;strong>Lifecycle Database&lt;/strong> embeds &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/cle/">CLE (Common Lifecycle Enumeration)&lt;/a> data directly into your SBOMs, following the ECMA-428 specification. For every component we recognize, you get:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>What You Learn&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Why It Matters&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Release Date&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Know how old a component is&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>End of Support&lt;/td>
&lt;td>When bugfixes stop (security-only after this)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>End of Life&lt;/td>
&lt;td>When all support ends, including security patches&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;h3 id="coverage">Coverage&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Linux Distributions&lt;/strong>: Alpine, Ubuntu, Debian, Fedora, Rocky Linux, AlmaLinux, Amazon Linux, CentOS Stream, Oracle Linux, openSUSE Leap, Wolfi&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Language Runtimes and Frameworks&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Python (2.7, 3.10-3.14)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>PHP (7.4, 8.0-8.5)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Go (1.22-1.25)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rust (1.90-1.92)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Django (4.2, 5.2, 6.0)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rails (7.0-8.1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Laravel (10-13)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>React (17, 18, 19)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vue.js (2, 3)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>With this data in your SBOMs, you can answer questions like &amp;ldquo;Which of our containers are running EOL base images?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;When does Python 3.12 stop receiving security patches?&amp;rdquo; without leaving your SBOM tooling.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is what the lifecycle data looks like in a CycloneDX SBOM:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-json" data-lang="json">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>{
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;python3&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;version&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;3.12.1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;properties&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> { &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;cle:releaseDate&amp;#34;&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;value&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;2023-10-02&amp;#34;&lt;/span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> { &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;cle:eos&amp;#34;&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;value&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;2025-04-02&amp;#34;&lt;/span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> { &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;cle:eol&amp;#34;&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;#34;value&amp;#34;&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;2028-10-31&amp;#34;&lt;/span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>}
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;h2 id="run-it-anywhere">Run It Anywhere&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Until now, sbomify-action lived exclusively in CI/CD pipelines. That made it hard to test configurations, debug issues, or generate SBOMs during local development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With v0.11, install it from PyPI and run it wherever you need:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>pip install sbomify-action
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>$ sbomify-action
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> __ _ ____ ___ __ _
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> _____/ /_ ____ ____ ___ &lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>_&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span> __/_ __ / | _____/ /_&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>_&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>___ ____
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> / ___/ __ &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">\/&lt;/span> __ &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">\/&lt;/span> __ &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">`&lt;/span>__ &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">\/&lt;/span> / /_/ / / / / /| |/ ___/ __/ / __ &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">\/&lt;/span> __ &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">\
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>__ &lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span> /_/ / /_/ / / / / / / / __/ /_/ / / ___ / /__/ /_/ / /_/ / / / /
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>/____/_.___/&lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">\_&lt;/span>___/_/ /_/ /_/_/_/ &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">\_&lt;/span>_, / /_/ |_&lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">\_&lt;/span>__/&lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">\_&lt;/span>_/_/&lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">\_&lt;/span>___/_/ /_/
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> /____/
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>v0.11 - Zero to SBOM hero
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>The CLI supports both command-line flags and environment variables, so your existing CI configurations translate directly. Test locally, commit with confidence.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="choose-cyclonedx-or-spdx">Choose CycloneDX or SPDX&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Your supply chain partners may require SPDX. Your internal tooling may expect CycloneDX. You should not have to choose between them or accept a degraded experience with one format.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our goal is &lt;strong>feature parity between CycloneDX and SPDX&lt;/strong>. With v0.11, we have made significant progress:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>sbomify-action --lock-file requirements.txt -f spdx -o sbom.spdx.json
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>License sanitization, lifecycle data, and enrichment from all data sources now work identically regardless of output format. Whichever format your organization or supply chain partners require, you get the same high-quality, enriched SBOMs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="prove-what-happened-to-your-sbom">Prove What Happened to Your SBOM&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When auditors or customers ask how an SBOM was generated, you need to show your work. The new &lt;strong>audit trail&lt;/strong> logs every transformation applied during generation and enrichment, with timestamps.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-gets-tracked">What Gets Tracked&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Overrides&lt;/strong> - Component name, version, and PURL changes from CLI or environment variables&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Augmentation&lt;/strong> - Supplier, manufacturer, authors, licenses, VCS info, lifecycle phase additions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Enrichment&lt;/strong> - Per-component metadata additions (description, license, publisher, URLs)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sanitization&lt;/strong> - PURL normalizations, URL validations, stub components added&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="output">Output&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Every run produces three outputs:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Summary table&lt;/strong> in the console showing counts by category&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>audit_trail.txt&lt;/strong> written alongside your SBOM output with full details&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Collapsible group&lt;/strong> in GitHub Actions with the complete audit trail&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Here is what the audit trail looks like:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code># SBOM Audit Trail
# Generated: 2026-01-18T12:34:56Z
# Input: requirements.txt
# Output: sbom.cdx.json
## Override
[2026-01-18T12:34:56Z] OVERRIDE component.version SET &amp;#34;2.0.0&amp;#34; (source: cli/env)
[2026-01-18T12:34:56Z] OVERRIDE component.name MODIFIED &amp;#34;old-name&amp;#34; -&amp;gt; &amp;#34;my-app&amp;#34; (source: cli/env)
## Enrichment
[2026-01-18T12:34:57Z] ENRICHMENT pkg:pypi/requests@2.31.0 license ADDED (source: pypi)
[2026-01-18T12:34:57Z] ENRICHMENT pkg:pypi/requests@2.31.0 description ADDED (source: pypi)
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>All timestamps are in UTC (ISO 8601 format), making it easy to correlate with CI logs and other audit evidence. This is exactly the provenance and integrity evidence that compliance frameworks like FedRAMP and SOC2 require.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="rust-ecosystem-support">Rust Ecosystem Support&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Rust projects now get first-class support:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Native SBOM generation via cargo-cyclonedx&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Package metadata enrichment from crates.io&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This follows our &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action/blob/master/docs/adr/0001-plugin-architecture.md">plugin architecture&lt;/a> principle of &amp;ldquo;native-first with generic fallback.&amp;rdquo; Native sources like crates.io provide the most accurate metadata for their ecosystem, with generic aggregators as fallbacks for broader coverage.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="other-improvements">Other Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Docker Image&lt;/strong>: Multi-arch support (amd64/arm64), lazy installation of Java/Maven and Go to reduce image size.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>PURL Handling&lt;/strong>: Fixed double-encoding issues, consistent version updates, short git hashes for SBOM versions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Compliance&lt;/strong>: NTIA compliance checkers aligned with the NTIA 2021 standard.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="breaking-changes">Breaking Changes&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The &lt;code>rpmrepo&lt;/code> and &lt;code>ubuntu&lt;/code> enrichment sources have been removed, replaced by LicenseDB which provides broader and more consistent coverage.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Install from PyPI:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>pip install sbomify-action
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Or continue using the GitHub Action as before. The CLI and Action share the same codebase and configuration options.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action/compare/v0.10...v0.11">full changelog on GitHub&lt;/a> for complete details.&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item><item><title>Announcing sbomify v0.24: The One with All the Plugins</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/14/announcing-sbomify-v0-24-the-one-with-all-the-plugins/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2026/01/14/announcing-sbomify-v0-24-the-one-with-all-the-plugins/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today marks a pivotal release for sbomify. With v0.24, we are laying the foundation for what will become a fully extensible, plugin-based platform. This release introduces our new &lt;strong>Plugin-Based Assessment Framework&lt;/strong>, a unified architecture for running automated assessments on every SBOM upload. This represents a fundamental shift in how we think about sbomify&amp;rsquo;s architecture going forward.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="plugin-based-assessment-framework">Plugin-Based Assessment Framework&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The headline feature of v0.24 is our new assessment plugin system, documented in &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/blob/master/docs/ADR/ADR-003.md">ADR-003: Plugin-based Assessments for SBOM Uploads&lt;/a>. If you want to understand where sbomify is headed, this architectural decision record is essential reading.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="four-assessment-categories">Four Assessment Categories&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The plugin framework is designed to support four distinct categories of SBOM assessment:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Category&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Description&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Examples&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Security&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Vulnerability scanning via external tools and APIs&lt;/td>
&lt;td>OSV, Dependency-Track&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>License&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Policy evaluation against approved/denied license lists&lt;/td>
&lt;td>License policy checks&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Compliance&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Validation against regulatory and industry standards&lt;/td>
&lt;td>NTIA, CISA, CRA, FDA&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Attestation&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Integrity and provenance verification&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Sigstore, in-toto&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Each category has different characteristics. Security plugins integrate with external vulnerability databases that change continuously, so they support scheduled re-runs. Compliance and license plugins are deterministic for a given ruleset version. Attestation plugins verify cryptographic signatures and provenance data.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="compliance-plugins-shipping-now">Compliance Plugins Shipping Now&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This release ships with five compliance plugins ready to use. Each plugin aligns with our &lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/">compliance documentation&lt;/a>, so you can understand exactly what is being validated:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/ntia-minimum-elements/">NTIA Minimum Elements&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> - Validates your SBOMs against the foundational US baseline for SBOM data fields&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/cisa-minimum-elements/">CISA 2025 Minimum Elements&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> - Checks compliance with the updated US guidance including hash, license, and generation context&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/eu-cra/">EU Cyber Resilience Act (CRA)&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> - Validates against Regulation 2024/2847 requirements (beta)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://sbomify.com/compliance/fda-medical-device/">FDA Medical Device Cybersecurity&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> - Ensures medical device SBOM requirements are met, including lifecycle properties&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Checksum Verification&lt;/strong> - A test plugin that validates SBOM integrity through checksum verification (useful as a reference implementation)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Each plugin runs automatically when you upload an SBOM. Simply enable the plugins you need in &lt;strong>Settings → Plugins&lt;/strong>, and assessments happen transparently in the background.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="why-this-architecture-matters">Why This Architecture Matters&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The design decisions in ADR-003 are intentional and set the stage for everything that follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Assessments tied to uploads, not content hashes&lt;/strong> - Each upload is assessed independently, giving you a complete history of checks over time&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Immutable AssessmentRun records&lt;/strong> - Every assessment is recorded permanently, enabling full audit trails and historical tracking&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Python SDK with normalized results&lt;/strong> - All plugins return results in a consistent &lt;code>AssessmentResult&lt;/code> schema with &lt;code>Finding&lt;/code> entries, making it easy to compare and aggregate data across plugin types&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Config hashing for reproducibility&lt;/strong> - When assessment results change, you can trace exactly why by comparing configuration hashes&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Per-team plugin enablement&lt;/strong> - Teams can enable the plugins relevant to their needs, with feature gating based on billing plans&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-migration-path">The Migration Path&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This plugin system is the future of sbomify. In upcoming releases, we will be migrating our existing features into this architecture:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Phase 2: Security Plugins&lt;/strong>
Our current &lt;strong>OSV vulnerability scanning&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>Dependency Track integration&lt;/strong> will be refactored into security plugins. This migration will make these features more modular, give you historical tracking of all vulnerability scans, and allow the same plugin architecture to power scheduled re-scans as vulnerability databases are updated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Phase 3 and Beyond&lt;/strong>
We have a roadmap of additional plugins including license policy evaluation, attestation verification (Sigstore and in-toto), and VEX (Vulnerability Exploitability eXchange) statement processing. The goal is to make sbomify a platform where you can mix and match the capabilities you need.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="vuejs-to-alpinejs-migration-complete">Vue.js to Alpine.js Migration Complete&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We have completed the frontend migration we started in previous releases. This release replaces the remaining &lt;strong>35 Vue.js components&lt;/strong> with lightweight Alpine.js implementations backed by Django templates.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This migration closes out &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/blob/master/docs/ADR/ADR-001.md">ADR-001: Django Monolith&lt;/a>. As documented there, our detour into Vue turned out to be a mistake. While we wanted to maintain an API-first approach, leveraging Django Templates with server-side rendering minimizes complexity compared to a separate Vue frontend. Equally important, Vue made end-to-end testing more challenging, and we had several blocks silently failing as a result.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The result is a significantly smaller bundle size, faster page loads, a more maintainable codebase, and much better test coverage. If you have been following our journey from Vue.js to Alpine.js + HTMX, this release marks the finish line.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="contact-profiles-cyclonedx-alignment">Contact Profiles CycloneDX Alignment&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Contact profiles have been restructured to align with the CycloneDX specification. The new &lt;strong>3-level hierarchy&lt;/strong> (Profile → Entity → Contact) matches how CycloneDX represents organizational and contact information.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you have existing contact profiles, they will be automatically migrated to the new structure. No action required on your part.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="billing-system-improvements">Billing System Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We have made several improvements to how billing works:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dynamic pricing from Stripe&lt;/strong> - Pricing is now synced directly from Stripe, ensuring consistency across the platform&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Promotion codes at checkout&lt;/strong> - You can now apply promotion codes when subscribing or upgrading&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Billing period visibility&lt;/strong> - Your current billing period and next billing date are now displayed in team settings&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improved subscription management&lt;/strong> - New management commands for subscription reconciliation and better webhook handling&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="other-improvements">Other Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Trust Center&lt;/strong>: Consolidated templates, improved SEO, and better UX across the board&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CycloneDX 1.6+&lt;/strong>: Added manufacturer field support with backward compatibility for 1.5&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CI/CD Templates&lt;/strong>: New configuration templates for Azure DevOps and Jenkins&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>License Expressions&lt;/strong>: Optimized parsing with server-side rendering support&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mobile Experience&lt;/strong>: Improved search bar responsiveness on mobile devices&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Document Upload&lt;/strong>: Better drag-and-drop experience&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Workspace Labels&lt;/strong>: Now use title case (Product, Compliance Artifact, Project)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="security-and-infrastructure">Security and Infrastructure&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>On the security front, we addressed findings from Semgrep and Bandit scans, added &lt;code>noreferrer&lt;/code> to external links, and fixed a user invitation limit bypass vulnerability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Infrastructure updates include upgrading our base image to &lt;strong>Debian Trixie&lt;/strong>, updating &lt;code>python-keycloak&lt;/code> to 7.0.1, and bumping our GitHub Actions dependencies to their latest versions.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="bug-fixes">Bug Fixes&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Fixed duplicate artifacts appearing in release pages when components belong to multiple projects&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed barcode rendering on private product identifiers page&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed latest badge display and modal issues in release UI&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed private component access returning 404 instead of 403 Forbidden&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed &lt;code>$schema&lt;/code> alias handling in CycloneDX SBOM serialization&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed domain verification cron job registration&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you are self-hosting sbomify, update to v0.24 to take advantage of the new plugin system. For users on our hosted platform, these features are already live.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To enable assessment plugins, navigate to &lt;strong>Settings → Plugins&lt;/strong> and enable the assessments relevant to your requirements. From there, every SBOM upload will be automatically assessed, with full historical tracking of all results.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/compare/v0.23...master">full changelog on GitHub&lt;/a> for complete details.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As always, I would love to hear your feedback. Drop us a note or open an issue on GitHub if you have questions, suggestions, or ideas for new plugins. The plugin architecture is designed to be extensible, and we are eager to hear what assessments would be most valuable to you!&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item><item><title>Major Updates: sbomify v0.21 and Action Module v0.8 &amp;amp; v0.9</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2025/12/19/major-updates-sbomify-v0-21-and-action-modules/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2025/12/19/major-updates-sbomify-v0-21-and-action-modules/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://sbomify.com/assets/images/sbomify-v0-21-release.png" alt="Major Updates">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We have been busy at sbomify! Today we are announcing a triple release covering significant updates to both the core platform and our GitHub Action module. Here is a breakdown of what&amp;rsquo;s new.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sbomify-v021-the-one-where-we-almost-ditched-vue">sbomify v0.21: &amp;ldquo;The One Where We Almost Ditched Vue&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This release brings substantial improvements to the user interface and underlying technology stack. As the release name suggests, we&amp;rsquo;ve undertaken a significant refactoring effort to streamline our frontend architecture.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="key-features">Key Features&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Vulnerability Trends Dashboard:&lt;/strong> A new interactive dashboard to visualize vulnerability trends over time.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Enhanced Workspace Management:&lt;/strong> A new workspace switcher with a modal interface in the sidebar makes managing multiple environments easier than ever.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Custom Keycloak Login:&lt;/strong> We&amp;rsquo;ve introduced a custom Keycloak login theme with Tailwind CSS styling for a more seamless authentication experience.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improved Navigation:&lt;/strong> A new navbar search, improved notifications, and version display in the footer.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Under the hood, we migrated the Documents and SBOMs tables from Vue.js to &lt;strong>HTMX and Alpine.js&lt;/strong>, resulting in a lighter and more responsive interface. We also cleaned up the codebase by removing deprecated Vue.js components.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/releases/tag/v0.21">Read the full v0.21 release notes&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="sbomify-action-v09-the-one-where-generation-gets-modular">sbomify-action v0.9: &amp;ldquo;The One Where Generation Gets Modular&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Our GitHub Action module has received a major architectural upgrade focused on modularity and extensibility.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="modular-generation">Modular Generation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Version 0.9 introduces a &lt;strong>plugin architecture for SBOM generation&lt;/strong>. This system uses priority-based selection with automatic fallback (e.g., trying &lt;code>cyclonedx-py&lt;/code> first, then &lt;code>Trivy&lt;/code>, then &lt;code>Syft&lt;/code>), ensuring you get the best possible SBOM for your project type without manual configuration.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="ubuntu-apt-enrichment">Ubuntu APT Enrichment&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We&amp;rsquo;ve added native metadata source support for &lt;code>pkg:deb/ubuntu/*&lt;/code> packages, covering LTS versions from 18.04 to 24.04 and 24.10.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="built-in-validation">Built-in Validation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Generated SBOMs are now automatically validated against the JSON Schema to ensure strict compliance.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="sbomify-action-v08-the-one-with-enrichment-plugins">sbomify-action v0.8: &amp;ldquo;The One With Enrichment Plugins&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Just prior to v0.9, we released v0.8, which completely rewrote the SBOM enrichment system.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="plugin-based-enrichment">Plugin-based Enrichment&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Similar to generation, enrichment is now plugin-based. We prioritize multiple data sources to maximize NTIA compliance. We have implemented 8 data sources including &lt;strong>PyPI, Debian, deps.dev, ecosyste.ms, PURL, ClearlyDefined, Repology, and RPM Repo&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Crucially, &lt;strong>lockfile components are now enriched&lt;/strong> rather than removed, preserving the integrity of your dependency graph while adding valuable metadata.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="expanded-ecosystem-support">Expanded Ecosystem Support&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>RPM Repository Enrichment:&lt;/strong> Native Tier 1 enrichment for RHEL-compatible distros (Rocky, Alma, CentOS Stream, Fedora, Amazon Linux).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dart/Flutter:&lt;/strong> Added support for Dart packages via pub.dev and &lt;code>pubspec.lock&lt;/code> enrichment.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CycloneDX 1.7:&lt;/strong> Full support for the latest CycloneDX 1.7 schema.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>These updates represent a significant step forward in making sbomify the most flexible and compliant SBOM management platform.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out the updated &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action">sbomify-action repository&lt;/a> to get started with these new features!&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item><item><title>Announcing sbomify v0.20: Custom Domains &amp;amp; Streamlined Onboarding</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2025/12/12/announcing-sbomify-0-20/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2025/12/12/announcing-sbomify-0-20/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://sbomify.com/assets/images/release-0-20-cover.png" alt="sbomify v0.20 Release">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We&amp;rsquo;re excited to announce the release of &lt;strong>sbomify v0.20&lt;/strong>, a significant update focused on empowering organizations to make their Trust Center truly their own. This release introduces custom domain support, a redesigned onboarding experience, and numerous improvements to workspace management and security.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="custom-domain-support">Custom Domain Support&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The headline feature of v0.20 is &lt;strong>custom domain support for public Trust Center pages&lt;/strong>. Workspaces can now use their own domain (via CNAME) to serve their public Trust Center, making it seamlessly integrate with their existing web presence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With this update, you can:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Configure a custom domain directly from your workspace branding settings&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Use clean, slug-based URLs when accessing via your custom domain&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Benefit from extended caching with proper invalidation when your content changes&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This feature is perfect for organizations that want their Trust Center to live at something like &lt;code>trust.yourcompany.com&lt;/code> rather than a subdomain of sbomify.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="redesigned-onboarding-wizard">Redesigned Onboarding Wizard&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We&amp;rsquo;ve completely reimagined the onboarding experience for new users. The previous multi-step wizard has been simplified into a &lt;strong>single-step SBOM identity setup&lt;/strong> that gets you up and running faster.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Key improvements include:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Automatic redirect for first-time users to set up their SBOM identity&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Plan-aware getting started flow that adapts to your subscription&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Modernized UI with better handling of edge cases&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="workspace-management-enhancements">Workspace Management Enhancements&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Managing your workspace just got easier with several quality-of-life improvements:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Workspace name editing&lt;/strong>: Change your workspace name directly from settings&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>User invitation management&lt;/strong>: Manage pending invitations from the settings page&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improved session management&lt;/strong>: Better caching and workspace switching with proper cache invalidation&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="team-invitation-system-improvements">Team Invitation System Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We&amp;rsquo;ve overhauled how team invitations work with a new &lt;strong>token-based invitation system&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>More secure invitation URLs backed by database tokens&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Persistent team settings with toast notifications for invitation status&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Improved handling and styling throughout the invitation flow&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="public-pages-improvements">Public Pages Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Your public Trust Center pages now offer an even better experience:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Breadcrumb navigation&lt;/strong> for easier navigation on component pages&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Copy-to-clipboard functionality&lt;/strong> for quick sharing&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed layout and logo display issues&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Consistent &amp;ldquo;Trust Center&amp;rdquo; capitalization across all templates&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="security-hardening">Security Hardening&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This release includes important security improvements:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Fixed incomplete URL substring sanitization (addressing CodeQL alerts)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Added admin permission restrictions for removing team owners&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Improved workspace member removal and session handling&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Added comprehensive tests for edge cases with pending invitations&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="infrastructure-updates">Infrastructure Updates&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Under the hood, we&amp;rsquo;ve made several infrastructure improvements:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Improved HTTPS/TLS handling with Caddy&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Configurable port exposure in Docker setup&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New &lt;code>bin/deploy.sh&lt;/code> deployment script&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Updated deployment documentation&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="by-the-numbers">By the Numbers&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This release involved significant effort across the codebase:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>125 files changed&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>~9,663 lines added&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>~1,611 lines removed&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re self-hosting sbomify, update to v0.20 to take advantage of these new features. For users on our hosted platform, these improvements are already live.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/releases/tag/v0.20">full changelog on GitHub&lt;/a> for complete details.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As always, we welcome your feedback and contributions. Drop us a note or open an issue on GitHub if you have questions or suggestions!&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item><item><title>Announcing GitHub Action 0.7.0 and sbomify 0.19</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2025/12/05/announcing-github-action-0-7-0-and-sbomify-0-19/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2025/12/05/announcing-github-action-0-7-0-and-sbomify-0-19/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://sbomify.com/assets/images/release-0-19-cover.png" alt="Zero to SBOM Hero">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We are excited to announce significant updates to both our GitHub Action and the core sbomify platform. This release brings major architectural improvements, enhanced security features, and expanded support for SBOM standards.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="github-action-070">&lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/github-action/releases/tag/v0.7.0">GitHub Action 0.7.0&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The latest version of our GitHub Action includes major changes to enrichment, format support, and telemetry.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="major-changes">Major Changes&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Enrichment via ecosyste.ms&lt;/strong>: We have switched our package metadata enrichment from Parley to the &lt;a href="https://ecosyste.ms">ecosyste.ms&lt;/a> API. A big thank you to @andrew for this integration!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>SPDX Support&lt;/strong>: We now offer full support for SPDX 2.2 and 2.3 formats alongside CycloneDX, powered by the new &lt;code>spdx-tools&lt;/code> dependency.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Enhanced Telemetry&lt;/strong>: Sentry error tracking now respects repository visibility, ensuring that private repositories do not send CI context.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="improvements">Improvements&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>API Updates&lt;/strong>: The product releases API now uses &lt;code>sbom_id&lt;/code> instead of &lt;code>artifact_id&lt;/code>/&lt;code>artifact_type&lt;/code>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Release Tagging&lt;/strong>: Improved workflow for release tagging with better ID resolution.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Vendor Normalization&lt;/strong>: Fixed tool vendor normalization to prevent serialization comparison errors.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Caching&lt;/strong>: Better cache management for enrichment API calls.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Error Filtering&lt;/strong>: User errors (validation/configuration) are now filtered from telemetry to reduce noise.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="testing--dependencies">Testing &amp;amp; Dependencies&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We&amp;rsquo;ve added comprehensive Sentry filtering tests across GitHub Actions, GitLab CI, and Bitbucket Pipelines, along with new tool vendor normalization tests. Dependencies have been updated to include &lt;code>spdx-tools&lt;/code>, &lt;code>beartype&lt;/code>, &lt;code>click&lt;/code>, &lt;code>isodate&lt;/code>, &lt;code>ply&lt;/code>, &lt;code>rdflib&lt;/code>, &lt;code>semantic-version&lt;/code>, &lt;code>uritools&lt;/code>, and &lt;code>xmltodict&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="sbomify-019">&lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/releases/tag/v0.19">sbomify 0.19&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is a massive release for the sbomify platform, involving a complete frontend architecture migration and significant infrastructure enhancements.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="summary">Summary&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Major frontend architecture migration&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Infrastructure enhancements&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="architecture-changes">Architecture Changes&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We have almost completed the full migration from Vue.js to a stack of &lt;strong>Django + HTMX + Alpine.js&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Removed ~3,700 lines of Vue code.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>All frontend is now server-driven with Django templates.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Added &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/blob/master/docs/ADR/ADR-001.md">&lt;code>ADR-001&lt;/code>&lt;/a> (Django Monolith) and &lt;a href="https://github.com/sbomify/sbomify/blob/master/docs/ADR/ADR-002.md">&lt;code>ADR-002&lt;/code>&lt;/a> (Languages &amp;amp; Frameworks) to our architectural decision records.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="infrastructure--security">Infrastructure &amp;amp; Security&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Caddy Reverse Proxy&lt;/strong>: Now handling automatic Let&amp;rsquo;s Encrypt TLS certificate management and health monitoring.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Custom Domain Support&lt;/strong>: Workspaces can now use custom domains with auto-provisioned TLS and automated validation.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Security&lt;/strong>:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Added Turnstile CAPTCHA on enterprise contact forms.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Enhanced client IP detection with spoofing protection.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Keycloak authentication fixes.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="new-features">New Features&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Global Components&lt;/strong>: Workspace-level reusable components.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Contact Profiles&lt;/strong>: Reusable supplier information for SBOMs.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Workspace Visibility Controls&lt;/strong>: Toggle between public and private workspaces (paid plans).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improved CycloneDX 1.6 &amp;amp; added 1.7 Support&lt;/strong>: Support for the latest SBOM specifications.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Release Date Tracking&lt;/strong>: Added an optional &lt;code>released_at&lt;/code> field.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Vulnerability Scanning Dashboard&lt;/strong>: Centralized management for scans.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Enhanced Trust Center&lt;/strong>: A redesigned public workspace page for better transparency.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>These updates mark a significant step forward in our mission to simplify SBOM management and security compliance.&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item><item><title>Big Update to sbomify</title><link>https://sbomify.com/2025/07/04/big-update-to-sbomify/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sbomify.com/2025/07/04/big-update-to-sbomify/</guid><description>&lt;p>Happy 4 July to our US friends.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Today, we are pleased to announce that we have shipped yet another big update to sbomify, version 0.15. This release has two major focuses:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improving the look and feel – and overall experience – of all public pages&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Introducing support for documents in addition to SBOMs&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The latter is especially important because it paves the way toward our ultimate goal: becoming the best open implementation of CycloneDX&amp;rsquo;s Transparency Exchange API (TEA), where documents are first-class citizens.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-are-these-two-features-such-a-big-deal">Why are these two features such a big deal?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Imagine you are a product company. People in the community have told us they want a portal where they can direct users to security artifacts. These artifacts might be SBOMs, but they could also include penetration testing results, FCC or CE certification documents, and many other items.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With this new feature, that is now possible. All you need to do is create a new &amp;ldquo;Component&amp;rdquo; in sbomify and upload your documents there with versioning. If you create a product (such as &amp;ldquo;sbomify&amp;rdquo;) and a project (for example, &amp;ldquo;compliance documents&amp;rdquo;), you can then add a component called &amp;ldquo;FCC Certificates&amp;rdquo; and share those documents by making the relevant components public directly in the user interface.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="a-compliance-hub">A Compliance Hub&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In short, sbomify is evolving into a compliance hub. SBOMs remain important, but they are now just one part of a broader picture. Speaking of SBOMs, we have also exposed our product- and project-level SBOM aggregation download feature to public pages. This means that if you have a project with ten different components—for example, ten different microservices—you can now download an aggregated SBOM that links all of them together using externalReferences in CycloneDX*.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Want a live demo? Check out our &lt;a href="https://app.sbomify.com/public/product/eP_4dk8ixV/">public product page&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>* Note: This is currently available only for CycloneDX, and it assumes your SBOM components are marked as public.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description><category>announcement</category></item></channel></rss>